today today legendary chat
сегодня сегодня легендарный чат
roulette meeting february Thank you very much
рулеточная встреча февраля Я очень спасибо
to everyone who came, everyone who joined that
всем кто пришли все кто присоединился
what
что
we are being bombed by our power plants Yes
нас бомбят наши электростанции Да
was today an arrival day or was yesterday yesterday
сегодня был прилетный или вчера вчера
dav Khmelnytskyi came to us there
дал Хмельницкий был прилет у нас там
too, there is an interruption today, for example with
тоже перебоя вот сегодня например из
ten o'clock in the morning, here I am sitting
десять утра вот здесь где я сижу света
No, but I damn well signed up for different ones
нет но я блин записался разными
the guys are also on different standbys with gadgets
гаджетами ребята тоже на разных резервных
ready in the event of a power outage
готовы В случае выключения света быть
that's why I think we'll do something interesting
да и потому я думаю что мы сделаем интересный
ether so because you are all tired that we are there
эфир так как вы все встали что мы там
I really want to do it with some kind of dibir
с каким-то дибиром очень и хочется
I want a Ukrainian intellectual
хочется украинского интеллектуального
content for those people who will listen to
контента для тех людей, кто наслушат с
other countries, first of all, we will
других стран в первую очередь мы будем
speaks Ukrainian И for
говорит на украинском языке
Ukrainians if you have any
украинцев если у вас будут какие-то
questions that
вопросы которые
what it is
что это такое
right now I have it here
сейчас-теперь Это у меня здесь
now Mr. Andriy
сейчас господин Андрей
we wash for the first time little by little
вымыть впервые мы понемногу
out of all of us, none of us have found everything
из нас всех вообще никто не нашел все
will be covered with a copper groove
накроется медным пазом
We save America, Europe
Америки Европы экономим
in my opinion, Morozenka is the lightest
по-моему Морозенко больше всего света
let's go to him, I will Yes, a little in
поехали к нему я буду Да немножко в
darkness so because I want to draw something
тьме так как я хочу протянуть чем
longer stream I don't know how much of it
дольше стрим Я не знаю насколько его
enough But that's enough
хватит Но хватит да
I agree yes for those from other countries
договорю да для тех кто из других стран
we will communicate in Ukrainian language in
мы будем общаться на украинском языке в
the first one for the Ukrainian audience
первую очень для украинской аудитории
if you have any interesting ones
если у вас будут какие-то интересные
questions and questions can be written in
вопросы к вопросу можно писать в
Telegram channel in We have a channel in
Telegram канал в У нас есть в
the last post about this stream is there
последней там пост об этом стрим там
you can leave questions in the comments
можете в комментариях оставлять вопросы
if you want that your question was answered
если вы хотите что вам вопрос был ответ
in Russian, write что я из
на русском языке да напишите что я из
the other side, for example, is such a Yes, that is
другой стороны например такой Да То есть
you make a question and on the other hand that
делаете вопрос и с другой стороны то
It is so that those who are visiting understand that eh
есть чтобы е-е эти в гости понимали что э-э
you need to answer there not in Ukrainian
нужно вам ответить там не на украинском
because you won't understand at all, so let's go
ибо вы ни фига не поймете итак давайте
Hello everyone, thank you very much for coming
все поздороваемся очень спасибо Что собрались
I think it's pretty interesting to say the least
Я считаю что скажем это довольно интересное
ether And you know what wanted to be provocative
эфир И знаете какие хотел провокационное
question to ask everyone what is the latest book from
вопрос задать всем какую последнюю книгу с
stories you have read
истории вы прочли
and I knew, I knew who was who
и я то знал я то знал то кто какой
not provocative because we are with Mr. Vitaly
не провокационное, потому что мы с паном Виталием
there is a great book about it, maybe another one
об этом классная книга какой то может второй
It's strange that I still don't have such a smart girl
это странная у меня еще нет такого Умничка
He will buy three for himself, but I now have two
На три себе прикупит Да я сейчас два
bought it What is something From the ministry it
купил это Что это что-то От министерства это
the history of civilization is right here at 500
история цивилизации здесь прямо на 500
book pages
страниц книги
to him
к нему
from Russia to closer to the screen so that people
от России до ближе к экрану чтобы люди
saw to the Principality of Galicia
увидели в Галицком княжестве
compiled by Oleksandr Chernenko, history
составитель Александр Черненко история
civilization of Ukraine
цивилизации Украины
Olena Chernenko Damn, I just know
Елена Черненко Блин я просто знаю
Oleksandr Chernenko is right
Александр Черненко это да
and Oleg knowing Olenka Oleg if you look
и Олега зная Аленка Олег если смотришь
congratulations to us so let's find so
нам поздравления так давайте можно так найти
let's start somehow everyone can do something there to people
начнем как-нибудь каждый может каким-то там людям
some wishes, just a kind word will say
какие-то пожелания просто хорошее слово скажет
And here it is now
А вот сейчас
a good word to people is good to people
доброе слово людям хорошо людям хорошо
word
слово
we add to people's health
добавляем людям на здоровье
I can thank Mr. Andrii, thank you
могу поблагодарить вот господин Андрей благодарил что
here we all joined. I thank you for that
вот мы все присоединились Я благодарю за то что
invited gathered I think we will
пригласил собрали Я думаю что мы будем
gather if people like it we will
собираться если людям понравиться будем
to gather regularly and in different it And to
собираться регулярно и в разных это И до
I do this when I open the announcement
кстати я делаю такой уж при открою анонс
Yes, we will also have guests next Saturday
Да у нас следующую субботу тоже будет гости
So we will do it, I won't say who Yes
Так мы сделаем я не буду говорить кто Да
specifically already But we will have an active one
конкретно уже Но у нас будет действующий
evening will be girls bloggers Today we
вечер будут девушки блоггеры Сегодня мы
gathered historians to A next time
собрали историков да А в следующий раз
pick up girls So plan on
знакомиться с девушками, так что планируй
next Saturday, too, two same Do
следующую субботу тоже себе две такие
things one question from which was asked
кстати один вопрос из которых задавали
January Who are you By education
январь Кто ты По образованию
And who among you Who among you are all historians
А кто из вас Кто из вас есть историками все
except me everyone except me I am not a historian For
кроме меня все кроме меня я не историк За
I am not a historian, I say this openly by education
образованием это открыто говорю я не историк Я
I'm just curious
просто интересуюсь да
Kyiv State Pedagogical School
Киевский государственный педагогический
Institute named after Oleksiy Maksymovich
институт имени Алексея Максимовича
Gorky is now a national pedagogic
Горького сейчас национальный педагогический
Drahomanov University Well, me too
университет имени Драгоманова Ну я еще
studied when he was in Gorky
учился когда он Горького был
Christ, Faculty of History, Mr. Zhenya
Христос исторический факультет Женя
Kyiv National University named after
Киевский национальный университет имени
Taras Shevchenko archeology
Тараса Шевченко археология
my manager. And you've already graduated, yes
моим руководителем А ты уже выпустился да
has already been released, but listen to where you are, where you are
уже выпустился а вот Слушай где Ты где Ты
the excavation was the most interesting
на раскопку было самое интересное
the most interesting, well, one of the most interesting can be
самое интересное ну одно из самых интересных можно
to say this
сказать это
Mezyrych Cherkasy Oblast Well there
междуречей Черкасская область Ну там
paleolithic parking lot
палеолитическая стоянка То есть это скупки
mammoth hunters There is literally everything
охотников на мамонтов Там буквально все
with these bones, my mother and I will be sprinkled completely all over
этими костями мама и усеянную полностью вся
these interstices are under these layers. Well, there
эти междуречья он под этими пластами Ну там
precisely because I am digging their parking lots already
именно именно с копирую стоянки их уже
they dug in the 60s-70s or 80s
копали в 60-70-х или 80-х.
how there were so many weak ones there
как там очень такие слабенькие были
research So now they decided to renew and
исследование То теперь решили обновить и
already more thoroughly And at what depth is it
уже тщательнее А на какой глубине оно
lies down
залегает
I'm just not a storyteller, but one
Я просто я же не истории да от одного
once we were asked why there
раз у нас там попросили зачем там
patriotic organization years somewhere
патриотической организации лет где-то
2010-2012 there is such a village as Gubin
2010-2012 есть такое село Губин типа как
the Bolehov principality was like
болеховское княжество было словно
this and that
этот и там
we have Kamianets-Podilskyi University
у нас каменец-подольский университет
he constantly digs these hillforts, but
он там копает постоянно эти городища но
they came across some pottery
они наткнулись на какую-то керамику
It was necessary to help them for 2000 years
2000 лет так и нужно было им помочь
to dig because they didn't have enough people
ибо докопать у них не хватало людей
they dug up there for a short time. Well, I'll say Yes somewhere
там короче выкопали Ну я скажу Да где-то
a meter and a half or a meter exactly a meter exactly
метр-полтора или метр точно метр точно
the depth there was some ancient furnace
глубина там какая печь древняя была
I don't understand some of that, but that one
какие я в том не разбираюсь но тот
the professor told everything. We are shorter
профессор все рассказывал Мы короче
diggers were helping them, it was him, but I
копателями помогали им это его но я
You know what I was thinking. Is it really true?
вот знаете что задумывался Неужели вот действительно
it takes shelter there for 1000-2000 years
там 1000-2000 годов покрывается
so led the layer of soil in different ways
настолько вели слоем почвы по-разному
absolutely it depends Exactly on what
абсолютно это зависит именно от того какие
soils, that is, if there are any sandstones on
почвы есть если какие песчаники на
Sandstones For example, I was like it
песчаники Вот например был я как оно
Vypozoviv Vypozoviv is not far from
Выполз Выполз это недалеко от
there are a lot of shields, well, shields
щитовицы ну шестовицы очень многие
knows
знает
okay, in general, it fell out. That's how they bought it there
ладно В общем выпал Так там скупали
The settlement of the times of Kyivan Rus is it
Городище времен Киевской Руси
was at such a depth that politically
было на такой по глубине, что политически
the parking lot is simply that these sandstones are sand
стоянка просто что эти песчаники Пески
they overtook the sand over the centuries
они за столетие нагнали ну песок
constantly if the wind works the wind and so
постоянно если бы ветер работа ветра и так
then they caught up that it is deeper than
дальше они нагнали что оно глубже
should be ie In some places there
должно быть есть На одних местах там
somehow it can be at a depth in general
как-то может быть на глубине вообще
half a meter, maybe less here and on others
полметра вот может и меньше здесь, а на других
3 m and 5 and As many as you want Well, that is, here it is
3 м и 5 и Сколько хочешь Ну то есть здесь это
absolutely different
по-разному абсолютно
but what what you what you let's go
а вот чего вы вот вы Давайте к
tell historians what you decided to become
историков скажи чего вы решили стать
historians, exactly what prompted you to do the same
историками именно что вас подвигло это же
history at school history is the same
история в школе история – это такая жесть
I was not interested that it was just a slipper
была не интересна что просто [ __ ]
It's to whom like yes yes I Later I at all
Это кому как да да я Впоследствии я вообще
did not study well at school Well, relatively speaking
плохо учился в школе Ну да относительно
but I was interested in the story, even though
но история мне было интересно хотя тоже в
school was somehow not going well A, but in general
школе как-то не очень шло А но в общем
interesting. I don't know. We have a damn school
интересно Не знаю У нас в школе блин
history was the only thing ancient of the world
история была единственная что древняя мира
it would be interesting if I was a small sixth grader
интересно было бы я был малый шестой класс
There were cards there, there were some cheers to put out
Там карты были эти там какие-то ура тушить
there you watch A in high school somehow
там смотришь А в старших классах как-то
it was so zazubrita shorter such dates
оно было так зазубрите короче такие даты
Such dates are inevitable. What do you think?
как вы считаете
modern school history it is correct
современная школьная история она правильно
built teaching Is it tin
построена преподавание Или это жесть
it's literally here I'm the only one with
это буквально здесь я один только из
school history I have a connection This is tin
школьной истории имею связь Это жесть
and what should be changed in this gesture so that it
а что нужно изменить в этой жесте чтобы она
began to change everything, for example, the entire concept
стала менять все например всю концепцию
children do not need any education there at the town hall
образования не надо детям никакие там в ратуше
Murartu, that is, there are some central ones
мурарту то есть есть какие-то центральные
topics around which it is necessary to develop
темы Вокруг которых нужно развивать
the critical thinking of patriotism is still there
критическое мышление патриотизма еще там
something A to learn how
что-то А учить как
higher educational institutions of history
высших учебных заведениях истории
Homer and Dreiser all countries it
Гомера и Драйзера все страны оно
no one needs absolutely all of this
никому не нужна абсолютно это все
I will say the same with our textbooks
я скажу так вот с нашими учебниками
as we had in 10-11 grade The truth is still there
как у нас была в 10-11 классе Правда есть еще
I studied at the end of 1997 and 1998
учился кончается был 97 98-й год это
such nausea was somehow there just there
такая тошнота была как-то вот там просто вот
teaches teaches all dates so then when I
учит учить все даты да потом когда я
it has already become cold for me to install it myself
уже стал студеном мне самому установить
in different schools everywhere is some kind of [ __ ]
в разных школах повсюду какая-нибудь фигня
Much depends on the teacher
от учителя Многое зависит
just wanted to say that it all depends on
только хотел сказать что все зависит от
I had a teacher. Well, it was different too
учителя у меня Ну тоже было по-разному
different
разном
Well, I think I'm the only one
Ну я Мне кажется я как раз только
thanks to the teacher, he started quite quickly
благодаря учителю довольно быстро начал
to fanaticize the history of the history, that is, I have to
фанатиты истории истории то есть у меня к
I don't know this very quickly. And you say
этого очень быстро такое не знаю И говорите
It's not interesting. No, I don't understand that. He asks here
Не интересно Нет я такую ​​не понимаю Здесь спрашивает
The central figure in the school only
Центральная фигура в школе только
the administration does not know about it in general
администрация об этом не знаю в общем вся
problem
проблема
see Anna writes bloggers chat do not read
смотрите Анна пишет блоггеры чат не читай
watch the chat that is on YouTube sooner than
смотрите тот чат, который в Ютубе скорее
all can read can read
все могут прочитать можете прочитать
Yes
да
I'm reading the chat Well, I'm already like that
я читаю чат Ну я вот мне уже да
looks at me good question I would on
смотрит на меня хороший вопрос Я бы на
I will answer it now. See if you
него отвечу сейчас Смотрите если вы
you want the questions not to be missed
хотите чтобы вопрос не пропустили
leave your question in Telegram like this
оставляйте ваш вопрос в телеграмме так в
I am dropping the last telegram
телеграмме в под последние вот я сбрасываю
the message on your Telegram is the last one there
послание на свой Telegram там последний
the post is about today's stream in it
пост – это о сегодняшнем стриме в нем
ask questions Let's me and what about you
задавайте вопросы Давайте я и что уж ты
I saw a cool question for myself Come on, you can
увидел классный вопрос себе Давай можешь
to answer him But here Vladyslav asks
его ответить Но тут Владислав спрашивает
Can bloggers tell me where and how
могут ли господин блоггеры сказать где и у
which documents are written exactly in quotation marks
каких документах написано именно в кавычках
the state of Ukraine, I can't say where
держа Украина я не могу сказать где
written by the state of Ukraine, I assume that
написано государство Украина я предполагаю что
we are already talking about the days of the UNR going on there
уже речь идет о сутках УНР там речь идет
about a state called Ukraine, but this
о государстве с названием Украина, но это
more to Mr. Vitaly And where it is written
больше к господину Виталию А где написано
the country is Ukraine, that's y
страна - Украина так это у
Alberto canceled
Альберто отмена
envoy of the Venetian Republic to
посланец венецианской республики в
Bohdan Khmelnytskyi is written there
Богдан Хмельницкий там написан
their country is called that's where I read it
страна их называется ну там я читал
the Russian translation of their country
русском переводе страна их
called Ukraine in the time of Bohdan
называется Украина времена Богдана
Khmelnytskyi Therefore, everything is simple
Хмельницкого Поэтому все просто а вот
come on, we all expect specialists
давайте раз мы все ожидаем специалистов
question I would like to buy this capital
вопрос Я хотел бы покупать это капитально
I would like Yes I would like this Well I found it
я хотел бы Да я хотел бы этот Ну нашел
Taras Chuhlib Can I still confuse and
Тарас Чухлеб Может я еще спутаю и
sure unsure maybe
уверен неуверенный возможно
Buchatsky Peace Treaty I am not sure
Бучачский мирный договор Я не уверен
is it valid but
или он действителен
1700 o
1700 ой
This is exactly what he found in the Polish archives
Именно это он нашел в польских архивах
it seems that it is actually written in Ukrainian
вроде бы там написано действительно Украинский
state
государство
something like that Well, I'm not sure about it
что-то такое вот Ну я не уверен в его
Well, then he's real. Here's a little bit for you
Ну тогда он настоящий Вот вам немножко
later Khmelnytskyi is already Ukrainian
позже Хмельницкого уже украинский
the state is also the third in the portrait itself
государство также третье на портрете самого
Bohdan Khmelnytskyi's portrait of Gondius
Богдана Хмельницкого портрет гондиуса
there is already a normal portrait and there is
там уже есть портрет нормальный а есть
the portrait is humorous when it is boring
портрет юмористический, когда он ослиный
we ears there made and so on And there
мы ушами там сделан и так далее И там
it is written that the leader of the Ukrainian country is there
написано что вождь украинской там страны
Ukraine seems to have something like that
Украина что-то такое вот но кажется
written in Latin something like ne ohlos a
написано латино что-то типа не охло
lebis
лебис
of the Ukrainian people
украинского народа
we now have a little on the then
на тогдашнем у нас сейчас немного
negative
отрицательное
This is Leps from the Roman People, I did not gather you
это Лепс из Римской Народ я вас собрал не
just a story, namely chat roulette players
просто историю а именно чат рулеточников
yes, that's the question. And who rolled how?
да вот такой вопрос А кто как докатился
to this life What entered the roulette chat And
до этой жизни Зашедшие в чат рулетку И
decided to take up this difficult task
решили вот заниматься это нелегкой
business
делом
who's the first Let's roll like this
кто первый Давайте я докатился таким
as I found out too late
образом что я поздно перед этим узнал
in general, it's 4 taka for me. It must be something
вообще для меня 4 такая это Вероятно что-то
there was something like this for ages. Well, no
было веками было что-то такое отходное
I know, I don't look at anyone at all
знаю вообще есть на это не смотрю никого
nothing, and then somehow it happened by accident
ничего а потом как-то так попал случайно
I don't remember who the first one might be
там не помню на кого первого возможно
it was a zombie, maybe it was January
это был зомбоящик возможно это был январь
maybe it was Luhansk, but I'm sure
возможно это был Луганский ну я точно
I remember that I decided to do this with
помню что решил я этим заниматься с
the moment when I saw the video in January
того момента, когда увидел в январе видео
with some kind of nedobolgerom Separ Yakyk
с каким-то там недоболгером сепаром
said that This is how if such as January
говорил что Вот как если таких как январь
there will be more, then we will have problems and
будет больше то у нас будут проблемы и
also saw the video Yes in history everyone
еще также видели видео Да в истории все
Mr. Vitaly and I were just there
там было как раз господин Виталий я и
stereo decor for the video where they are too
стерео декора за видео где они также
discussed this topic that is needed somehow
обсуждали эту тему что нужно как-то
well, try to popularize it more
ну стараться больше популяризировать именно
such historical moments because really
такие исторические моменты потому что действительно
very poorly educated, it seems to me
очень слабо признанным Мне кажется
now even Ukrainian and Russian and
сейчас даже и украинский и русский и
and others in principle Well, somehow
и другие в принципе Ну как-то да
Can you tell me abbreviated and concise?
мне рассказать сокращенно кратко ли можно
if it's short
если сжато то
I had opened me at all
было у меня открыл меня вообще
the desire has been there for a long time because I have a channel
желание давно есть потому что я у меня канал
created since 2018, just me and
создан еще с 2018 года просто я
the desire was there even earlier, just me already
желание было еще раньше просто я уже
actively began to lead before I had
активно вести начал раньше у меня было
the desire to do something even earlier
желание что-то делать еще раньше
full-scale war I wanted to be
полномасштабной войны Мне хотелось быть
somehow involved in this, but I am like that
как-то задействованным в этом, но я так
I thought, I can't do anything, I don't know anything
подумал я ничего не умею ничего не знаю
what can I do And I loved watching
что что я могу делать И я любил смотреть
chat roulette is also a separate story like me
чат рулетку это тоже отдельная история как я
came across it
на это наткнулся
here and at one point I started to come across
вот и в один момент я начал наталкиваться
on historical videos Well, the history is a long time ago
на исторические видео Ну историю давно
I am interested, but I also have some videos
интересуюсь но и некоторые видео у меня
jaw dropped from how much
отвисала челюсть от того, насколько
I imagined the story on On in a different way
по-другому я представлял себе историю
There were interesting historical videos on TV
тв были интересные видео исторические именно из
I was interested in documents
документами меня интересовали документы
the history of Russia is a channel where everything is exclusive
история России канал где исключительно все
dedicated to the documents and I decided that this
посвящено документам и я решил что это
you can use whatever is in the roulette format
можно задействовать в формате рулетки
there are many bloggers who are engaged in roulette
многие блогеры занимающиеся рулеткой
but I don't see anyone in this format
но в таком формате Я никого не вижу
so that in terms of history they are
чтобы именно вот в плане истории они
strong-willed, they try hard
сильнейшие винисты они сильно пытаются
humiliate the Ukrainian nation there and everything
унизить там украинскую нацию и все
such Well I thought what can I do with it
такое Ну я подумал что я могу с этим
fight if I prepare a little and that's it
бороться если Я немножко подготовлюсь и вот с
In 2018, I created a channel, but not actively
2018 я создал канал но активно не
I was thinking all these things in my head
вел я это набирал в голову эти все
documents, all this knowledge, somewhere, something
документы эти все знания где-то где-то
I was reading somewhere, watching something, and that's how I came
читал где-то смотрел и так вот пришел
before this
до этого
My situation is similar to Nikita's, I am too
у меня похоже на Никиты ситуацию я тоже
started with bloggers in Luhansk Karpov
начинал с блоггеров в Луганский Карпов
It is popular there very directly But guys
там популярна очень на прямом Но ребята
reasonable, but there was a historical fact
толковый но исторический фактаж был
weak I think But what is that? Well, guys
слабенький думаю Да что же такое Ну ребята
as if I can speak and tell a story
вроде бы я отрекать и умеют рассказывать а
historical fact is such a romance
исторический фактаж какой-то романтика
the middle of the 19th century
середины XIX века назад нужно себе
to get into this business And so into the forest
влезть в это дело Да так и в лес
oh look
о смотрите
Glory be to whom it is purely our Freedom
Славься кого на это чисто наша Свободы
shout autumn And this means that we
кричат ​​осень А это значит что мы
dragged out. Look, I'm saying that Russia is hitting on
протянули Видите я говорю что Россия бьет по
our substations here and there with ten
наших подстанциях тут вот здесь с десятой
there was no light in the morning. I typed these here
утра не было света Я набрал здесь этих
generators so that we can stretch it and we
генераторов чтобы мы протащили и мы
stretched so that everyone is very, very grateful
протянули так что всем очень-очень Спасибо
that's cool cool
это круто круто
I wanted to say this in our chat
я хотел бы это сказать у нас в чате вот
it is interesting, but put a plus is By education
интересно вот поставьте плюс есть По образованию
a historian or a history teacher or
историком да или учитель истории или
historian, yes, put a plus sign so that we
историк да поставьте плюсик чтобы мы
saw this so good question
увидели этот так вот хороший вопрос
left
оставляли
the problem and awareness of the principle
проблему и осознание принципиальной
positions between history and propaganda as
позиции между историей и пропагандой как
everyone realizes it for themselves or is possible
каждый осознает это для себя можно ли
sacrifice the facts to the historical
приносить факты в жертву историческому
myths
мифов
nothing depends
зависит ничего
if we are talking about historical science, then no
если речь идет об исторической науке, то нет
if we are talking about propaganda about
если речь идет о пропаганде о
in a positive sense the word and simplification
в положительном смысле слово и упрощение
you understand that this is already a simplification
это же понимаете приносить уже упрощение
this is already a sacrifice
это уже принесение в жертву
such historical details, but
таких исторических каких-то достоинств но
you can't teach history in general
ты не можешь излагать историю в целом
for the general consumer is not simplified in
для широкого потребителя не упрощено в
precision in a scientific form, therefore I
точности в научном виде поэтому я
I think so
считаю что да
2 minutes I'll switch now
2 минутки Я переключу сейчас
on reserve, shorter on normal power supply
на резервное короче на нормальное питание
during this time you can read
за это время можно почитать
Your opinion is nationalistic
ваше мнение какие националистические
there are organizations other than the oun itself
организации кроме самого оуна есть
I am not the successor of the OUN and the UPA, including me
преемником ОУН и УПА в том числе я не
I think there are some successors
думаю что есть какие-то преемники
it was an organization of its time and yes
это была организация в свое время и так
exists to this day
существует по сегодняшний день
successors a month ago someone there
преемники месяц назад кого-то там
Nobody was elected as the new head of the Sumy region at night
выбрали новым председателем ночью Сумщины Никто
does not know about it
об этом так не знает
so the organization does not have such success
да организация не имеют такого успеха
I already think OUNTE and OUN are modern - they are
уже я думаю оунте и ОУН современное – это есть
I don't even know how
примерно как вот даже не знаю что как вот
Russia and Russia are like them so much because it is
Русь и России это как они настолько потому что это
opposites after all And this is like Cossacks
противоположности все-таки А это как казачество
then the Cossacks are modern
тогда и казачество современное это
so I want to convey that I saw her to Evchatika
так хочу передать видел евчатку ее
Roman Mykolaiv Yes, you are a historian by education
Роман Николаев Да ты По образованию историк
I have known my brother for a very long time
Мой знакомый собрат очень давно если бы мы
acquaintances, yes, greetings, yes, questions
знакомы так поздравительным так вопрос
Let's go right away. So, who advises what
А давайте сразу Так вот кто что советует
to read to people because they asked a lot
почитать людям потому что много спрашивали Вот с
what to start, but you don't know how to do it
чего начать но не так знаете как для
historians And so far as for the average
историков А так куда как для обычной
a person who does not understand anything about this
человека, который нифига в этом не понимает
this is to Mr. Vitaly
это к господину Виталию
I would start with Natalia Yakovenko's history
Я бы стартовал с Натальи Яковенко истории
The Ukrainian book is a little old, but
Украина книга немножко древняя но
written by Zhivenka And in general, like everyone else
написана живенькая А вообще как всем
I advise the gate of Europe Serhiy Plakhia This
советую ворота Европы Сергея плахия Это
the latest that is the latest that came out
последнее что есть самое последнее что получилось
it is from Serhiy Yekelchyk of the history of Ukraine
это у Сергея екельчика истории Украины
but she doesn't speak English yet
но она англоязычная она пока не
translated I haven't read A myself yet
переведена Я еще сам не читал А
a bad start is normal
стартовать плохие нормально
Well, I don't know, there is a whole collection there
Ну и я не знаю там есть целый сборник там
a story without censorship is called chic
история без цензуры называется шикарная
collection to me I like me ot v
сборник мне Мне нравится я вот в
principi taka recommended I read
принципе такая рекомендовал Я читал
small book saw this book P
маленькой книжечки увидел эту книгу П
Vitaly among recommended I her once
Виталия среди рекомендовано я ее когда-то
read Ukrainian nationalism Ukrainian
читал украинские национализм украинский
nationalism a short history course
национализм краткий курс истории
Ukraine, she is short, she is small, she is
Украина она коротка она маленькая она
how quickly the notebook goes is quite interesting
как блокнотик быстро идет довольно интересная
It's cool, and I'll add something from myself
Прикольно и от себя добавлю что вот мне
Somehow books like so and so didn't come in
как-то не заходили книги вот так вот
briefly about everything about the whole story
кратко обо всей истории
tells me it started to procrastinate
рассказывает мне начало откладываться
when I'm on narrow documents somewhere
когда я именно по узким документам где-то
I found documents and this document
вот я находил документы и этот документ
is impressed, then it is better to give
впечатается тогда лучше дать
memorable You can even give
незабываемый Вы можете даже подарить
remember. For example, you are reading
запоминать Вот например ты читаешь
something there It would seem something like that
какую-то там Казалось бы что-то такое какая-то
there is a customs statement, there is this one
там выписка таможена там этим этот
the list is there at the Vitebsk customs office
перечень там на витебской таможне
checkpoint and there is a list of who passed through it and what
заставе и там лично кто проходил ее что
what truck, what goods, and it seems to be the same Well
что воз какой товар И кажется это же Ну
of course a person will not remember but through
конечно человек не запомнит но через
what is written there, for example, that he is a Muscovite
то что там написано например что москаль
there Bogdanovich Moskal carriage there in
там богданович москаль повёз там в
The Grand Duchy of Lithuania
Великое княжество литовское то то Тото и
when they ask you And what is it
когда тебя уже спросят А что такое
Moscow, you know what it is because you can
москаль ты знаешь что это ты можешь
show historical documents and so If
показать исторические документы а так Если
you will read a short definition somewhere
ты прочтешь где-то определение короткое в
which in some book Well, I don't like it
которому в какой-то книге Ну оно мне не Да
I remembered a specific document
запомнилось как конкретно документ
or, for example, the country Ukraine In the document
или, например, страна Украина В документе
during the time of Bohdan Khmelnytskyi, you know what
времен Богдана Хмельницкого ты знаешь что
it was written then and you already know when
это написано тогда и все ты уже знаешь когда
the word Ukraine appeared in the sense of
появилось слово Украина в значении с
country in relation to our territory
страны по отношению к нашей территории
to our territory, but immediately like this
к нашей территории, а вот сразу такое
questions are often asked in the chat room, there are Tsi
вопросы вот в чат рулете часто вот там Эти
Muscovites are saying something there
[ __ ] там что-то там говорят там
Novgorod, these are their own myths, how are you?
Новгород вот эти их свои мифы вот Как вы
think when you poke them with something
думаете когда вы им тыкаете каким-то
document as much as it is for them
документом насколько для них это
convincingly I wild document I I with
убедительно я дичу документ я Я из
because he told me at the very beginning
с самого начала говорил мне в начале
you can already get me a little in the comments
меня немножко в комментариях уже доставать
even at first it's like you're explaining them there
даже нача что будто ты им объясняешь там
It's almost like Stop it because they don't
Типа чуть ли не прекращает объясняет потому что они не
I have already tried to many people
дойдет Я я уже сколько людям пытался
explain I didn't, I started It's not for
объяснить Я же не я же начинал Это не для
them and never set myself the goal of something in
них и никогда не ставил своей целью что-то в
them to change I started it with clear
их изменить я начинал это с четким
realizing that I cannot fix them, I do
осознанием что их не исправить я делаю
it is interesting for Ukrainians, Ukrainians and I
это для украинцев украинцам интересно и я
wanted Ukrainians to be interested and to
хотел чтобы украинцам было интересно и чтобы
Ukrainians learned something from me
что-то украинцы узнавали у меня
my jaw dropped and I decided to share
отвисала челюсть и я решил поделиться
it may be the same for others
этим с другими может кому-то так же будет
interesting here only for this Only for
интересно вот только для этого Только для
Ukrainians, I did it
украинцев я это делал
by the way, I also emphasize very often
я кстати тоже очень часто подчеркиваю
many people say that to me, what are you to him A
многие мне так говорят чего ты ему А
what's there Just what you will tell him I say
что там Толку что ты ему расскажешь Я говорю
what is this frame that comes across to me
что вот этот кадр который мне попадается
I don't care about it. I use it
мне пофиг на него Я его использую
as a material for filming so That is, we are on
как материал для съемки да То есть мы по
in fact, on finding some kind of evidence yes or no
сущности на находом какого-то упрека да за
with its help we make educational
помощью него делаем обучающий
exhibit
экспонат
which is then watched by thousands and hundreds
который смотрят потом тысячи и сотни
thousands And for them there is just this product of I
тысяч И вот для них есть как раз этот продукт Я
by the way, they often write to you like this or
кстати часто вам е-е такое пишут или
there in the comments or come across
там в комментах или попадаются в
on the fourth I watched you and for example
четвертом я вас смотрел и например
I understood something for myself, there is such a thing
что-то там понял для себя вот есть такое
Of course, from the side of the Russians, is he a Ukrainian?
Конечно со стороны россиян Или украинец
Russians Russians from Russians I don't remember is in
россиян россияне из россиян не помню есть в
I have even met a lot
меня есть Даже встречал очень много
meetings I meet with Russia subscribers
встреч встречаю с Россией подписчиков
Russia is absolutely normal, say the ladies and
Россия абсолютно нормально говорят дамы и
look there
смотрим там
I see that, I have seen many Russians
я такое вижу я многих видел россиян
who said yes, I'm looking at you, that is
которые говорили так я тебя смотрю ты то есть
they are adequate but they are adequate with
они адекватны но они адекватны с
from the very beginning And so that I could change someone
самого начала А так чтобы я кого изменил
and some saw wrote to me about it
и мне об этом написали какого-то увидел
This has never happened to me. For example
мне такое не случалось мне Например
very much very I forgot can
очень много очень Я забыл может
it was something even less than
было ну это это что-то даже меньше чем
statistically error I work mainly
статистически погрешность Я работаю в основном
on the very stops, that is, they are me
на самых упорах то есть они меня
sexual and [ __ ] type When they eat
переполоть и беся типа Когда им
shows silver And they say No, that's not all
показывает серебряный А они говорят Нет то все
fakes, that's when you show them 10,000 now
фейки вот то когда им 10 000 сейчас покажешь
they still change a little and already
они все-таки немного меняют и уже
next time don't shout, that is, they
следующий раз не кричат ​​ну то есть они
that's how they look. Well, well, there's no way
так смотрят такие Ну да ну типа там нет
Well, it's controversial, you know how
ну там это спорно это знаете это как
unequivocally
однозначно
someone wrote there in the comments for questions
кто-то там в комментариях для вопросов писал
tell Morozenka that he's done enough
скажите Морозенко, что он уже задолбил
show a coin, let's do something else Yes
показывать монету давай уже что-то другое Да
Yes, yes, those are from a jug. Maybe if they write it down
да да такие из кувшин Может если бы это пишут
What is the name of the channel where Yes in headphones
Как называется канал где Да в наушниках
it is called box varitake with Voice
оно называется бокс варитаке с голосом
it's true, my channel is January channel eh
правда мой канал январь канал е-е
now I choose yours
сейчас я вот я выбираю как раз ваши
I am sending the link now to everyone in the chat
ссылку сейчас я сбрасываю всем если бы в чат
a long time ago
издавна
By the way, we congratulate grandfather in headphones
Кстати поздравляем деда в наушниках он
I have already scored a hundred thousand and passed 100 thousand
набрал уже сто тысяч преодолел 100 жмет
border On this and on YouTube, yes
рубеж На этом и на Ютубе да да
please put
поставьте пожалуйста
pros who greets And now I will be yours
плюсики кто приветствует И сейчас я вам стану
channels Yes, but questions for now
каналы Да да а пока вопрос
here is also a question for everyone, why don't you
вот тоже вопрос ко всем Почему вы не
tell me which territory of Ukraine
говорите ручные какой территории Украины
were given in exchange for the Crimea, I did not
были отданы в обмен за Крым я так и не
understood in short there was no territory
понял короче ни одной территории не было
given in exchange for Crimea, it's a fake, it's a fake
отдано в обмен за Крым это фейк это фейк
does the exchange of territories end or in
обмен территориями заканчивается или в
On the 25th, Zhenya was already there, knowing more precisely
25-му там уже Женя более точно зная в
20 there in the 6th year when Taganrog is not there yet
20 там 6-м году когда там Таганрог еще не
they also gave somewhere in the area of ​​the trip there
отдали и где-то в районе путешествие там
exchanged This is the first half of the 20s
обменяли Это первая половина 20-х годов
as far as I remember Well yes Yes there is some
насколько я помню Ну да Да там какая-нибудь
such tegane of he referred exactly
такие тегане оф он относился именно
first to
сначала до
Ukrainian Soviet War Well, yes
Украинской Советской войны Ну да
Soviet, then yes, and then none
советской потом да а потом его никаких
of territory exchanges in the 54th year, the last
обменов территории 54-м году последний
the exchange of territories is 51 years from Poland
обмен территориями это 51 год из Польши
there, Taganrog was given instead of Crimea, yes
там Таганрог отдали да вместо Крыма да
Taganrog moved to the first half of the 20s
Таганрог удалил первую половину 20-х
25 or 26 years old. Well, I'm sure
лет еще 25 или 26-й Ну я же говорю я точно
not able to remember good question yes
не способен помню хороший вопрос да
Maksym Grunyk asks what can be read
Максим груник спрашивает, что можно почитать
cover these Rurik from the old Norman
покрыть эти Рюрика из старой Норманнской
theories
теории
the question is what can be read by
вопрос о том, что можно почитать по
reality
реальности
Well, see Russian modern myths and
ну смотрите русский современный мифы и
their state is built on that as
их государства да построен на том как
they attach themselves to Russia, which was there
они себя приплетают к Руси что был там
Old Ladogam Novgorod is later shortened to these
Старый Ладогамский Новгород позднее сократили до них.
the Swedes are there, the Varangians, the Normans. Who are they?
шведы типа там варяги Норманны Кто они
had come to Kyiv, and that's how it is now
были пришли в Киев и вот так и теперь
Moscow has some pretensions to Russia
Москве имеют это какие-то предъявления на Русь
I have an answer to that. There is even no
у меня есть на это ответ Даже есть не
prehistoric and even if we assume this
доисторика и даже если предположить эту
the whole Norman theory in such an old one
всю Нормандскую теорию в таком старом
in such a form that Rurik came first
таком виде пришедший рюрик сначала
in this kingdom somewhere near Novgorod
в эту власть там где-то у Новгорода
then went down the Dnieper. But they are here
потом спустился по Днепру А они ведь здесь
what did the Scandinavian ethnics come to
к чему ну пришли скандинавы этнические
the ancestors of the Swedes and then descended well
предки шведов а потом спустились ну
sat there for a while somewhere on the lap a
посидели какое-то время там где-то на ладу а
then they went down to Kyiv and the wholesaler said Well
потом спустились в Киев и опт сказал Ну
Therefore, Kyiv will be the mother of Russian cities
будет Киев матерью городов русских Тому
what would be good here Everything is economical here
что здесь если бы хорошо Здесь все экономично
slaves can be traded profitably and
выгодно рабами можно торговать и
After all, why are you here? He sat down
все-таки вы здесь к чему ну Посидел он
there for six months or a year or two years there on
там полгода или род или два года там на
and then all of them came down
ладушки а потом спустились и все их
founded the Scandinavian state
основали государство скандина основали
states in the modern territories of Ukraine where
государств на современных территориях Украины где
here is a Muscovite in this this
здесь московик в этом этом
Rurik let them watch Igor Danylevsky
Рюрика пусть смотрят Игоря Данилевского
they read theirs and everything is clearly written there
своего и читают, а там все написано четко
and it is clear, if already from a scientific point of view
и ясно если уж с научной точки зрения то
there is a separate story so I dropped the channels
там отдельной истории так скинул каналы
guests in Telegram and now is it possible
гостей в телеграмм и сейчас можно ли
defeat the Russians only with the truth of the Russians
победить россиян только правдой россиян
you can win with a bullet
можно победить шаром
I recommend this method, look, I know what
рекомендую такой способ смотри я знаю что
we do not agree with you because
мы тебя не согласны потому что
how many balls do we need if we don't
сколько шаров нужно так если мы не будем
use the word because I said
использовать слово как я говорил
Trotsky once yes these at least like him
троцкий когда-то да по крайней мере как ему
attribute that the times there were civil
приписывают что времена там гражданской
war, one agitator is worth several there
войны один агитатор стоит там нескольких
divisions And that is, I always also bring it up
дивизий А есть и я всегда тоже привожу
example if we don't work with
пример если мы не будем работать с
their brain with their consciousness yes that
их мозгом с их сознанием да то
there will be new and new hordes of mobs
будут все новые и новые эти орды мобиков
Yes, and if there is already a prisoner there
Да А если уж там гоп уже зеки до
They don't go to Wagner because they watched it somewhere
Вагнера не идут, потому что где-то там насмотрелись
the news was already shorter somewhere
новости да не слушались где-то уже короче
mobilization
мобилизация
how to properly show how to properly
как правильно показать как правильно
convey tipa this So I believe that
донести типа этот Так что я считаю что
fully i partially
полностью я частично
I agree that what is optical is possible
согласен что такое оптические к тому что можно
I agree that it is necessary to influence them
на них повлиять я согласен что надо
to fight with words, but the word is directed at
воевать словом но слово направлено на
I don't have more Ukrainians, so it's not
украинцев больше я так значит это не
one must exceed one's role in history How
нужно превысить свою роль в истории Как
Comrade Lenin said. As Tsey said
говорил товарищ Ленин Как говорил Этот
how is it
как оно
Classic Yes, what about yuzyuls and the Good Word
Классик Да Что с юзюлями и Добрым словом
you can do much more than simple
можно сделать гораздо больше чем просто
kind words with one kind word you are
добрые слова одним Добрым словом ты
you won't do anything if the colts are good there
ничего не сделаешь аколь там кольты хорошо
the word it is already this has a much better effect
слово гораздо лучше влияет это уже это
it's already our way to throw away like some
уже по-нашему вот сбросить Как некоторые
yes, three channels of our boys
да три канала наших ребят
And I'm sorry, you can now
А я это я извиняюсь можно сейчас
connect because you have a camera
подключиться потому что имеясь камеры
connect Yes now a second Oh how
подключиться Да сейчас секунду О как
related 30-year war and rebellion
связано 30-летняя война и восстание
I don't have the Khmelnytsky question at all
Хмельницкого вопроса Я вообще не
I understand what this is about
понимаю о чем это
Well, how is 300 connected?
Ну как связано 300 никак не
connected Strictly speaking
связана Собственно говоря
1,600 What is the end of 1,648 means
1600 Который Ну закончилась 1 648 значит
18 to 48
18-го по 48
Oh, this is the first of one of the world's first
Ой это первая из одной из первых мировых
I don't even remember the wars in Europe there
войн в Европе там даже не помню
when Khmelnytsky fought there in my opinion
когда воевал Хмельницкий по-моему там
fought or the cadets have such a legend that
воевал ли у юнкерки есть такая легенда что
he fought there
он там воевал
not that it was directly somehow
не так чтобы она напрямую была как-то
associated with the uprising
связана с восстанием
they ask Pavel Stryletsky a question
спрашивают Павел Стрелковый вопрос
the question of two sviridates How do you like it?
вопросы двух свиридетесов Как вам
manages to keep his nerves as
удается сохранять свои нервы как
communication with Russians is also possible for me Yes
общение с россиянами мне тоже есть Да
I teach only what I do not dig
я же преподаю только то где я не рою
I keep them where you keep them, that's not it
храню там где их материешь такое не
I teach it, but you can't teach it. And there is
преподаю это же нельзя преподавать А есть
such that you would like to teach but there
такое что вы бы хотели преподавать но там
they left her so much shorter
столько короче матов ее оставили
torture the earth
замучить земли
of course, all of us people teach in
конечно все мы люди выкладывайте в
telegram channel Well, well
telegram-канал Да ну
something in Telegram something on Patreon And where What
кое-что в телеграмм кое-что на патреон А где Что
Does not teach me some things that
Не излагает у меня некоторые есть вещи что
simply Hands do not reach that So in
просто Руки не доходят до того
I have actually I have a stock of videos because
меня есть на самом деле У меня есть запас видео бо
I also recorded videos from the 18th year onwards
я еще записывал видео что с 18-го года и в
I have such shots there, I will think so V
меня есть там такие кадры я так подумаю В
I am a real person, a real person
меня реально человек реально человек
record with a person who is absolutely serious
запись с человеком который абсолютно серьезно
told me for about an hour about
рассказывала мне где-то около часа о
Reptileoid procontactors, which of them are I
репетилоидов проконтактюров какие из них я
I honestly say that there is a person who likes me
я честное слово говорю есть человек который мне
seriously told I tried Well there
серьезно рассказывала я старался Ну там
I will post this video, it's a pity that I have
я выложу это видео это же Жаль что у меня
there was no tinfoil cap. This is like him
шапочки из фольги не было Это это как он
he is like that, there is such a thing there
такой он кобо от есть там такой да
I also got it, yes, it's been a long time
попадал мне тоже так да это давно уже
recorded
записано
all
все
why does Vox without a flag ask What are you?
почему Вокс без флага да спрашивает Чего вы
do not hang the flag
не вешаете флаг
I used to hang up, then take off, Lord Yes
я когда-то вешал потом снимал Господи Да
I ask why Mr. Vitaly became noticeably rarer
спрашиваю почему п Виталий стал заметно реже
release your videos
выпускать свои видео
Well, I would not like to talk about this topic
Ну, я бы не хотел на эту тему говорить
got bored I, too, less often and we all have them
задолбались Я я тоже реже и всем У нас есть
life apart from We don't sit all day
жизнь кроме Мы же не сидим целыми днями
digging these videos We have some BTW
копаем эти видео У нас есть какие-то Кстати
it hurts, you know one of the main questions
болит знаете один из главных вопросов
it was January. Let's stream when they come
было январь Давай стрим когда будут
do you stream or don't you stream there is such a thing
стримы или не делаешь стримы есть такое
there is a desire such a desire is an idea
желание есть такое желание есть идеи
But
Но
I entered your Telegram channels there
у тебя в Telegram каналы зашел там
they are almost making a revolution there, come on
революцию там чуть не делают давай
stream let's stream stream January stream
стрим давай сдерживаем стрим январь стрим
And if anything, this Morozenko takes a long time
А если да что-то этот Морозенко долго берет
this
этот
readjusts the camera light he has there
перенастраивает камеру свет у него там
something
что-то
Yes
да
some [ __ ] How much time do you spend
какое фигня Сколько времени вы проводите
I rarely spend trolleys a day
уже троллейцы в день я провожу редко
but when I already go in, it's three two three
но когда уже захожу то три две три
four hours
четыре часа
question to everyone in the 96th year of Chornobyl
вопрос ко всем 96-му году Чорновил
Tanyuk and others launched the Nuremberg project
танюк и другие запустили проект Нюрнберг
There are two places where the totalitarian regime was tried
Есть два места, где судили тоталитарный режим
CPRS, do you know something about it or can you
КПСС знаете ли вы что-нибудь об этом или можете
I'm the first to hear about it
рассказать я первый слышу об этом
something was like that, but it's something
что-то было такое, но ну это какая-то
public was public such yes
общественная была общественная такая да
initiative
инициатива
it probably did not gain wide publicity
она, видимо, не получила широкой огласки
By the way, at the expense of the Russians
Кстати еще на счет российских
historical myths are very often in them besides
исторических мифов очень часто у них кроме
the one there that Alya Rurik dreams of the city Yes there is
того там что Аля рюрик снов города Да есть
such that there was a Rus with a Kiwi center
такое что вот была Русь с центром киви а
then
потом
Vladimirska became shorter somewhere there
стала короче где-то там Владимирская
the essence and that's what it is. Yes, yes
сущность и вот когда такое Да да
specifically, in which year, who, how, who did it
конкретно В какой год кто Как кто сделал
this transfer before that was Kyiv and here
этот перенос вот до этого был Киев а тут
and then the decree and moved there to these
и далее указ и переместились там в эти
zadrypanski yes if that was all and they
задрипанские да если бы это и все и они
that is, this Russian myth about
плывут то есть этот русский миф о
of inheritance of Kyivan Rus Yes he is
правонаследий Киевской Руси Да он
breaks at this moment further they
разрывается в этом моменте дальше они
there they are taken from a certain Ivan the Terrible
там выводят от некоего Ивана Грозного
everything is going well with them there so oh but oh
все у них там хорошо идет так о но вот
this gap does not exist. How do you break it up?
этот разрыв нет вот Как вы им раздолбаете
them on this
их по этому
moment
момента
Russians, I can start, and I think Mr. Vitaly
русских я могу начать а я думаю п Виталий
I will fill you in more detail
Я наполню вас более подробно
John 3 Do they not pretend to me?
Иоанна 3 Они же и не мне себя какими-то
they are the successors of Russia or something
там правопреемниками России или что-то такое
was on the third
было на третьего
it first appeared in his titulars
у него у титолатур впервые появилась
Rus, but not even in the list of Russian cities
Русь но даже в перечне городов Руси не
was only in Kyiv
было Киева и только
1480 letter to Maximilian the First
1480 год письме к максимилиану первому
Habsburg Holy Roman Emperor
габсбурга императора священно-римского
empire, he wrote to him that the prince of Russia
империи у него он писал что князь Руси
two dots and there was a list of cities on
две точечки и там был перечень городов на
which he believed that tourists there for the first time in Kyiv
которые он считал что турусы там впервые Киев
just appeared
только появился
from Russia, only Chernihiv seems to be his
из России только Чернигов
tatu ot turi was First Well, first
тату от туре был Сначала Ну сначала
even Kyiv was not there and then Kyiv appeared
даже Киева не было, а потом появился Киев
ie It was a claim on the territory
то есть Это была претензия на территории
Russia Well, this is the period when they themselves
России Ну вот этот период когда они себя
began to understand them as Rus, that is, I them
начали осмысливать как Русь то есть я их
to praise in a conversation with this Well, just ask
хвалить в разговоре этим Ну просто спросить
and show me something to Ivan III
а покажите мне к Ивану III ну что-нибудь чтобы
said that these territories are Russia
говорило о том что эти территории являются Русью
Russia, Russia, they have everything, they have the SRS, they have it
Россия Русь все у них р срс он у них
eyes light up like zombies, that's why
глазах светятся как зомби.
things are an interesting question in your opinion
кстати интересный вопрос как по вашему мнению
about monuments and who needs monuments
относительно памятников и памятники кому нужно
put now modern Ukraine so on
ставить сейчас современной Украине так на
replacing all this with Pushkin and so on
замену этим всем пушкиным и так далее
Yes, that's who you would see from the historical ones
да Вот кого бы вы видели из исторических
let's talk about history
фигур так ну вот раз мы об истории
we say who should bet
говорим кому стоило бы ставить
Monuments in Ukraine or Razkoropatskyi
памятники в Украине или раскоропатский
Balbachan Namalovich Pavlenko is if
балбачан намалевич Павленко это если
Brother, only in Ukraine are they transferred Yes, yes
брат только в Украине переваливаются Да а
there is the depth of God in our Mazepi monument
там глубину Боже у нас Мазепе памятника
No, I live in Bila Tserkva, he is
нет Я живу в Белой Церкви е-е Он
was born in the village of Mazepintsi near Bila
родился в селе Мазепинцы под белой
church We do not have a monument to Mazepa to
церковью У нас нет памятника Мазепе до
of today and also Father's Devils
сегодняшнего дня и еще Чортков отца
to which Suvorov still stands Yes
которому Суворов еще стоит Да
I believe that I have heard such an opinion somewhere, I do not
Полагаю, что я где-то слышал такое мнение, я не
I know how fair she is
знаю насколько она справедлива что
monuments are placed to the Heroes of our time
памятники относятся Героям ХХ века
that is, the monuments of the past are somehow not
то есть прошлом памятники как-то не
it is customary to put although convinced that
принято ставить хотя убежден что
many places need monuments of the past
много где надо и памятники прошлом
put, I think that we have such a time now
поставить думаю что у нас сейчас такое время
that we will find monuments to someone
что у нас найдется кому памятники
put, for example, a monument
поставьте например памятник
to a collective defender, for example, a defender
коллективному азовцу например защитнику
azovstali defender of Mariupol can
азовстали защитнику Мариуполя можно
to put, and many places, for example
поставить и причем много где например
Hungarians That is why there is a monument to it
венгров Поэтому это там памятник этому
Arpad looks like Alya
арпаду даешь типа как там Аля
the father of the Hungarians Yes who translated them there
отец-венгров Да какой там перевел их
through the Carpathians, that is, it turns out in
через Карпаты то есть получается в
modernity should still be a principle
принципе все равно должна быть и современность
and the past on the fact that if there was a story -
и прошлое на том, что если бы было история -
this is the basis on which it is then formed
это тот базис на котором потом формируется
some kind of consciousness if you ask someone
сознание какое если уж спрашиваете кому
now I think about erecting monuments
сейчас ставить памятники то я думаю в
there areus
нас есть
Yes
да
and the modern past is so unspoiled here
и современным прошлым здесь такое непахане
field that oh-oh-oh
поле что ой-ой-ой
and when you see Ukraine after
и когда вы видите Украину после
the end of the war with all the crises and
окончание войны со всеми кризисами и
changes
изменениями
It is very difficult to answer this question
очень трудно отвечать на этот вопрос я
I see Ukraine as free as possible
вижу Украину как максимально свободной
a country of free people if anything
страной свободных людей что-то если уж
take such a historic time in our country
брать такой исторический раз у нас такой
today the stream still reminds of the times
сегодня стрим что-то еще напоминает времена
Cossacks are armed people, I am convinced
казаков это вооруженные люди Я убежден
that a Ukrainian should be able to freely
что украинец должен свободно иметь возможность
a Cossack is always free to own a weapon
свободную владеть оружием казак – это всегда
freely armed man is equality for
свободно вооруженный человек это равенство для
everyone is a fair trial
всех это справедливый суд
democracy
демократия
human rights and all that so he returned
права человека и все такое так вернулся
to us Yevhen yes
к нам Евгений да
I hope he will not hesitate because something at all
надеюсь не будет колебать что-то совсем
I monitor the issue in Telegram if you
я мониторю вопрос в телеграмме если вы
you see interesting questions in the YouTube chat
видите в чате Ютуба интересные вопросы
you can answer yes immediately
можете отвечать сразу да
I just have a question here
меня просто вопрос здесь как раз от
subscribers in the first place Then we already
подписчиков в первую очередь Потом мы уже
if I have time, maybe I'll ask for my own. Yes
если успею то может и свои задам А так
Now the question is, wait, I'll find it. So here it is
сейчас вопрос жди ​​найду Значит здесь по
the scale of that now so
шкале того сейчас да
for which Peter changed the name
для чего Петр и сменил название
of the Moscow state and what it gave him
Московского государства и что это ему дало
[music]
[музыка]
I don't think he had such a goal
я не думаю что у него такая цель была
change is general such historical
изменять это общая такой исторический
Stefan Yavorskyi and Theophanes tried him
процесс ему Стефан Яворский и Феофан
Prokopovich
Прокофьевич
it will be fashionable now to be called that
будет модно сейчас модно называться да
yes, well, it is an influence on no. It is a real influence
да ну это влияние на не Это реально влияние
of our church summer at events in
нашей церковной леты на события в
Petersburg. And the phone
Петербурге Ну и телефон
It's an interesting question. I don't know how much it is
вот интересно вопрос Не знаю насколько он
really means, asks Vito in Latin
действительно значит спрашивает Вито в латинском
in the language the letters yu and в were read the same as у
языке буквы ю и в читались одинаково как в
I really don't know, except for times on my pants
Я правда не знаю разу ну на штанов
writes whether there is a connection between this fact and
пишет ли связь между этим фактом и
variations of the name Ukraine and in the countries here
вариациями названия Украина и в странах здесь
it is about what is on the old maps
речь идет о том, что на старых картах на
Ukraine is written on some old maps
некоторых старых картах Украина написана
through Latin in Ukraine but through in a
через латинские в Украине но через в а
what is it connected with
с чем это связано
he is all fluently written
он весь тот письменностью фу во плавно
through ve, in my opinion, it is so French
через ве по-моему это такая французская
language of the middle of the 17th century
язык середины XVII века
Well, there is definitely such a moment
Ну там однозначно есть такой момент е-е
For example, if we take some strange ones
Например, если мы берем какие-то странные
Roman coins There is always an ending
римские монеты Там всегда окончание
of the emperor is written as Otse same in IS da
императора пишется как Вот же в ИС да
that is, if, for example, the emperor Antoninus
то есть если например император Антонин
it is written not Antonin, but antoninus if there
пишется не Антонин А антонинус если там
Trojan and Janus if Adam Adams That is
троян и Янус если Адам Адамс То есть
this ending through Ben and through A
это окончание через Ben и через у А
precisely through in, although it is read as in ie
именно через у хотя читается как у то есть
Well, it's me
ну это мне
in Latin
в латыни
some rule is even more so
какое-то правило такое еще больше кто
ending we are talking about the prefix not about
окончание речь идет о префиксе не о
I saw the Ot suffix in the chat
суффикс Вот увидел в чате е-е
interesting question Sasha Syrotyuk asks why
интересный вопрос Саша Сиротюк спрашивает почему
Oleg is considered semi-mythical
Олег считается полумифическим
is checked by parallel sources in
проверяется параллельным источникам в
I have a question about the same thing
меня вопрос как раз по этому же
Oleg's contract of 911 may be
договор Олега 911 года он может быть
the source can not be the source yes
источником не может быть источником да
Let's see
Давай Смотри
Stories of past years or somewhere or there
Повести временных лет или где-нибудь
In the story, the crimson is also popular
Багряного и в повести имеет народный
the source, that is, there it is indicated that
источник ну есть там там указывается что
Oleg seems to be mentioned
вроде бы упоминается Олег
no Bagryany does not mention it for sure
ни у Багряного точно не упоминается это
all
все
vidumkista, I wanted to check some
выдумкиста это же я хотел проверить какая-то
because I also couldn't find just what with
потому что я тоже не мог найти как раз что с
of the Byzantine side, well, like Oleg
византийской стороны ну типа Олега как
it would not be just to enter
бы нет это только внести
asks Well there is no What's the difference What's the difference
спрашивает Ну нет Какая разница Какая разница
in ryatushki it turns out so easily for
в рятушки получается так просто для
viewers need to understand what and how
зрителей надо понимать что вот как
I am not a historian to understand, that is, like me
понять не историк вот как мне есть
there is no mention in one source yet
упоминание в одном источнике не есть еще
a historical fact, that is, in order to
историческим фактом да то есть для того чтобы
we said that now it will be difficult
мы говорили что сейчас начнут сложно
to explain to people what I understand is how
объяснять так людям я то что понимаю как
not a historian Maybe not historians
не историк Так может как не историки
explain to others when, for example, look at
объяснить другим когда например смотрите в
In the past, people did not know what was critical
прошлом люди не знали что такое критическое
thinking and For example, I am reading now
мышления и Вот например я читаю сейчас
they know justice
знают ну справедливости
it's fair just me to the point that
справедливо просто я к тому что
for example, I read I did on the cartridge very much
например я читал Я делал на патрон очень
great very great analysis post
большое очень большое сообщение с анализом
text history of the northern peoples wait
текста история северных народов ждите
Olaf Magnus is the 17th century
Олафа Магнуса это е-е 17 века
appears to be 17th or 16th century and he describes
кажется 17 или 16 века и он описывает
he describes werewolves in various mythical
оборотней он описывает в различных мифических
creatures And as reality and there very much
существах А как реальность да там очень
it is interesting to read seriously, but I advise you to read it
интересно читать серьезно вот советую почитать
the history of the northern peoples of Olofomance is
историю северных народов олофоманса это
as fascinating as the book is, it's not really there
как как увлекательная книга она не очень там
new I read to make a big post in
новая Я читал чтобы сделать большой пост в
Telegram Oh, on Patreon and you understand
телеграмме Ой на патрионе и понимаете и
people didn't question it like that
люди не ставили под сомнение так как это
a lot of people are doing a lot now
много делают сейчас сейчас люди гораздо
more skeptical therefore only one source
более скептически поэтому только один источник
just as he says about something is not proof of it
как и говорит о чем-то еще не является доказательством того
that it was so even more so if we
что оно так было тем более если мы
we are talking about the Tale of Bygone Years
говорим о Повесть временных лет
written there in the 12th century
написана там в 12 в.
another story if you accept one opinion
еще другая история если принять одно мнение
that basically it is written in 12
что в основном вот оно написано в 12
century, but what are the events there
веке но е-е события какие там
described, for example, the same Oleg ryu it
описываются например тот же Олег рю это
the ninth century in general as a person with
девятый век вообще как человек из
people have such ideas about the world
такими представлениями там о мире что люди
which are even older than those who wrote about
которые еще древнее тех, кто писал о
werewolves, if you can't, how can they
оборотней если бы нельзя как им можно
see how it is checked What
посмотреть как это проверяется Что
for example, if it is about one of the different ones
например если об одном из разных
territory there, for example, Arab sources
территорий там, например, арабские источники
Scandinavian sources and ours there are local
Скандинавские источники и наши там местные
sources say about one thing approximately
источники говорят о чем-то приблизительно
the same then we can already assume
то же самое тогда мы уже можем предположить
that they all do not have some mass
что у них всех не какое-то массовое
landlord And if it's just someone
помещение А если это только кто-то
one says that and the others all say no and Nobody
один говорит то а другие все нет и никто
simply does not know about these people anymore
больше не знает об этих людях просто
people should be sent to school
людей нужно отправить в школьный
textbook from the fifth grade of the tentacle
учебника по пятому классу щупака
The burlaks are there clearly
Бурлаки там пескаревой где четко
it is written that there are two study periods
написано что есть два периода изучения
history to scientific and scientific everything
истории к научному и научному все что
was written before the 18th century - this is before
писалось до XVIII века – это до
the scientific period of studying the history of people
научный период изучения истории люди
wrote what they wanted and how they wanted and so on
писали что хотели И как хотели И так далее
And only from the work of Leopold von Ranck
И только от труда Леопольда фон утра
the German historian who laid the cellars
немецкого историка, заложившего подвалы
on the scientific understanding of history
на научное понимание истории
the scientific study of history begins
начинается научное изучение истории
therefore, all these sources date back to the 18th century
поэтому все эти источники к XVIII веку
- this is only the work of historians. Only me
- это ну только работа историков Только я
not for those who try in them
не для тех кто там пытается у них
find something there, some kind of exercise, by the way
что-то там найти какое-то упражнение Я кстати
on account I think that will confirm on
на счет Я думаю что подтвердит на
account of this story
счет этой повести
can such a situation ot Take it now
могут такую ​​ситуацию вот Возьмите сейчас
a person who has some education has
человека имеющего какое-то образование имеет
Internet and tried that she sat down and
интернет и попробовал что она села и
wrote clearly about the events, for example
написала четко о событиях, например
300 years old without using
300-летней давности не пользуясь
some historical sources, yes
какими источниками там вот историческими
now she will just write fiction like this
сейчас она просто фантастику напишет да
And if the dude sat in the 12th century and
А если чувак сидел в 12-м веке и
he also had the task of writing something
так же ему была задача написать что-то
about nine o'clock, as here he is sipping it
о девятом так как это он серба он
wrote fiction, i.e. before science fiction
писал фантастику то есть к научной
period of reflection if I'm not mistaken
период осмысления если я не ошибаюсь это
the stories of the past years began there
же повести временных лет там начиналось
that first there was Adam and Eve then they left
что сначала был Адам и Ева потом пошли
to be born there
там родиться
the creation of the world from Japheth there
сотворение мира от яфета там
the mythology is gone
мифология пошла
it's generally interesting when for this
там вообще интересно когда при этом как раз
still Oleg again why why him
таки Олег опять таки почему почему он
more mythical because when it is said that
более мифический как когда кажется что
a like means it will sit here and there
вот лайк значит даст сидящий и здесь там
He lists the peoples of Finna Hungarian
народы он перечисляет Фина венгерский
Slavic and all that is written there
славянские и там пишется и все это
it's called Great Scythia Well, that's him
зовется Великая Скифия Ну то есть он
calls Nestor called great
называет Нестор называется большой
in Scythia it is called the mouth. That is, this
скифией он называется устью. То есть это
Scythia when it was before our phenomenon
Скифия когда она была это к нашему явлению
third century BC Velika
третий век до нашей эры Большая
Scythia of the 3rd century BC, the third of ours
Скифия III века до нашей третьей нашей
so mala sings yes yes here he means he
поэтому мала поет да да вот он есть он
remembers some memorable times Well, how
вспоминает какие-то запоминающиеся времена Ну как
he stirs it all, it is not clear what is there
он перемешивает все это непонятно что там
such a textbook of the fifth grade in the teeth of Hai
такое учебник пятого класса в зубы
study and you don't need everything written
изучают и все написано вам не нужно
to forget that Nestormonad and he thinks
забывать что нестормонад и он мыслит
religious categories
религиозными категориями
they wrote for us at the beginning of the boxing stream
для нас писали в начале стрима бокс в
as a result, he said that in school history
результате сказал что в школьной истории
it is necessary to change everything in general And now he says
надо вообще все менять И теперь он говорит
take a textbook from the fifth grade and
берите учебник по пятому классу и
look, it's all written there, No, just how
смотрите там все написано Нет просто как
a concrete example of that already
конкретный пример что уже
the textbook has such a thing that they change
учебнику есть вот такое А то что менять
all this is necessary to the bottom, ask for those
надо все это до основания За тех спрашивайте
refer to timity snyder Who is this
относиться к темите снайдера Кто это
generally like that
вообще такой
recently he collected just there for something or
недавно он собрал как раз там на что-то или
we don't know what this story means
на дар или нас что это история значит
he is an American historian on drones
американский историк на дроны он
collected yes
собрал да
a million or how many dollars there is more
миллион или сколько долларов там больше
the sniper's materials are useless
ничего себе не дадут материалы снайпера
bloody land red prince in general
кровавые земли красный князь вообще
the bombastic biography of Vasyl Vyshivany
бомбезная биография Василия вышитого
Vasyl, well, the Habsburg flight, X-ray this
Василия ну габсбург лет рентгена этого
By the way, he had nowhere in my opinion
Кстати у него было по-моему негде
it's his birthday recently
недавно день рождения у этого
Vasylovich, tell us who Vasyl is
Васильевича расскажите кто такие Василий
Vyshyvanka because many do not know this one
вышиванку потому что многие не знают эту
Sergei could potentially summarize the story
историю коротко Сергея потенциально мог бы
I am so intrigued to be the king of Ukraine
быть король Украины я так заинтригую
the king of Ukraine of whom we are not
всех король Украины которого мы Не
deserved as soon as in the composition
заслужили как только в составе
of the Austro-Hungarian monarchy
австро-венгерской монархии ну
if Austria-Hungary annexed Volhynia
если бы австра-венгрия присоединила Волыни
Podillia would be created autonomous
Подолье была бы создана автономная
a state under the auspices of the Austro-Hungarian Empire
государство под берлом австро-венгерского
an eagle that included Galicia
орла которая включала в Галицию
Transcarpathia, Bukovyna, Volyn, Podillia, and this
Закарпатье Буковину Волыни Подолье и это
would be the king of this Ukrainian
был бы королем этого украинского
part of the Austro-Hungarian monarchy is like this
часть австро-венгерской монархии такова
Polar from this as it is written Timothy
Полярная из этого как пишется Тимоти
Snyder was more than 18 years old
Снайдер 18-м году было больше чем в
Roman Surzhan writes about the Staropad issue
старопадского вопроса Роман суржан пишет
is interested in the question of the real borders of the Ukrainian People's Republic
интересует вопрос о реальных границах УНР
that's because the Russians often talked a
так вот россияне часто разговаривались
indeed, we meet different cards for what
действительно вот встречаем разные карты на что
she claimed UNR, which is real
она претендовала на УНР что реально
Alya controlled her eyes there in Taganroschi
контролировала эти Аля там таганросты на
This is the thickness they entered. It is necessary
толщина вот они входили Это надо
read I read the station wagon I forgot which c
читать Я читал универсал Я забыл который в
which station wagon has already been told about
каком универсале уже сказано о
territory of the third station wagon 9
территории третьей универсал 9
they are Ukrainian provinces without Crimea
украинских губерний без Крыма они
they wrote that there where The majority of the population
писали что там где большинство населения
simplified I can't quote I only
упрощено Я процитировать не могу Я только
once I read simplified what where Most
раз читал упрощенно что где Большинство
the Ukrainian population is clearly there
население украинское там четко
nine Ukrainian cucumbers were declared
заявлено девять огурцов украинских
province without Crimea And in others there
губерний без Крыма А у других там
territories if there will be tipa
территориях если будут там типа
plebiscites
плибисциты
then we choose a task
тогда мы выбираем задачу
The Kuban may or may not have been included often
Кубань входили чуть ли не факт может часто
our people also shout kubanko
наши люди тоже кричат ​​вот кубанько
Serhiy Agromenko is whole about the negotiations
Сергея агроменко о переговорах целая
such a book about negotiations, eh
книга такова о переговорах е-е
of the Crimean Tatar government under Suleiman
крымско-татарского правительства у Сулеймана
Syurkevych and the Kuban People's Republic
сюркевича и Кубанская народная республика
they do not know anything about joining Ukraine
о присоединении к Украине они ничем не
finished so shorter so I'm cutting it. [ __ ]
закончились так короче так подрезаю Бля
our Kuban was not part of the UNR like that
нашей Кубань не входила в состав УНР да
not everything further on your own at all is simple
нет все дальше самостоятельно вообще просто
there was his independent state
там было самостоятельное государство его
dispersed this Kuban Council in Denikin
разогнал в деникин этот кубанский Совет
it also existed for a short time
она просуществовала тоже короткое время они
should have become part of Ukraine, well
должно было войти в состав Украины
Hetman of the Ukrainian state
Украинского государства гетмана
Skoropadsky on the rights of autonomy
Скоропадского на правах автономии
but there were different options but
но там были разные варианты но
since the Germans lost the war a
поскольку немцы проиграли войну
Hetmans relied on everything. It went to dust
гетманами опирался все Это пошло прахом
question to Morozenka Someone writes I am very
вопрос к Морозенко Кто-то пишет Я очень
I like to collect coins and that's why I want to
люблю коллективировать монеты и потому хочу
go to archeology, what is your advice?
иди на археологию, какой совет?
to advise you don't love You love how
чтобы посоветовать не любишь Ты любишь как
it turns out to enter, maybe you will fall in love there
значит, вступать может, там возлюбишь
I mean, if the archaeologist goes to
имею в виду вот если на археолога идет в
there are universities that specialize in this
нас ВУЗы специализирующиеся на этом
place very specific promotion is exactly that
месте очень специфическая акция это прямо это
history multiplied I don't know in the cube or in
история умножена Я не знаю в кубе или в
squares, that is, there is as much as everything
квадрате то есть там насколько все
complicated in detail to some such this
сложно подробно к каким-то таким это
in fact it is difficult if honestly difficult Well
на самом деле это тяжело если честно тяжело Ну
that is, master it if you just love
то есть осилить это если ты просто любишь
collect coins Well, I also like V
коллекционировать монеты Ну я тоже люблю В
me, there is this album of Davnianivskyi
меня он там этого альбом древненовских
moments Well, here we are in the chat, what are you doing?
моментов Ну у нас здесь в чате вот вы вы что
interrupted finished what But no, I finish everything
перебил кончил что Да Нет все я заканчиваю
to the Faculty of History in Warsaw at that time
на исторический факультет тогда Варшавой
it is correct that the desire is without doubt
правильно что желание есть без сомнений
you have to join if you want to learn it
нужно поступать если хочется это учить
like some associative facts Yes
нравится какой-то ассоциатив факты Да
likes to do excavations It will be
нравится раскопками заниматься Это будет
it's very difficult. Well, if you want, let him go
очень тяжело Ну если хочется пусть поедет на
excavation digs shovel waves and then
раскопки покопает лопатой помахает а затем
understand, enter
поймет вступайте
surely say that if the boy thinks that he
наверняка скажи что если пацан думает что он
will come and deal only with coins
приедет и только монетами будет заниматься
Yes, he is probably in the first year
Да он наверняка на первом курсе
will hate that story even more. How much
возненавидит ту историю еще да Сколько
he needs a volume of information and that's it
ему нужен объем информации да это это
first you have to go on expeditions like me
сначала надо экспедициях побывать как я
by the way, that's what I did. I first went along
кстати так и делал Я сначала поехал по
expeditions a-a despite the fact that in fact still
экспедициях а-а при том что фактически еще
was not on this one and then already decided for
не был на этот а потом уже решил для
to treat myself Well, although I myself
себя поступать Ну хотя я из самого
at the beginning wanted to enroll in historical
начала хотел на исторический поступать
there are certain circumstances did not allow me
нет там определенные обстоятельства не позволили я
decided already later at the master's degree if
решил уже потом на магистраторе если бы
to act in principle caught up quickly but
поступить в принципе догнал быстро но
it is difficult, that is, you have to live with it
это тяжело то есть тем этим надо жить
actually live that is
фактически жить то есть
I have a question because we already have it
у меня есть вопросы поскольку У нас уже
historians and archaeologists in the profession in conversation
историки и археолог в профессии в разговоре
when history and archeology can
когда история и археология смогут
come to an agreement and why In general they cannot
договориться и почему вообще они не могут
to agree
договориться
such a philosophical question
такой философский вопрос
biology describes the material part
биология описывает материальную часть
cultures can be materially determined by it
культуры материально по ней определить
some social things he talks about
социальные какие-то вещи о которых говорит
history is very difficult Well there is a classic
история очень тяжело Ну есть классический
example if we unearth jeans
пример если мы откопаем джинсы
try to prove how it is archaeological
попробуйте доказать как это археологическая
culture their on force here describe This this
культура их на сила вот опишите Это эта
administration is an example you know I want
администрация это пример знаете Я хочу
lead here
навести вот
Yes, look, I have a tip. Yes
Да смотрите вот у меня есть наконечник Да
for example, the Scythian tip. That is, we
например Скифский наконечник То есть мы
we are called the Scythian natomicnik
называемся скифским нотомником
[music]
[музыка]
that is, see two there 600 or how many
то есть смотрите две там 600 или сколько
thousands A Scythian tip Friends Well
тысяч А Скифский наконечник Друзья Ну
so the Scythians were here, and here we are
значит Скифы Здесь были да вот мы
we find it somewhere near Poltava Aga
находим там где-то его под Полтавой Ага
So the Scythians were here. Well, that's actually it
Значит, были здесь Скифы Ну на самом деле это
tip of the Scythian type, i.e. his
наконечник скифского типа, то есть его
used by all the peoples there
использовали все там народы которые там
but I don't know where it ends, probably somewhere
вот я не знаю где кончается должно быть где-то
ends in Vinnytsia region somewhere there
заканчивается Винницкой области где-то там
Well, there are very few people from Lviv
ну Львовские встречается очень мало аж
there all the way to the Urals there all the way there in general how
там до Урала туда и туда в общем как
to determine what kind of culture it is
определить какая это именно культура по
to this tip Well that's the problem that's it
этому наконечнику Ну это проблема это это
it is very difficult, that is, it turns out to be simple
очень тяжело есть получается просто
military technology very quickly
военные технологии очень быстро
spread themselves people see About it
распространяли себя люди видят
does the mill work the same, for example yes or there
работает так же мельница например да или там
Zhirnova is effective every now and then
Жирнова время от времени она эффективно
preparation technology for material
технология приготовления к материальной
culture to define socio-cultural
культуры определить социокультурное
environment is difficult archaeology
среда тяжеловата археология
finds culture on two certain
находит культуру на двух определенных
territories, let's say conditionally Well, for example
территориях скажем условно Ну например
one region of Ukraine and another region
одна область Украины и вторая область
Ukrainian archeology finds one there
Украины археология находит там одну
archaeological culture and the history of Po
археологическую культуру а история По
documents say that there is already one nation
документах говорит, что там уже в один народ
one tribe another tribe and genetics still
одно племя другое племя а генетика еще
the third important factor is genetics
третий важный свести генетика
in general, biology describes biological
вообще-то в биологию описывает биологическую
the human side is not ours at all
сторону человека это вообще не до нас
By the way, I always do
Кстати сложности Я всегда до
archeologists, you can imagine the question
археологов этакий вопрос ты а вот представьте
so let's say that after 500 years or so
вот давай так через там 500 лет или
For a thousand years, gram has been dug up like this
тысячу лет так откапывают грамм
the music record is drawn like that
музыкальную пластинку так вот там нарисован
some kind of Marilyn Manson, yes, some one is there
какой-то Мерлин Мэнсон да какой-то там он
as a demon is like that, so what are people who are not
как демон такой так вот что люди не
would have information that it was not
имели бы информацию что это было не имели
what kind of history is lost
какую-то историю вот потеряно Да было бы
so that they can think about how you are
так чтобы они могли подумать вот Как вы
archaeologists well
археологи ну
guess you dug up a jug
додумываете вот вы откопали кувшин
saw some picture there and started
увидели там какие-то рисунок и начинают
it meant that there is fertile there
это означало что там плодородное там
blah blah that's how it all happens
бла-бла вот как оно это все происходит
Well, that's it. It's very specific there even
ну это это Я это очень специфика там даже
archeology itself is not their branch
сами археологии я их не ответвления
That is, someone is engaged in swindling
То есть кто-то занимается поглатчиком
numismatics or gnostics are different
нумизматика или нистика там разные эти эти
they are engaged there specialists They
они занимаются там специалисты Они
exactly there, well, this is something to do in depth
точно там ну это это углубленно заниматься
And in general Nu pogla chiku so very Nu
А вообще Ну погла чику да очень Ну
it is possible there if a jug, for example
можно там если кувшин например
of Trypil culture and Trypilsk
Трипольской культуры да Трипольская
in principle, if it stands out like that
в принципе, если оно так выделяется
among others and does not confuse with others
среди прочих и не спутает с другими
cultures, well, if it's any, there are many of them
культурами ну если это какая-то там я много
most ceramics can be found here
больше керамика здесь ее можно найти
it is also very widely distributed there
также очень широко она там распространена там
somewhere intertwined mainly here
где-то переплетается в основном здесь
more even if there are some cultures
больше даже если культуры какие-то
stand out more for some reason
выделяются тем больше по каким-то там
burials, burials - this is evidence
погребениях захоронения - это вот свидетельствует
about some religion, well, some religion
о какой-то религии ну религии Да какое-то
paganism that some were buried in jugs there
язычество что там одних хоронили кувшинах
jugs were burned, others were buried
сжигали кувшины закладывали хоронили других
they simply put them in the graves of others
просто клали в могилы других да или
corpse-laying or corpse-laying of everything
трупание или трупа возложения всего
two principles and a million people yes yes To
два принципа а народов миллион да Да
This thing is interesting
вещи это интересно Вот когда встречал такую
a phrase that history digs on
фразу что и история копается на
dustbins and in graves, that's what Ot remembered
мусорниках и в могилах так вот и вспомнил
we have the town of Horodok Khmelnytska
у нас в городе Городок Хмельницкой
region was also excavated some
области так тоже было откопано какую-то
you can see the inn and there was a pit 2 m or so
видно Корчма была и Там яма 2 м или
how many different glass jugs?
сколько разных кувшины стеклянные
a person was directly raked out a bunch of them
человека там прям выгребали их куча да на
a whole dissertation can be accumulated
целый диссертацию может накопаться
Of course, where did everything go?
конечно куда сбрасывали все что весь
useless What do you think Here are our eyes
хлам Как вы думаете Вот наши эти
landfills yes for archaeologists there
полигоны мусора так для археологов там
of the future, if it is lost, there will be
будущего если будет потеряна будут
let's say the same store of knowledge
таким же скажем положим знаний
it's hard to say, Andrii likes to work
это трудно сказать Андрей любит заниматься
as biology
как битологией
look lookwe
смотрите смотрите мы
excavated, let's say let's say something concrete
раскапывали скажем давай что-то конкретно
here the question is how is archeology in general
здесь Вопрос в том как археология вообще
will be through there or she will be like this
будет через там или она будет так
you can ask me this, look alone
можно меня спрашивать такое смотрите один
the subscriber really wanted to ask Mr
подписчик очень хотел спросить у п
Vitaly about Olena Volodymyrivna Ruthenian
Виталия об Елене Владимировне русине
it was she who wrote the book Ukraine
именно она написала книгу Украина
under the Tatars, Lithuania over Ukraine
под татарами Литвой над Украиной
the institute can be viewed, it is necessary that Vitaliy
институт можно посмотреть, надо чтобы Виталий
commented on this work and the author himself
прокомментировал это дело и самого автора
he is a highly specialized specialist in this field
это высокопрофессиональный специалист по этим
the dark period of approximately 13-15 centuries
темным периодом примерно 13-15 века
period when we have the fewest sources of this
периода когда у нас меньше источников это
there was a series of
была серия какая
in the late 1990s, it was washed by the state
помыл в конце 90-х получило государственную
award historical series there in my opinion 15
премию историческая серия там по-моему 15
volumes and, in my opinion, one of the strains was written
томов и по-моему один из штаммов писала
this is Olena Rusyna from the period 14-16
это Елена русина как раз о периоде 14-16
century
век
that it is worth paying attention to the high class
что стоит внимания высококлассность
specialists really don't know where she is
специалисты правда не знаю где она
something happened in the last 10 years. Well, I'm fine
прошла однажды последние годы 10 Ну я ничего
I didn't see it from her. Well, there is a connection there
от нее не видел Ну там связан а
precisely the comment of the question with the fact that she is there
именно комментарий вопроса с тем что она там
mentions Ukraine, and that is, interprets everything about it
вспоминает Украину да есть толкует ее все
it's closer to what it originally was
все-таки ближе к тому что Сначала это
it was more like something else
было все же скорее какое-то еще
border or Oceana, well, that's just the way they all are
погранични че Океана ну это просто так все
Tlumachi is a border area between
Толкователи это пограничная территория между
settled agricultural population and
оседлым земледельческим населением и
nomadic population and then content
кочевым населением а затем содержание
terms change in history began
терминов меняется в истории начиналось
as a border territory
как по границе приграничная территория
then it moved to separate Well how
потом оно перешло на отдельные. Ну как
separate principalities were meant But
отдельных княжеств имелись в виду Но
the book is cool. By the way, if so
книжка классная Кстати вот Если да
to look at the modern Kherson region there
взглянуть на современную там херсонщину
Odeshchyu is a steppe zone, so it is in
одещину вот это степную зону так то в
in principle, I looked at the migration ones
принципе я так смотрел по миграционным
waves that can be found in Wikipedia here and there
волнам которые можно в Википедии так то там
the Huns went through the war like this
гунный проходили да войной так то
Bulgarians migrated, Bulgarians are someone else
болгары мигрировали болгары ми то кто-то
constantly on this territory of the Steppe
постоянно по этой территории Степной по
in fact, it was not inhabited
сущности она не была заселена оседлым
the people are nomadic
народом так получается была ли кочевой
the head of the Great Steppe from the interior
голова Большая Степь от внутренних
regions of Mongolia, it ends
районов Монголии он заканчивается аж
Portugal in the south of Spain this
португалией на юге Испании этот
Great Steppe Here it rests
Большая Степь Вот у нас она упирается
in my opinion, this one is in the Danube on the territory of Ukraine
по-моему в Дунай на территории Украины эта
the zone of nomadic peoples there are farmers
зона кочевых народов там земледельцы
Cossacks appeared in the 15th-16th centuries
появились ну этот 15-16 век казацкий
development of the South of Ukraine - This is only then
освоение Юга Украины - Это только тогда
appeared because the Ukrainians colonized these
появились поэтому украинцы коломизировали эти
territory so that you understand yes yes just me
территории чтобы вы понимали да да просто я
that's how all the migrations there are
так вот все миграции туда на
everyone can say the Danubian language like that
дунайщину можно так сказать все
passed through our headquarters from the Urals
проходили через наш штаб вот с Урала
sivirus e-e of these steppes yes That is, it comes out
сивирус е-е этих степей да есть получается
that there is no autochthonous population there
что там автохтонного населения там нет
such Yes
такого Да
it's just
это просто
This is from the Stone Age
это еще Да это еще с каменного века еще с
that is, it all began in the stone age
каменного века это все началось то есть
Nomads and nomads were conditionally there
были там условно Да замороби и кочевники
So the nomads are even closer
Вот и кочевники ближе они они даже
at first they sat there on the Left Bank, yes
сначала садились там на Левобережье да
i.e. initially there were such contacts there
то есть сначала были такие контакты там
The pit culture is the same here they are
Ямная культура та же вот они
were in contact with the Tripoli yak
контактировали с трипольской которая была
Zelemous culture and then it completely
землеуской культурой, а потом оно совсем
otsia otsia otsia the whole south he basically
вот это весь юг он в принципе
he was a nomad just before that
кочевническим был это как раз до того
period, as Mr. Vitaly noted, that is
периода как господин Виталий отметил
there is such a cool thing that ours
там такого какого-то прикольно что наши
the ancestors are precisely Yamna culture it
предки есть именно Ямная культура это
Indo-European culture, not the people of Tripoli
индоевропейская культура, а не трипольцы
what kind of farmers By the way, with these people from Tripoli
какие земледельцы Кстати с этими трипольцами
we often say that these are the people of Tripoli
часто у нас говорят что вот трипольцы это
the ancestors of Ukrainians, let me tell you, you see
предки украинцев да расскажу видите
as much as it is a myth, it is a myth absolutely
насколько это миф это миф абсолютно
appeared I think at the end of the 19th century
появился думаю в конце 19-го века
first XX when they began to dig up
сначала XX когда стали раскапывать
This myth appeared in Tripillia Well, it's good in
Триполье появился этот миф Ну хорошо в
me then such a profane question as long as I
меня тогда такой профанский вопрос пока я
I didn't get lost because I have one more strap
не пропал потому что я еще одна ремарочка у меня
In two minutes they can turn off
в Через две минуты могут отключить
the light I will not return to me is
свет Я уже не вернусь у меня есть
generator, but the neighbors won't understand
генератор но ну соседи не поймут
if i turn on now its already evening
если я включу сейчас уже вечером
generator, so if I disappear, thank you all
генератор поэтому если исчезну то Всем спасибо
to be with us, I will ask as a layman
чтобы были с нами вот как профан спрошу вот
Tripilians, they were, they were, they were
трипольцы вот они были они были
very long as far as I know
очень долго насколько знаю очень
a long period of time was here on ours
большой промежуток времени здесь были на наших
territories and not only ours
территориях и не только наших
the population was large er Where did they go
население было большим е-е Куда они
shared Did they? Well, they didn't leave at all
делись Неужели они Ну не оставили совсем
offspring Are they extinct in man
потомство Неужели они вымерли человеку
died out completely
вымерли полностью
they are there at all with a difficult question about that
они там вообще с трудным вопросом после
that, in principle, the pizza still needs to be found
что в принципе да и пиццы еще нужно найти
quite a large base, but they don't actually have one
достаточно большую базу, а им нет фактически
Well, I have a small base there. Well
Ну там меня небольшая да база вот Ну
in fact if they found more on
на самом деле они если бы нашли больше на
west to southwest. That is, you can
запад на юго-запад То есть можно
assume that at all
предположить чтобы вообще
dad by descendants I apologize to the oldest
отцы потомками Простите самых древних
people and can it be assumed simply though
людей и можно ли допустить просто хотя
b as an assumption that we are carriers, let it not
бы как предположение что мы являемся носителями пусть не
Big but small but some kind of fate
Большой но небольшой но какой-то судьбы
genes of Trypilians
генов трипольцев
they disappeared as such, let's say conditionally
они исчезли как таковые ну скажем условно
disappeared even there 2000 years BC
исчезли и еще там 2000 лет до нашей эры
Maybe she assimilated partially I want
Может она ассимилировалась частично хочу
now, in fact, there were any
сейчас практически по-любому были какие-то
partly some connections with the pit
частично какие-то связи с ямной
culture. Well, they were like no
культурой Ну по-любому были как не
critics there are like someone who is a prisoner of someone there
критики там как кто-то кого-то там плен
took something else. Well, they dissolved
взял еще что-то было Ну они растворились
most likely, perestavshchyna. That's how they are
скорей всего переставщины Вот такая она
crisis agriculture as far as I understand
кризис земледелие насколько я понимаю
even Anya is there, especially this upper one
даже Аня там же специально этот верхний
a layer of black earth and there was no way
слой чернозема и не было возможности уже
live this election
жить на этих выборах
came there for us and built such a place
пришли там нам место, а построили такое
the huge settlement is huge
огромное поселение огромные
settlement There literally up me there
деревня Там буквально вверх мне там
There are 500 hectares of settlements, damn it
500 гектаров есть поселений от это блин
How many
сколько
population of 20,000 people
населения 20 000 населения
and they came, they sat here, there, well
и они пришли они здесь посидели там ну
let's say 50 years. Yes, you went further
скажем 50 лет Да вы были пошли дальше вы
used to be this land, it has not become like that anymore
были землю эту она стала уже не так ну
that is, at the maximum and they moved on
то есть на максимуме и они дальше перешли
burned or they burned after themselves
сжигали или они сжигали за собой
settlements, most likely they take it with them
поселение скорее всего они это с собой
they burned settlements if there were even any
сжигали поселение если бы там где даже
the sacrifice is said to have been brought like this
жертву говорят что приносили как это
settlement of the house, that is, they have such
поселение дома есть у них такого
specific and went on to see if I didn't
специфическая и дальше пошли смотри если я не
I'm wrong, that's what this culture is called
ошибаюсь это же называется эта культура
Tripillia is in Romania in the village of Cukuteini
Триполье ведь в Румынии в деревне кукутейни
It was also Yes. That is, it is one and the same
тоже было Да То есть это одна и та же одни
and the same people or just a similar culture
и те же люди или просто похожая культура
it is called what they call culture, that is
это называют как называют культурой вот
they dug up this well in Trypilla
раскопали у нас копали в Триполье эту Ну
if it's your first time, the other was near
если ты первый раз другое было около
Tripillia returned on Friday
Триполье но пятницу вернулись
and in Romania they excavated a hemlock and this is it
а в Румынии раскопали в кукутине.
too And called yesterday Painted ceramics
тоже И назвали вчера Рисованный керамики
and everything is called
да и все называется
such a very wide area was the settlement
так очень широкий ареал был расселен
Moldova, the Right Bank of Ukraine, that's all
Молдавия Правобережье Украины это все
one archaeological culture from the south
одна археологическая культура с юга
went north
шла на север
so further, something interesting happened
так дальше дальше было какое-то интересное
question
вопрос
a person does not stop asking why
человек не унимается спрашивает почему
He was on an excursion with Bandera
Бандера он был на экскурсии с
Exenhausen and ask why Bandera lived
эксенгаузене и спрашиваю почему Бандера жил
in a two-room cell with all conditions
в двухкомнатной камере со всеми условиями
how to explain to people what it is called
как объяснить людям что это называется
an honorary prisoner of his Nazi will
почетный узник его Хотела нацистская
Germany to use in their interests
Германия использовать в своих интересах
he was accused of subordinating
его же выговаривали что он подчинил
their units of the Vlasov Army and not
свои отряды власовской армии и не
wanted when they want to use a person
захотел когда человека хотят использовать
I also create normal conditions for him
для него создают нормальные условия и Я
I understand correctly that Stalin's son was sitting
правильно понимаю что сын Сталина сидел
there itself in the same ones
там же у таких же
I don't think so
я не думаю что
Yakov Stalin was sitting in a two-room apartment
Яков Сталин сидел в двухкомнатной
he was too
он тоже был
revolution
революция
were
были
Well, that is, maybe he sat like a son
Возможно, он сидел как сын
Stalin as an ordinary prisoner, that is, in
Сталина как обычный узник то есть в
poor conditions compared to Bandera or
плохих условиях в сравнении с Бандерой или
I don't remember. In short, you will tell us about Russia
не помню Короче ли ты Россия нам расскажу
that Bandera was flattered by Stalin's son
что Бандеры плесал сына сталинаш
machine of the company
автоматом компании
By the way, this is the question
Кстати вот такой вопрос
Kiy Chek of choirs and their sister Lybid is
Кий Щек хоров и их сестренка Лыбедь это
myth And when she appeared
миф А когда она появилась
of past liters Tales of past summers 11
прошлых литров Повести временных лет 11
wrote somewhere it turns out If we
написали где-то получается Если нам
are told referring to the general
рассказывают ссылаясь всеобщая
there is a lot of Slavic legend there and
славянская легенда много там и
three brothers were in Warsaw and so on
варшировали три брата и так далее это
typical for the hands of Central Europe
свойственное для рук Центральной Европы
there is an interesting point of interest in this
там интересное любопытство есть у этого
babblekova some such article of origin
бальбаковая какая-нибудь статья происхождения
Russia where he mentions Simonov Simonov and
Руси где он вспоминает Симонов Симонов и
Goethe reduces Dana to the point that
Гете которую я Дана таким сводит к тому
as if the Goths killed Sunilda Yaka there
будто там готы убили сунильду какую
Zgotsky is translated as Swan
изготского переводится как Лебедь
I think there are several
Мне кажется несколько
a number of sources that are related to
ряд источников которые привлекают
mention of Rus until 862, i.e. before there 9
упоминаний Руси до 862 года т.е.
there are centuries
век есть
earlier 9th century sources and more
более раннего 9 века источники и еще
some of those Rosomon Roksolans
какие-то там тех росомонов роксоланов
one of the first is tied to Russia
привязывают к России один из первых – это
Pania's belt looks different
пояс панийский вроде разные
That's why he writes the yaguns of Toli Rua for this
Так он там пишет за это ягунь Толи Руа
Tolerating the table Well, I saw this video
толирующий стол Ну что-то я видел это видео
on the channel of the history of Russia, it is an attractor
на канале истории России это притягатель
listen
слушать
see Goths on the territory of Ukraine Yes
смотрите готы на территории Украины Да
That is, the same Germanic tribes were like that
То есть это же германские племена были так
there is such an opinion that they had a city
вот есть такое мнение что был у них был город
on the Dnieper somewhere in the area of ​​the city of Kyiv no
на Днепре где-то в районе города Киева
until they localized it like this
пока не локализовали так
I've already heard something like that. Well, I'm something
это я уже это слышал что-то такое Ну это я что-то
I don't remember. That is, there is no such thing
не помню есть нет такого
confirmation that it is clean because there is some
подтверждение что чисто потому что там какая-то
Toligut fortress The fact is that
крепость Толигуцкая Дело в том что
we refer to the Gothic period as archaeological
доготов мы относим к археологическому
the culture of the giantess it ends there
культуру вельбашка она заканчивается там
well, she used to come there almost like that
ну она приходила там предел якобы
I don't know if it's here somewhere
будто здесь где-то ну оно не знаю
Zhytomyr region can be there in Russia. Well
Житомирская область может там по России Ну
it was changing, it was more towards the west
оно менялось оно больше это к мероприятию
In other words, Volyn is still there in Ukraine
Украина То есть это Волынь там еще
fell into this Albas culture and
попадала в эту альбасовскую культуру
so that instead of Kyiv, their fortress would be well
чтобы на месте Киева крепость их была ну
it's not, well, if you take Chernyakhivsk
это не ну если брать черняховскую
culture as Gothic Slavic culture
культуру как готовая славянская культура
how would it be then she will go and give such a person to
как бы тогда она пойдёт такой выдал в
in such a plan, yes, but if you take eh
таком плане да а вот если брать от е-е
Anna Union of tribes anti so that is
аннский Союз племен анти да т.е.
they were so simplified for us
они были вот для нас так упрощено это
just Slavs or is it she
просто славяне ли это она
it seems to me the Union of Balto-Slavics
мне кажется Союз балто-славянских
tribes if I'm not mistaken
племен если не ошибаюсь
Chernyakhiv culture That is, it is Yansky
черняховская культура То есть это янский
Union, how different were these
Союз он насколько там разные были эти
nationalities that we cannot say who
народности что мы не можем сказать кто
it was definitely all serious, right?
это точно был вот все серьезно там как нет
are they trying to cultivate Chernyakhiv culture with
стараются ли черняховскую культуру из
she is still a pig there, let them start here
ее еще свинья там пусть начинают тут
the book that you showed the second top there in
книгу что ты показывал второй топ там в
to the first Volume of the side 20 progots on
первом томе стороны 20 проготов на
the territory of Ukraine there is the 12th season
территории Украины там 12-й сезон
it is written who are what, where they were and so on
расписано кто такие что такое где были и так
further sent to the sources to the first
далее отправляют к источникам в первый
that's why that book
поэтому вот этой книги
so he is a doctor of historical sciences and
да он доктор исторических наук и
specialist in Tripoli culture Well
специалист по трипольской культуре Ну
it will be difficult for you to have a holiday there
там тяжеловато будет все у вас праздники которого
did not read No no did not read No he just already
не читал Нет нет не читал Нет он как раз уже
Probably, when you have it, it moved to...
Пожалуй, когда у вас то он перешел е-е к
Grinchenko is very happy at the university
Гринченко в университете очень
many people also write there, and don't you need to
многие тоже там пишет А не надо ли в
Return the name Rus to Ukraine, for example
Украине вернуть название Русь например
No
нет
a good one will also turn the flag over
хороший еще и флаг перевернут
Excuse the name of Russia. Don't do [ __ ] to people
название Руси извините Нет хрен делать людям
No, it's just that people have something mythical
Нет ну просто есть вот у людей мифическое
thinking that we will still call them Rus for that
мышление что мы их еще назовемся Русь на это
like Gold Polubotka da tipa
как Золото Полуботка да типа
I'll leave it to us right away
сразу нам оставляю
[music]
[музыка]
is it possible, I'm still asking
можно можно еще я спрашиваю
so now what are the military events
так сейчас значит какие военные события
Okrimkuska different and Baturina were on
кромекусской разные и Батурина были на
Katsapi's hands
руках кацапи
Baturyn What other similar destructions were there
Батурин Какие еще были такие похожие уничтожения
the devil of the nearby Sich in 17009 Together
чертом близкой Сечи в 17009 году Итого
with high school students
с батуриными
you raise the sources there Jacques that they are here
поднимаешь источники там Жак что они здесь
created only the population
творили только население
here or something about Kharkiv so that's it
здесь что ли кстати о Харькове так вот
often there is such a myth that he organized it there
часто там есть такой миф, что там организовал
it was founded there by the Cossack Kharko, as it were
его основал там казак Харко будто так
like this, where does it come from?
как вот какие вот откуда происходит
a good myth Long live What origin
хороший миф Да здравствует Какое происхождение
Kharkiv, and if I'm not mistaken, a little
Харьков и если я не ошибаюсь, то немножко
east of Kharkiv Oblast, there is street Chi
восточнее Харьковщины там же улицы или
Polovtsian Well, and Beredey Well?
половецкие Ну и бередейские ли Ну
Turkic-speaking peoples already lived like this and had
тюркоязычные уже народы так жили и имели
cities of the world
города мира
I know
Я знаю
except Slavyansk
кроме Славянска
the city of Kharkiv was founded Well, I don't know there
город Харьков основали Ну там я не знаю
as far as I have not yet looked at
насколько я не сильно еще смотрел на
the account of this is there as far as I am concerned
счет этого ну там насколько я
I remember there were some first ones there
помню были какие-то первые какие-то там
Freedoms and Cossacks, that is, the Cossacks are there
Свободы да казацкие есть казаки там
gradually settled there from the settlement
селялись ну постепенно там из поселения
somehow it grew there
какого-то оно выросло там
later it developed into a city
в город уже потом позже развилось
that is, so that they came, founded, said
то есть так чтобы пришли основали сказали
here will be the city of Kharkiv, like Russia
вот будут град Харьков такого нет Россия
they don't say what
не рассказывают что
In 1654, Oleksii Mykhailovych issued a decree
1654 Алексей Михайлович издал указ
incised lines and so on
засеченная черта и так далее
this is such an interesting question. So when there is
это такой быть интересный вопрос Да когда есть
the first mention of the trident and I will immediately add
первое упоминание о трезубце и я сразу добавлю
or really
действительно ли
coat of arms of the Russian Empire and the modern one
герб русской империи от современной
Russia is a coat of arms and it is a coat of arms of some kind
России - это углавир да это герб какой-то
Hordes there
там Орды
where did they get this double-headed jacket and when
откуда у них это двуглавая куртка и когда
was the first mention of the trident, I want to say
было первое упоминание трезубца хочу сказать
something interesting since I'm already so interesting
кое-что интересное раз я уже в такой интересной
company and together I haven't had it for 10 minutes
компании и вместе У меня уже 10 минут не
turning off the lights is in the Tale of Bygone Years
выключают свет в Повести временных лет
interesting phrase I also saw this on
интересная фраза Я тоже это увидел на
channel History of Russia a long, long time ago, what is this
канале в истории Руси давно-давно что это
video But it is so interesting that I fell in love
видео Но оно так интересно мне запало в
the head was there about what came to
голову было там о том что пришел к
Novgorod the Prince of Kyiv appears well
Новгорода киевский князь кажется ну
some of our Prince also writes like this in the original
какие-то наш Князь и в оригинале пишет так и
magpies of the city of Novgorod
возные стракусы отверстия града Новгорода
i.e. carousel magpies and the same
то есть возные стракусы и тем самым
opened the gates of Novgorod And surrenders
открыл ворота Новгорода И кажется
the official translation says that it is he
официальный перевод говорит что это то есть он
the bricklayer of the machine brought so that is he
стенобитный машины принес чтобы то есть он
took the author of the history channel by storm
взял штурмом, а автор канала история
Russia says that Polish language courses -
России говорит, что курсы по польскому языку -
it's teeth and tricks, you can, well, it's like that
это зубы и трикусы можно ну типа это как
version of the theory that it can be understood as
версия теория что это можно понять как
the trident, that is, the princely sign, was carried by the prince
трезубец княжеский знак вознес княжеский
a sign and thus in Novgorod what it is
знак и тем самым в новгородке что это
The prince opened the gates of Novgorod to him
Князь открыл ему ворота Новгорода
I don't know how much this theory has the right to
не знаю насколько это теория имеет право на
life, but there is such an interesting phrase there
жизнь но вот такая вот интересная там фраза есть
and three courses - It really sounds Well, I don't
и три курса – это действительно звучит Ну я не
there are no linguists and naslinguists
лингвисты и среди наслингвистов нет
Sounds interesting
Звучит интересно
regarding this tooth and this tooth in general
по отношению к этому зубу да и зуб это вообще
it's there, well, it's relative Chebetsky Yes
оно там ну такое относительная щебетская Да
there somewhere maybe some Poseidon becomes a tooth
там где-то может какие-то Посейдон становится зубом
This is an old one. I have a coin, no
такое это древнее е-е У меня есть монета не
showed, I can still show, well, an option
показывал я еще могу показать ну вариант
will not be visible
не будет видно
a coin of the Bosporan kingdom put it
монета боспорского царства ставьте стать
I just I just wanted to say something
Я только Я только хотел сказать что
the first three teeth in our territory are on
первые три зуб на нашей территории - это на
coins of the Bosphorus yes
монетах босфорского да
fourth fourth century AD it
четвертый четвертый век нашей эры это
Bosphorus Kingdom That is, this is modern Kerch
босфорское царство То есть это Керчь современная
Yes pantikapei mints such coins from
Да пантикапей чеканит Такие монеты из
I read this legend there with tridents
трезубцами я не читал там Эту легенду
Yes, that is, what did he mean there? And so on. Well
да то есть что он там означал Да и дальше Ну
this is what can be seen there, but then we him
это такое Что там видно но потом мы его
nowhere to see and you all It starts with
нигде не видим и вы все Это начинается с
two-toothed. That is, they say that running is running
двузуба То есть там говорят что бегает- бегает
there runs even two teeth appear
там бегает даже появляется два зуба
then we clearly see Svyatoslav
потом Святослава мы уже отчетливо видим
seal and then it became a trident
печать, а затем она стала трезубцем
in general, this phenomenon is interesting because if it
вообще этот феномен интересен, ибо если это
for example, an ancestral princely sign, why?
например родовой княжеский знак то почему
it changes soon from father to son
он меняется скоро от отца к сыну
every time it changes i.e. in
каждый раз он меняется то есть в
Svyatoslav we see two teeth
Святослава мы видим двузубый
[music]
[музыка]
in
в
Volodymyr already has a trident in Yaroslav's trident
Владимира уже трезубец у Ярослава трезубца
only another they make changes That is it
только другой они вносят изменения То есть это
interesting. In general, no one knows why I
интересно Вообще И никто не знает почему Я
for example, I did not hear what the tradition was for
например не слышал что была традиция а для
they were modern and everyone wore them
их это было настоящее и каждый носил
something special, they are such individualists
что-то свое они какие-то индивидуалисты
there were generally tridents from the flag
были вообще трезупцы из флага
Barbados took what you guys don't know
барбадосы взяли что вы не знаете ребята
every time By the way, a black one was jammed there
все раз Кстати зажали там черная
the red flag is the flag of Angola, that's it
красный флаг – это флаг анголы вот такое
By the way, Barbadians live if I don't
Кстати живет барбадосов если я не
I'm wrong Volodymyr the Great Yes he is
ошибаюсь Владимир Великий Да он
was baptized in Chersonesos like that. That is, it is there
крестился в херсонесе да То есть это там
where Sevastopol is modern. Yes, it is
где Севастополь современный Да есть О е-е ком
belonged to this territory, but it is often like that there
принадлежала эта территория вот часто такая там
why Tarakan principality yes
почему тараканское княжество да
how correct it was
насколько оно правильно было
do not confuse the principality with a bazaar
княжества не путай нам базарием
show this Kerch Taman Peninsula
покажите этот Керчи таманский полуостров
from there
вот туда
The Kerch Strait on both sides yes a
Керченский пролив с обеих сторон да
Chersonesus Who owned the Greek settlement
Херсонес Кому принадлежал греческий поселение
the Roman Empire, the Roman Empire, is the word
римская империи империи ромерию ибо слово
The Byzantine Empire began in the 16th century
Византийская империя приступили в 16
century then Here is this Tmutarikansky
веке тогда Вот эта тмутариканская
principality it was subordinated to Russia
княжество оно подчинялось России
whether or not this is the Chernihiv part
или это Черниговская часть
Chernihiv principality from somewhere there
Черниговского княжества из какого-то там
moment yes
момента до
And they did not enter this Circassian land
А эти земли черкессини они не входили
already
уже
second people ran because not some myths
вторые люди бегали как ни некоторые мифы
They will listen to what they heard there
послушают что там слышали ручной доходила
there, before that, to some Pyatigorsk
там ну до этого до какой-нибудь пятигорска
population reached the middle Volga in
население доходили до средней Волги в
In the 19th century, I would not be against the court
19-м веке как бы я бы не против суда
only me will spread the territory of Ukraine
распространит территорию Украины только меня
remember this, but we ask by the way
запомните такое вот еще кстати спрашиваем
ot Vladyslav Shelebit Kyiv Khazarska
от Владислав шелебит Киев хазарская
the fortress, you know where this myth came from
крепость откуда взялся этот миф знаете вот
often these Russians say that there are some
часто эти россияне говорят что там какие-то
such a fortress Java Khazarskaya was something
крепость такую ​​Ява хазарская была что-то
where did it come from this myth about which I am
откуда это взялось этот миф о которой я ибо есть
in Arabic sources but not exactly about
в Арабских источниках но не совсем о
Khazar there is a layer of Russians about the Russians
хазар там есть о русов слой ро- Руси
wear trousers wide to the elbows
носят шаровары широко там локтей
the material goes Something like that and the concept itself
материала идет Что-то такое и само понятие
Kuyava still needs to see where it is
куява здесь еще нужно посмотреть где оно
generally meets they meet
вообще встречается они встречает
Arabic Kyiv-Kuyiv is like no one here
арабский киев-куев здесь как бы никто не
Zhenya is discussing whether or not they are discussing
дискутирует или дискутируют Женя
they discuss in different ways there there this there
дискутируют по-разному там там этот там
they are guided by the fact that kuyava is the same
они же ориентируются на то что куява это же
There, like an ambassador, there was something else there
там Типа посол какой-то был там еще что-то
such a Vizier I don't know you don't remember Hai
такое Визирь Я не знаю не помните Пусть
perform in general, it is Kuyava that is there
выполняют вообще именно куява это там
it is interesting that it is found on
интересно то что оно встречается на
the territory of Poland
территории Польши
Slovakia as well as Serbia even. That is to say, this
Словакии как и Сербии даже есть это
kuyava it also means how One Earth will be
куява оно еще означает как будет Одна земля
that is, it is not a fact that it is precisely this
то есть не факт что это именно от этого
it went there, it could be a local one
пошло там оно может быть и местное какое-то
Even if there is in Arabic sources
Даже если там в Арабских источниках есть
Imagine Slavia, as if there were only three lands there
о трех словно земле одна там воображении Славия
Arcadia
Аркадия
where to sculpt him on the map Nobody knows
куда его лепить на карту Никто же не
knows where today
знает где сегодняшнего дня
by the way, someone wrote if settled
еще кстати кто-то написал если оседлыми
the south was not inhabited by people, so why?
людьми не был заселен юг и почему
the city of Wild Garden appeared in the city
появился город Дикий сад в городе
Mykolaiv is about 2,000 years old
Николаеву ему примерно 2000 лет что-то
I think here
мне кажется здесь
maybe he is a rodtsat plant 25 km below
может он завод родцат в 25 км под
Mykolaiv, I was there, a good place
Николаева я там был хорошее место.
Russians often say things like that
вещи часто знаете там русские говорят вот
there
там
The Russians founded Odessa, that is, the Germans
русские основали Одессу да т.е.
Kateryna is there with the Spaniard Deribas
Екатерина вместе там с испанцем дерибасом
and a Frenchman, this Duke de Richelieu, I do
и французом этим дюком де Ришелье Я да
I understand Turkish in Turkish settlements
понимаю турецкий по-турецки поселение
Khadzhibey made Odesa like That's how it is
Хаджибей сделали Одессу как так
can you explain what happened on the spot
можете объясните что же было на месте
Odessa as it was founded
Одессы как ее основали
and Kateryna just issued the foundation
а Екатерина только издала основание
porta on the territory of Khajibey, by the way, there
порта на территории хаджибея кстати там
Kateryna does not have the word Odesa in the rescript
слово Одесса в рескрипте нет у Екатерины
Don't make it up
Пусть не выдумывают
And what it meant was later understood
И что оно означало это позже взялось
no one knows. Well, according to such legends, where
никто не знает Ну по таким с легендам где
you can call them that, it was like Odessa
можно их так называть это типа был одесос
the ancient city is some kilometers away
античный город там где-то километров
newly captured cities with Greek names in
новозахваченные города греческими названиями в
Kateryna is like a new Greece from there
Екатерины типа оттуда новая Греция
to establish the same politics, well, Greece is
основать так же политику ну Грецию это
not a claim to Constantinople the Third
не претензия на Константинополь Третий
Rome, of course, they claim all their lives
Рим конечно претензия все жизнь
they rushed there the same way
туда рвались там же какая-то
what is this 1854, probably the Crimean War
какой это 1854 год ну это Крымская война
as if and there about the fact that Europa stands like this
словно а там о том, что Europa стоит такая
Tima Bear, which is signed by Russia and
тайма медведи который подписан Россия и
there Constantinople is so shining something
там Константинополь такие сияющий что-то
claims should this Konstantin Well they
претензий должен этот Константин Ну они
he's been like that all his life
всю жизнь тот да
konstantinopolished as tell me
константинополировались как скажи мне
they ask, by the way, have you seen the project
спрашивают кстати там Видели ли вы проект
tell a story from Ukrainian comedians
от украинских комиков расскажи историю
I don't know how to treat him
как к нему относиться не знаю что
refueled did not see shorter it is only some
заправил не видел короче это только какие-то
cells 95 quarter no By the way on account
ячейки 95 квартал нет Кстати на счет
telling the story in an unconventional way
донесение истории в нетрадиционной форме
yes
так вот
your conversations not yet see your conversations
ваши разговоры еще нет смотрите ваши разговоры
chat roulette is also a non-standard method
чат рулетке это тоже нестандартный способ
telling the story is true
донесение истории правда
the classic story came out as a teacher
классическая история вышел учитель, который так
yes yes yes yes when we look behind there
да да да да когда мы смотрим за там
srachkom two people yes Russians Ukrainians
срачком двух человек да русские украинцев
it is more interesting to us because it is a conflict between opponents
нам это интереснее потому что это конфликт оппонент
Yes, and we are always like this Oh damn, A and a bunch
Да и мы всегда такие О блин А и куча
people remember these facts Yes and therefore
людей запоминают эти факты Да и тому
I believe that if one appears
я вот считаю что если появляется какой-то
there are projects in a funny form. Yes, for example
проекты там смешной форме Да например
have you ever seen some guys writing there?
там или когда-то видел какие-то пацаны писали
about the events of Kozachchyna in the style there
о событиях Казачьи в стиле там
brotherly fights, yes, I was there
братковских разборок да вот был там
Bohdan Khmelnytskyi is there, he was there
типа там Богдан Хмельницкий он был там
sharp boy was How do you feel about
четкий пацан был Как вы относитесь к
Is it possible to submit a history of such projects?
таких проектов можно ли историю подавать
such is available to young people, for example
такое доступно молодежи, например
form
форма
you can
можете
everything That everything that is not prohibited everything is possible
все Что все что не запрещено все можно
just so that it does not pass if in
просто чтобы оно не перешло если бы в
I personally don't like this kind of circus
какой-то этот цирк не палкой Мне лично
the idea came to convey this to the opponent because
пришла идея доносить так с оппонентом
I knew that when such things happened to me
я знал что когда мне случались такие
facts, such documents, as I already said
факты такие документы какие вот как я уже
said from which the jaw hangs down I knew what
говорил от которых челюсть отвисает Я знал что
Muscovites will not be able to play roulette in any way
московиты в чат рулетке не смогут никак
I can't seem to master them
мне ну типа овладеть никак они
such things are disarming and I knew that in
обезоруживают такие вещи и я знал что в
I had a feeling that it would be interesting
меня было ощущение что это будет интересно
I was interested and people will be interested
мне было интересно и людям будет интересно и
therefore, a very cool question is whether Yevgeny is writing
поэтому очень классный вопрос Евгений пишет или
Ukrainians were once called Cherkassy Ya
назывались как-то украинцы Черкассами Я
let me clarify, that is, whether the city of Cherkasy has one
уточню есть город Черкассы
relation to these Circassians, let's say
отношение к этим черкесам, которые скажем
live there in Russia, I wanted this question
живут там в России я хотел этот вопрос
to put Mr. Vitaly
поставить п Виталию
and official Russian sources
и официальных российских источниках мы
Cherkassy were called That is, it is an ethnonym as
Черкассами назывались То есть это этноним как
it is an exo ethnonym of Ukrainians
это экзо этноним украинцев
Let's just say it has nothing to do with Cherkasy
Скажем так к Черкассам нет отношения
yes to the city of Cherkasy
в город Черкассы да
the city was named after the ethnonym, there is even one there
по этнониму назвали город там даже есть
I don't remember any maps. Well, not a map
карты какая-то и не помню Ну не карта
it is called something like a draft of Ukrainian and
называется чоткеж чертёж украинских и
Cherkasy towns
черкасских городов
all documents written in Ukrainian
все документы, которые писали на украинский
Belarusian is Russian, they are in them
белорусском это русском языке они у них
official is written in Belarusian script like this
официальная писана белорусским письмом да
he was singled out and singled out
он так себе определили и определили
for myself, this does not mean that it is over
для себя это же не значит что оно по
written in Belarusian
белорусское написано
see tatal question
смотрите вопрос татал
Tatar-Mongolian Ihor is very much so
татаро-монгольские Игр так вот очень
I often met different people there
часто Я встречал там разные
there were no alternatives at all
альтернативные что вообще не было никаких
there is Tatar-Mongol and that's just there
там татаро-монгол да что это просто там
artificial term and so on you can
искусственный термин и так далее вот можете
to explain what Ihor's father was up to
объяснить в чем заключалось папа Игорь
But so-called as it is called correctly
И так называемое как его правильно называть
were the Mongols here like that or they just
были ли здесь монголы так или они просто
were once there as a military force and
были как-то там военной силой а
placed their governors Chi there
ставили своих там наместников Или
we have left a Mongolian trace through
оставшийся у нас монгольский след через
this and so on. As far as I know the Mongols
это и так далее Насколько я знаю монголы
constituted only the top of the Mongols
составляли только верхушку монголов было
as now there are not many. That is, it's all a rush
как и сейчас немного То есть это все нашествие
it was also a mixture of different ones
это была так же смесь разных
Turkic tribes there and so on
племен там тюрок и так далее
Modern Mongols are different Mongols. Well, maybe
современные монголы это разные монголы Ну может
Let's start with the fact that they are different. Well, that's it
Идем с того а чем они разные ну это
People's Christmas We are not Ruthenians, we are Ukrainians
Рождество народа Мы же не русины Мы Украинцы
This is different. Yes, the bulk of the troops were there
это другое Да там основная масса войска были
Kipchaks as far as I am Well, because I read
котчаки насколько я Ну потому что я читал
everyone agreed that we are Ruthenians, Ruthenians
всем согласился что мы русины русины
For Ukrainians, it is very different, even literally
Украинцы это очень разное еще буквально на
in the west of Ukraine Well, let's say there
западе Украины Ну скажем там
today, my great-grandfathers could still Ya
сегодняшнего мои прадеды еще могли Я
already a Ukrainian, only the difference is small
уже украинец только разница То небольшая
the mongols were admirable was a concept
монголы были восхищение было концепции
the yoke has been changed by a comrade who is there, Lord
ига передумана товарищем кем там Господи
Simple quarantine in my opinion. She is not
простые карантин по-моему Она же не
substantially
стабильно
seized the territory under the control of the tribute
захватили подконтрольную территорию дань
we paid for a certain time If you want
мы платили определенное время Если вы хотите
you can ask a specific question in
конкретно вопросы задать можете в
Write Telegram, I will drop the link because in
Telegram написать я скину ссылку потому что в
chat they can get lost a little
чаты они могут немного потеряться Я
I read the lesson, but if anything
читаю участок поглядываю но если что-то
it will be interesting, it will be interesting, it is possible
интересное будет какое-то интересующее можно можно
there is a question about this
какой-то такой вот вопрос по этому
sons for virgins question also reasons
сыновей за девы вопросы также причины
appearance of the term Ukraine and Ukrainians on
появления термина Украина и украинцы на
as a counterweight to all the aspens
противовесом все и осины
what do you think about this weather Well 19
что вы думаете по этому погоды Ну 19
century when it was already determined that
век когда было уже определено что
Ukrainian language Little Russian adverb in
украинский язык Малороссийский наречие в
Russian interpretation was clear
русской интерпретации было понятно
that it is a separate language, that we have our own history
что это отдельный язык что у нас своя история
and the names are similar to the world, but they are Russian
а названия похожи мируские А они русские то
our elite adopted the term
наша элита взяла на вооружение срок
of Ukraine in order to separate itself This
Украина для того чтобы отделить себя
began at the beginning of the XIX century and
началось еще в начале XIX века и
actually took hold at the end of the 19th century
фактически закрепилась в конце 19-го
century in order to separate
век для того чтобы отделить
the history of our people from the history of those for
историю нашего народа от истории тех за
porebryky Zalej rights by the Germans
поребриковых залейских правах немцами
Cossacks called themselves very much in documents
казаки себя называли в документах очень
Let's say so very often and very much and
Скажем так очень часто и очень много и
We the people meet very picturesquely
очень живописно встречается Мы народ
Christian, Ukrainian, and so on
христианские украинский и так далее другое
the matter is what they meant by this but
дело что они имели под этим в виду но
it can be called so prevailed
это можно назвать таким преобладающим
in Russian to local Russian and Naukova
по-русски на местные русские Научная
such a name Yes that Based on the sources
такое название Да что Опираясь на источники
NATO something find something We are not Russian
НАТО что-то найти что-то Мы же не русский и
Russians so that they are not like royalty
русские чтобы не было как гонорарды
Honolei is interested in the question
гонолея вопрос интересует
were the things of the Scythians ordered by the Slavs
были ли скифы вещи порядками славян
in general Yes How many Scythians Sarmatians
вообще Да На сколько Скифы сарматы
connected culturally genetically with
связаны культурной генетически со
the Slavs
славянами
as genetically unrelated
как генетически не связаны
cultural is also not related Otzhenyakh says
культурная тоже не связана отженях говорит
they had some place like for example
они имели какое-то место так как например
the same patients, but it was like that
те же терпелки но это было такое
indirectly, that is, there were some there
опосредованное то есть были какие-то там
mixing yes well Scythian things must be on
смешивание да ну Скифы вещи имеется в
keep in mind that maybe it was something there
в виду что возможно это была какая-то там
pre-Slavic population
предославянское население
it was predominantly agricultural there
она была там преобладающей земледельческой
she was like that. Well, she was no longer like those
она такая Ну больше не похожа была на тех
Scythians, royal Scythians who were on
скифов скифов царских которые были на
south. That is, it can be seen that they are there
юге То есть это видно что они там я на
the language of some nomads there, and these are the names
языковые какие-то кочевники а эти именно
they sold bread there, and they were farmers
там торговали хлебом да земледельцы они
such more Let me say something Because
такие более Позвольте я кое-что скажу Бо
when people ask if ours are there
когда люди спрашивают, есть ли там те наши
ancestors, those are our ancestors in relation to me
предками те нашими предками мне есть относительно
I suppose I am not a geneticist to say this
этого сказать я предполагаю я не генетик
for a historian for an archaeologist, but I assume
на историк на археолога, но я предполагаю
that all those tribes, all those peoples who lived
что все те племена, все те народы, которые жили
some long time on our territory
какие-то длительное время на территории нашей
land, one way or another, is the offending measure
земли так или иначе в той мере являюсь
our genetic ancestors are simply ot
нашими генетическими предками просто есть вот
I will not say one Russian blogger
один русский блоггер я не буду говорить
who but I think most people know who it is
кто но я думаю большинство знает кто это это
very great blogger He is quite interesting
очень большой блоггер Он достаточно интересен
such different scientific things
такой разные научные вещи
he somehow made popular science
научно-популярный он как-то сделал
video about just about genetics about who
видео о как раз о генетике о том кто
what is the prefix who is or is their ancestor and
чем есть префикс кто е или им предок и
there was such a fact that for example as
имелось такой факт что например как
this Charlemagne is so European
этот Карл Карл Великий да европейский
This king is such that the French are His
Этот король такой, что Французы Его
consider, well, in general, He said that everyone
считают ну в общем Он говорил что каждый
a modern European is every white Caucasian
современный европеец каждый белый европеоид
has a part of this Karl's genes in him
есть имеющая в себе частицу генов этого Карла
because in the past there was very little
потому что в прошлом было очень мало
there are very few people, for example
людей очень мало людей то вот вот например
every European there a thousand years ago
там тысячу лет назад каждый европеец
more precisely, a modern European almost has genes
точнее современные европеец почти имеет гены
of every European in the past, that is, it
каждого европейца в прошлом есть оно
everything is so confusedly connected there that
там так все перепутано связано что
Genetically, it probably flows in each of us
генетически видимо у нас в каждом течении
the blood or the blood of many of those tribes flows
кровь или у многих течет кровь тех племен
those peoples who lived in this territory
тех народов, которые жили на этой территории
someone there, for example, the Slavs can
кто-то там например славяне могут
leave more Well those whom we consider
оставить больше Ну тех кого мы считаем
the Slavs left more offspring because
славянами оставили большее потомство
there for some reason at the beginning of the era As far as I am
там почему-то в начале у эры Насколько я
I know there was a demographic riot in the word I
знаю был демографический бунт в слове я
if I'm wrong, then the historians are me
если я неправ то историки меня
will correct it somehow like this here
поправят поэтому вот как-то так здесь
Mrs. Olga from Chatusha does not quarrel with me
ссорится на меня госпожа Ольга из чатуши не
everyone has a Telegram Ms. Olga Yes, it's just me
у всех есть Telegram госпожа Ольга Да я просто
there is definitely a question in the telegram that I will not miss
в телеграмме есть точно не пропущу вопрос
here they are, and the chat is running, but yours
вот они есть а чат этого бегущего но ваше
question I found Mrs. Olga asks
вопрос Я нашел госпожа Ольга спрашивает
where Roksolana actually comes from
откуда на самом деле происходит Роксолана
Roksolana is an artistic myth
Роксолана – это художественный миф так или
really a character who later became a myth
действительно персонаж, который позже стал мифом
Where is she from?
Так откуда она
no one knows I don't know this more than anything
никто не знает Не знаю это больше всего
literary myth under which they ask well
литературный миф под которого спрашивают ну
you know, that is, the personality is really like that
знаете то есть реально личность такая
Manieva was in the village. She is lying there
была в деревне маниево Она там лежит
together with the beloved
вместе с любимой
Suleymanov is the burial place of Roksolana Where from
сулейманов есть погребение Роксоланы Откуда
it is from a Polish romantic story
она это из польской романтической истории
geography went into this myth of the Poles
географии ушел в этот миф поляки
painted then that she was Polish
расписывали тогда что она полька Мы
of course, in the 19th century they wrote that she
конечно в 19 веке написали что она
Ukrainka for Rohatyn Whatever
Украинка за Рогатина Хотя что того
there is no document about it, it is like this
документа об этом не существует это такой
watch a beautiful myth, let it live
прекрасный миф да здравствует смотрите
an astronaut from Kryvyi Rih asks a lot
астронавт из Кривого Рога спрашивает очень
interesting stories of the settlement of Jews on
интересные истории поселения евреев на
the territory of modern Ukraine, please advise
территории современной Украины посоветуйте
literature and Tell something a little about
литературу и Расскажите что-нибудь немного о
it
это
Let them look for Johannes Petrovsky's book
Пусть ищут книгу йоханеса Петровского
shterna is called a shtetl, a chic book
штерна называется штетл шикарная книга
about Jews in the territory of Ukraine
о евреях на территории Украины
based on writing about the 17th and 18th centuries, but
основе пишет о 17-18 веке
model on the territory of Ukraine
модель на территории Украины
lived from the 9th century We live together with
с 9-го века жил Мы живем вместе с
Jews in our territories
евреями на наших территориях
The Jewish settlement is Jewish as it is
еврейская деревня еврейская как она и
the community appeared somewhere in the ninth
община появилась что где-то в девятом
the tenth is the question of the Khazar Khaganate
десятом вопросе о Хазарском каганате
on the territory how does he fit in
на территории как он вот вписывается в
history of Ukraine
историю Украины
Psaltivo boyak culture as they want
псалтиво боячья культура как хотят таки
enter
вписывают
did not interact in any way interacted for everything
никак взаимодействовали взаимодействовали за все
occupied a certain territory mainly this
занимали определенную территорию в основном это
eastern some south-eastern suburbs
восточные какие-то юго-восточные окраины
the interaction was normal
было взаимодействие обычное
about Roksolana yesterday and now it's the same
о Роксолане вчера а сейчас это так же
Russian chauvinism is Russian
русский шовинизм русский эта
mythmaking is it
мифотворчество это оно
it covered these Khazars, here they are
оповило эту этих хазаров вот они еще
not the old Nestorzhesh is interpreted as either
трактуют не старая несторж тоже как
monk he wrote it there in his own way a
монах он там по-своему это написал а
now it can also be called the Union
сейчас это так же можно сказать Союз
tribes, if there was Khazaria, it is not
племен если там была хазария это не
means that all there were Khazars and I
означает что Все там были хазары да Я
I would like to clarify that the Khazar culture is something like that
уточню что хазарская культура это ну такое
political name because by movement
политическое название потому что по движению
the archeology or the Alans can tell you there
может подскажет там археологическая или аланы
or the Bulgarians And here is Alan Bulgarian
или булгары И вот Алана Болгарские
the settlement is politically called
поселение политически называется
Khazarian pencil Azari A documents
хазарским олівцем азари А документы
know Kozar Kozar their dialogue The main thing
знают Козар Козар свое диалог Главное
that these are Alans and Bulgarians, and the Khazars are such
что это аланы и болгары а хазары – это такая
some general name for this
какое-то общее название этой
of the Salto-Mayan culture, that is, they
салтово-майской культуры есть они
they practiced Judaism there only in my way
исповедовали иудаизм там только по-моему
the top and not well not the entire time span
верхушка и не ну не весь промежуток времени
somehow And it is not a fact that they professed it
как-то и не факт что они его исповедовали
there was such a bun for today
был такой пузырь вот на сегодняшний
day, in my opinion, will say what is being discussed before
день по-моему скажет что дискутируется к
today
сегодняшнего дня
that is not certified by any such
то что не удостоверен какими-то такими
more literate with these slingshots there
более грамотными этими рогатки там где
they will all be cloudy very It is very
они все такое будет мутно очень Это очень
interesting situation
интересная ситуация
the monograph of the raft and prokhazar and that's it
монографию плотного и прохазаря да и все
the user asks why
вопрос вот спрашивает пользователь почему есть
the tendency of the disintegration of great powers on
тенденция распада великих держав на
small, for example, Czech words ie
маленькие например Чехии слова т.е.
was the Austro-Hungarian Empire
была австро-венгерская империя
the Spring of Nations collapsed on him there
развалилась на нем там Весна народов
arose. That's why there was a period of consolidation
восстала Вот почему был период укрупнения
yes, the Empire has now gone this way
да Империя а теперь вот пошла вот на эту
the formation can be said to be an empire
образование можно так сказать империи это
not ethnic
не этнические
creation on the state Yes we are about
создание на государственные Да мы же о
why are the states disintegrating now?
государственные почему вот сейчас идет распад государств
on national Why you Such process
на национальный Почему вы Такой процесс
went
ушел
because after the peace of Westphalia
потому что после вестфальского мирного
of the contract, more precisely in 1648, won
договора точнее 1648 победил
the principle of building a national state a
принцип построения национального государства а
not an empire
не империи
And why so I would say simplified this way
А почему так я бы сказал упрощенно этот путь
humanity in such links, but in the Link of the genus
человечества на таких звеньях вот на Ланке род
Tribe, nation, ethnic nation, so-and-so. No, that's it
Племя нация этносная нация так Нет ну вот
what happened they lived there for example
что произошло жили там например
different peoples, empires, and then
разные народы вот империи а вот потом
realistically How did it explode like that, not all of it
реально Как взорвалось да все нет все это
you raise a logical question to everyone
логический вопрос поднимаешь оно же каждому
a specific historical issue
конкретном историческом вопросе
is decided in different ways, of course, that is
решается по-разному обычно то есть
a specific historical period may be necessary
нужно может конкретный исторический период
specifically comb everything and say which one
именно гребенку все и сказать какой
The empire of empires is the size of some empire
Империя империи размер какая-то Империя
held on to the power of the Sword, so to speak
держалась на силе Меча так сказать
somehow brought civilization there everything
какая-то приносила цивилизацию там все
differently
по разному
Yes
да
can i ask a question
могу задать вопрос
Why Grozny considered himself a descendant
Почему Грозный считал себя потомком
Caesar
Цезаря
at least Caesar's mares are his problem and we are
хоть кобылы Цезаря это его проблема а мы
only
только
Oleksii Mykhailovych Oleksii Mykhailovych
Алексей Михайлович Алексей Михайлович
who is in contact with Bohdan Khmelnytskyi
который с Богданом Хмельницким контактовым
called a descendant of Julius Caesar in them there
именовал потомком Юлия Цезаря у них там
it was fashionable to write one's pedigree begins
было модно написать себе родословную начинает
I remembered Adam and Eve, that was cool
отгадал и Адама и Евы это же было круто
Listen, Yurik, and this is Zaitsev from one
Слушай да Юрик и вот это Зайцев из одного
it was written correctly, I did not hear anything from
того правильно писали я что-то не слышал от
Adama and I say yes, but such You understand
Адама и я говорю да но такие Понимаешь
there was some kind of trick, but they wanted
были какая-то такая фишка вот Они хотели
to get attached to all of them there, if only
примазаться там к этим всем если бы
Well, this is normal for elite people
Ну это нормально для элитных людей
of every nation Every nation went through this
каждого народа Каждый народ проходил такое
stage I, and if I'm not mistaken, then in y
этап я же и если не ошибаюсь то у
France has some kind of dynasty from eh
Франции какая-то династия от е-е
as this descendant of Christ somehow too
как этот потомков Христа как-то тоже
tried to bring out everything, well, everyone
пробовали выводить да все ну каждый
question I will tell you more, I don't, I don't
вопрос Я вам больше скажу я не я не
she typed, read what is written there
набрал она прочти там такого написано
I never thought about it, but here it is
я над этим никогда не задумывался но вот
just recently found out what this is
буквально недавно узнал что есть такое
the concept of anti-Semitism in general Semites and
понятие антисемитизм вообще семиты и
we call it like a group of peoples
мы это называем как группа народов
but what is Simite anyway? It's from Sim
но что такое вообще симити Это же от Сима
no one says I'm Fet. Well, I'm a Fetite
никто не говорит я есть Фет Ну я фетиты бо
we are supposed to be European nations in particular
якобы европейские народы мы в частности есть
the descendants are Feta Semenoya and there are others there
потомками являются Фета семеноя и есть еще кто там
was with it Ham and Effect and there are none
был с этим Хам и Эффект и нет там их
there were four, I think I'm already on which one
четверо было кажется я уже по какой
theories of type in the order of the Old Testament
теории типа по порядку Ветхий завет
You can't say that the Old Testament had a Bible
Ветхий завет тот имел Библии не скажешь и
there are descendants, it's already like that, then what And what
есть потомки, это уже так, потом что И что
allegedly, Europeans are the children of Japhet, well, the descendants
якобы европейцы дети яфета ну потомки
epheta and so on. That's all we are
эфета и так далее Вот и это все мы
was preserved, but it was preserved to turn blue
сохранилось но вот синеты сохранилось что
supposedly even still there is such a scientific one
якобы даже до сих пор такой научный
the term anti-Semitism, although the concept of the summit -
термин антисемитизм хотя понятие саммит -
it islike this
это Да есть
yes, a whole group of peoples yes And what else
да целая группа народов да А какое еще
Tatiana wrote
Татьяна написала
ask about serfdom when Ot
спросить о крепостном праве когда
for example, the fortifications of villagers took place in
например произошли закрепощения крестьян в
In Ukraine, that is, it was written in 1783
Украине так есть от 1783 да написано
that is, it turns out to 1785 and the second
то есть получается до 1785, а второй
Lithuanian Statute
Литовский устав
1900 is for the Russian Empire
1900 это за русское Империя это
called the second fortification of the peasants
называется второе закрепощение крестьян которое
began as a result of the price revolution
началось в результате революции цен
was the result of the discovery of America
была результатом открытия Америки
the opening of America to Eastern Europe gave
открытие Америки на восточную Европу дало
a very negative consequence in that
очень негативное последствие в том плане что
the spread of serfdom began
началось распространение крепостного права
in the gold that was imported to Europe fell in
в золото ввозимое в Европу упало в
food prices became extremely expensive
цены продовольствие стали стоить чрезвычайно
dear
дорого
region where food products are grown
регион, где выращивают пищевые продукты
Central and Eastern Europe is Poland and
центральной и Восточной Европы это Польша и
Ukraine and so on to the East and the division of Prussia
Украина и вот на восток и дельбы пруссия
Poland-Ukraine and the process started from there
польша-украина и оттуда начался процесс
settlement of peasants in these regions became
закрепощение крестьян это регионы стали
to deliver to Europe at a price through grain
поставлять в Европу в цену через зерно
through Ford Gdansk which became
через Форда Гданьск который стал
instantly a very rich city
моментально очень богатым городом
and this was the case for Eastern Europe
и это для Восточной Европы имело такое
deplorable consequences of the consolidation of the peasantry
плачевное последствия закрепощения крестьянства
while serfdom disappeared even there in
пока крепостное право пропало еще там в
the ninth century wants a day on account
девятом веке хотят сутки на счет
this
этого
after all, she did not have a Hetmanship
все же Гетманщина Она же не имела
serfs, that is, they are state peasants there
крепостных То есть там государственные крестьяне они
paid into the state decree, as if taxes
платили в государственную указную как бы налоги
well, personally, they were free, yes, personally
ну лично были свободны да да лично
were free But then when she came
были свободны Но потом когда пришла
It is the Russian Empire
Российская империя она
1783 Yes So small as if there will be a stream
1783 Да Так маленький будто да стрим будет
the saved stream will be recorded only
сохраненный стрим будет записан единое
look, we agreed on what to do
смотрите мы договаривались что да будет до
21:30 If you have the opportunity, maybe
21:30 Если у вас будет возможность может
continue you get to continue Well
продолжить вам удается продолжить Ну
I can give a little more 10 if there is a witness if
могу еще немного 10 если есть свидетель если
deliver 5,000 likes people stay Yes
доставить 5 000 лайков люди остаются Да
the question for the experts is also How
вот к экспертам вопрос тоже такой Как
to you historian Andriy Baitsar and his book
вам историк Андрей бойцарь и его книга
of Ukraine and Ukrainians in Europe
Украины и украинцы на Европейских
ethnographic maps
этнографических картах
Tatars appeared in the Crimea, who are their ancestors?
татары появились в Крыму кто их предки и
how did such a nationality come about?
как сложилось такая национальность
there how much Well can I start you there
там насколько Ну я могу начать вы там
continue because I'm not an expert in this
продолжите потому что я в этом не эксперт какой
maybe in Russian because that's how I understood it
может українською потому что я так понял какой
I didn't ask either, it's Crimean dads
не спросил ни там это Крымские папы они
it is considered more like a local one
считается более как местным каким-то
population that is, when they came already
население то есть когда пришли уже
Mongols There Well, I don't remember where I read it
монголы Туда Ну я не помню, где это читал
uh, it's not so simple, as well as here
э-э да не уж просто
10 months of population got mixed up and that's it
перемешались 10 месяц населенный и вот
how would the ethno come out of this later
как бы вышел потом этно из этого
Crimean Crimean Tatars, but I can
Крымского крымских татар но я могу
make a mistake
ошибаться
promyralsya on the basis of those peoples who
промирался на основе тех народов
lived in the south of Ukraine, this place is theirs
жили на юге Украины это место это их
family is the place of formation
семья - это место формирование именно
Crimean people, they do not know where they are
крымскотарского народа они нет угол
come
пришли
the Crimean Tatar population is not
крымскотатарское население – это не
What about the people who settled in the Crimea?
кочего и народ который осел в Крыму да
it turns out they are just a people who
получается они просто народ который
mixed with the theme of swings
смешался с теми качельниками
is a collection of certain ethnicities which
является е-е совокупностью определенных этностей, которые
lived in a certain territory of migration
проживали на определенной территории миграции
that no one canceled, but before in the Crimea, that is
что же никто не отменял а в Крыму
countries, it is also the autochthonous people of Crimea
страны это тоже автохтонный народ Крыма или
came
пришли
in my opinion, this is the local population
по-моему это местное население, которое
accepted Judaism
приняли иудаизм
if I'm not mistaken, then in this
я если не ошибаюсь то в этом в
protection from the country to the Principality of Lithuania
княжестве Литовском охрана из страны
was like that
была так и
at the prince's No, I don't remember because I was just there
у князя Нет я не помню потому что я был просто
when in Lithuania there is a settlement this Trakai
когда в Литве там есть поселение этот Тракай
The capital was still for me
мне столица была ли еще тогда то что вот как
of the Swiss Guard at the Pope's da
швейцарских Гвардии у Папы Римского да
so they said that the countries are still there
так говорили что страны там до сих пор
Karaite streets remained
остались караимские эти если улицы или
as if they were not recruited from the local Ascariani
будто набирали не из местных аскарийной
situation because it is simply a center of emigration
ситуации ведь просто центром эмиграции
Crimean Tatars the first Islam and
крымских татар первый же ислам и
hey, he's coming out of Lithuania
герай он же выходит из Литвы
yes, it's cool that someone put him there
да прикольно его же посадил кто там на
throne in the Crimean Khanate which
трон в Крымском ханстве который
the Lithuanian prince supported him
литовский князь поддержал его
Boxing question, which European country
вопрос к боксу какая страна Европы
I am most similar in history to Ukraine
историей наиболее схоже с Украиной я
even thought about it
даже задумался
that can be found
что хоть можно найти
Yes, Makhno is a hero or not. Guys, what do you think?
да Махно герой или нет Парни что думаете
about moss
о мохне
and everything is so clear if the hero of Ukraine
и все так однозначно если герой Украины
then probably as if he is an anarchist he is for
то пожалуй будто он анархист он для
Ukraine was not particularly important to him
него Украина особо значения не было
against Ukraine First
против Украины Сначала
a narco-communist, he fought against any
нарко-коммунис он воевал против любой
the state against Denikinians against
государства против деникинцев против
Ukrainian state UNR v
Украинского государства УНР против
Bolsheviks because he is anarchist
большевиков поскольку он анарг в
a communist He entered into alliances very often
коммунист Он вступал очень часто в союзы
zbolsheviks Well, that's what killed him
увеличителями Ну что его и погубило
the Union spoke
выступал Союз
these Karakalpaks are the ones that are currently in the territory
эти каракалпаки те что сейчас находятся на территории
Uzbekistan
Узбекистана
pakistan They are related to blacks
пакстан Они имеют отношение к черным
clubs that once existed in Russia
клубов которые были вот когда-то на Руси
simply
просто
ascent
восхождение
suffered
понесло
Somehow she is in a wild state there today
как-то дикое состояние она какая-то там сегодня
a ball is generally some kind of tulki or what
клубок это вообще это какие-то тюльки да какие
Well, as it is written, some tulki are written
Ну как пишет пишется какие-то тюльки какие
fled, they were resettled on the border everywhere
бежали их селили на границе за всю
download from nomads to First strike
закачать от кочевников да Первый удар
was called in the annals of ours
был какая-то называется в летописи наши
bad That is, who have switched to our side
плохое есть перешедшие на нашу сторону
that is, the bad thing here is not that they are bad
то есть здесь плохое это не то что они плохие
and the fact that they are not Christians, yes
а то что они не христианские да
By the way, but after acceptance
Кстати, а вот после принятия
900, like ours in 988. Yes, Volodymyr
900 вот как у нас 988 году Так Владимир
baptized Rus' as much as this one
крестил Русь так же, как и этот
the process stretched across the territory of Ukraine
процесс растянулся по территории Украины
Well, modern Ukraine, I don't think so
Да ну современной Украины Я же не думаю что
as
как
Zelensky and Poroshenko issued a decree there
выдал там Зеленский Или Порошенко указ
And if everyone started to believe there and
Да и все если бы начали там верить и
how new is this process
по-новому вот насколько этот процесс
Christianization of these territories stretched
христианизации этих территорий растянулся
in time and across the border to these bodies
во времени и по поребрику в эти органы
Christ lives Andrii
Христи живут Андрей
Well, we have finished
Ну у нас есть кончился
essential As far as I know for a long time I cannot
существенные Насколько я знаю надолго Не могу
You can't take it like that and quickly, you understand
Нельзя так и быстро, ты понимаешь
here as if to say
здесь если бы сказать
christianization always takes from those
христианизация всегда берет из тех
beliefs that were in that area
верований, которые были на той местности
some trophies, that is, we still have traditions
какие-то трофеи есть у нас до сих пор есть традиции
which
какие
trace their roots back to those times
уходят своими корнями от тех времен до
Christian there, everything on Ivan Kupala
христианских там всякое на Ивана Купала
those fires there are pagan
там эти костры это же языческие
that is if you If you ask
то есть если вы Если вы спросите
how far the Christianization has spread
насколько растянулись христианизация?
it's still autumn
до сих пор осень
Easter eggs are the same
на Пасху писанки это тоже
pre-Christian tradition that is
дохристианская традиция то есть
Christian reading as they are written Yes, but
христианское чтение как они написаны Да но
you can also say that this does not mean that before
можно еще сказать что это не означает что до
Volodymyr was not here, there were Christians
Владимира здесь не было христиан было и
most likely, it is written aristovych a lot
скорее всего много пишется аристович
you said that two or three weeks will be noticed
вы сказали что два-три недели на заметят
Yes
да
good yes except Zaporizhia Cossacks Yaki
хорош так кроме запорожских казаков
were there still Cossacks and were they called at all?
еще были казаки и вообще назывались ли
they are Zaporizhzhya Cossacks and
они запорожскими казаками а
Zaporozhye grassroots army Well, first
войско Запорожское низовое Ну сначала
the Zaporizhzhya army and then the Poles
войско Запорожское, а затем поляки
made their Zaporozhian army even then
сделали свое войско Запорожское и тогда
Cossacks said we will be an army
казаки сказали, а мы будем войско
I won't finish Zaporizhzhia because somehow
Запорожское не завершу.
to be counted like this, egg Cossacks ladies
отсчитываться так яицкий казаки дамский
Cossacks, Cossacks are Hajduks in Serbia
казаки казаки это гайдуки в Серби это
a normal phenomenon on the border between
нормальное явление на пограничные между
agricultural and nomadic civilization
земледельческой и кочевой цивилизации
such a group always appears
всегда появляется такая группа
Servigalov, which they are starting to beat here
сервигалов которое начинают колотить здесь
the truth of all Cossacks
свое государство правда из всех казаков
only we created our state
только мы создали свое государство
The constitution is there. No, that's later
Конституция там Нет ну это уже позже
was
было
the rest is just like border protection
остальные просто как пограничная такая защита
er, you still say p Vitaliy between er
е-е еще вы говорите п Виталий между е-е
civilizations and nomads always
цивилизациями и кочевыми всегда
starting from Serbia through Ukraine
начиная от Сербии через Украину
Danish Cossacks eggs said Uralic
датское казачество яиц сказал уральский
Cossacks is a whole such border strip
казачества это целая такая полоса пограничная
but but Ukrainian Cossacks it is
но но украинское казачество оно
special because special Because it is the only one
ибо особенно потому, что оно единое
essentially created such state forms
создало по существу государственные формы такие
management itself was provided, but it was not
предоставлено было само управление ну оно не
had such a form of state as we have
имела такой формы государства как у нас
you can have another question about this on the same topic
можно еще вопрос по этому по этой же теме
somewhere somewhere here I saw Yes
где-то я здесь видел Да
communication
связь
Just the same number of rows. Here is the first connection
Как раз рядов А вот связь первая
hetmans of Sichi by the factory of the princes of Kyiv
гетманов Сечи заводом князей Киевских
there were certain princely Yes there since time immemorial
были определенные княжеские Да там еще со времен
there and the Russian voivodeship from the kingdom
там и русского воеводства из королевства
Some Russians may have stayed there
Русь может какие-то оставались там на
the example of Vyshnevetskyi of Ostrog
примере острожских Вишневецкого
were they difficult to say Well, if you take
были ли трудно сказать Ну если брать
he is generally from the family of Vyshnevetskyi
байду Вишневецкого он вообще из рода
Hediminovych he to our princes and
гедиминовичей он к нашим князьям и
adopted no he by origin from
принято нет он по происхождению из
Lithuanians roughly speaking, we are his
литовцев грубо говоря это мы его
we record in the Ukrainians, and he is Prince
записываем в украинцев, а он Княжий
of the princely Lithuanian family and so that with
княжеского Литовского рода а так чтобы с
by ours, but it is actually Teos
нашими А вот теосский он уже собственно
Ostrozky proved that he was related
Острожский доказывал, что он имеет отношение
to the princes of Russia, well, again, this is a period
к князьям Руси ну опять-таки это период
fashion when they wrote to themselves as Ivan the Terrible
моды когда писали себе как Ивану грозному
Eyes
Эти
genealogical trees, that is, disappeared
гениалогические древа То есть пропал
By the way, name the best question there
Кстати вот вопрос там назовите самый лучший
I don't know which period in the history of Ukraine
период в истории Украины не знаю по какому
they want the best, so they said that it is golden
хотят лучший так говорили что золотой
day for Ukraine and there is no Golden Age A
сутки для Украины и нет Золотой эпохи А
I will say that now because firstly never
я скажу что сейчас как первый никогда
there were not as many fats in the butter as before
не было столько жиров в масле как как
now, that is, modern man is stretching
сейчас то есть растягивает современный человек
just generally has access to such
просто в общем имеет доступ к такой
medicine to which neither emperors nor those
медицины в которую ни императоры ни те
emperors who are generally from the gods
императоры которые себя вообще от богов
they never had their pedigrees
вели свои родословные никогда не имели
I would bite you and you would die of anaphylactic shock
укусила бы и ты умер от анафилактического
shock now the poorest person has the best
шока сейчас самый бедный человек имеет лучший
medicine in general calorie consumption in
медицину в целом потребление калорий в
There is a broad meaning of this word man
Широком смысле этого слова человека есть
bigger and a plus if you start a war
большей и плюс если уж брать войну
despite the fact that many people accuse me of something
несмотря на то что многие меня обвиняют что
And how do we fight? We never had
А как же мы воюем? Мы никогда не имели
such
таких
Let's put it this way. We never have that much
Скажем так Нам никогда столько не
helped to fight for Ukraine now
помогали как сейчас воевать за Украину
it was always somehow always difficult
всегда как-то вот было сложно всегда
surrounded by enemies Always someone wanted
окружены врагами Всегда кто-то хотел
divide and here in the west of the country
поделить здесь на западе страны
before we were sandwiched between the east and
раньше мы были зажаты между востоком и
the west now, the West is for us, but with us
закатом сейчас Запад за нас вот у нас
there is no It's calm in the west now
нет Вот этого сейчас на мероприятии спокойно
and we can and plus we have a lot
и мы можем и плюс нам очень много
they help. By the way, I always do too
помогают Ну кстати я вот тоже всегда
I say Yes, what if Well, we often have what if
говорю Да что если Ну у нас часто если бы у
people have such a search for this as Golden
людей есть такой поиск этой как Золотой
the days that used to be beaten better, you know how this one is
суток что раньше били лучше знаете как эта
the picture that reaches home is two sitting
картинка что дома доходит сидят две
monkeys And now it's cool
обезьяны А теперь уже самый классно да как вот
that is, if we take 100 even there
то есть если мы берем еще даже там 100
years ago, we didn't have any
лет назад наши де рады где не имели
there is an electrician, we are now oh damn light
там электрик мы сейчас ой блин свет
turned off yes For us it is game and they
отключили да Для нас это дичь а они
lived in such conditions, that's why I also say that
жили в таких условиях поэтому я тоже говорю что
you don't have to look for it, so to speak, and never
не надо искать вот говоря и никогда
there was no such unity of Ukrainians. Well, no
не было такого единства украинцев.Ну нет
I know at the expense of unity, it seems to me
знаю на счет единения Мне кажется
there were earlier periods
были раньше периоды
yes, although it is actually philosophical
да хотя на самом деле это философское
the question is because if you take fats in oil then
вопрос ведь если брать жиры в масле то
Of course, now the best A if measured
Конечно, самая лучшая А если мерить
by other measures
другими мерами
about the question of the monastery of Vydubychi - This
о вот вопрос монастырь Выдубичи - Это
indeed the place where the wooden idol appeared
действительно место где всплыл деревянный идол
during the Baptism of Russia Is this some kind of myth
во время Крещения Руси Это тип миф
such a legend such a Well these are all legendary
такой легенда такова Ну это все легендарные
testimony Well, how can they be verified in any way
показания Ну как их можно проверить никак
in the lines, the witness here is the only thing possible
в строках свидетель здесь Единственное что можно
say
сказать
Yes
да
[music]
[музыка]
now Moscow and Hungary want us
сейчас москвы и Венгрия хотят нас
share Well, I think this is an exaggeration
поделить Ну я думаю что это преувеличение
that in Hungary Hungary may want something there
что Венгрии Венгрия может что-то там хочет
Orbán comes out with these cards
Орбан выходит с этими там картами что ж
it is wanted there when they say Hungary
оно там хочется когда говорят Венгрия
wants Ukraine wants Ukraine - that's 40
хочет Украина хочет Украина – это 40
millions of people when they say Ukraine
миллионов населения когда говорят Украина
wants And who wants now Russians often
хочет А кто кто хочет сейчас россияне часто
they say Donbas hotel will separate saying
говорят Донбасс хотел отделиться говоря
Donbass wanted to last, who do you have?
Донбасс хотела длиться это вы кого имеете
in mind which tens of thousands of people which in
в виду какие десятки тысяч людей которые в
Donetsk in the 13th year on
Донецку еще в 13-м году на
pro-Ukrainian rallies took place that is
проукраинские митинги выходили т.е.
it is always necessary to specify something
всегда нужно конкретизировать может какой-то
specific Hungarians would like Transcarpathia
конкретные венгры хотели бы чтобы Закарпатье
was a part of Hungary under his authority
было частью Венгрии можно его власти
But there is someone like that
Кто-то такой есть но
Orban definitely wants to, he used to go out there with
Орбан точно хочет он же выходил там из
by this
этим е-е
they, you know, as they want, let him
они е-е как вы знаете как хотят пусть он
probably on that scarf Transylvania
видимо на том шарфике трансильвании
Domalyu Romanians gave A. a cap
прилаживающие румыны дали по шапке А
Transcarpathia wants not to be caught
Закарпатье хочет не надо поймать
Yes
да
describe the monument to the Cossacks in Taman - this
опишите памятник казакам в Тамане – это
what
что
of the Black Sea Cossacks of which Kateryna
черноморскому казачеству которого Екатерина
moved here to
переселила здесь в
so it was. I saw this monumental house there
да был Я там видел этот памятник домик
Lermontova Someone is just standing there
Лермонтова Там кто-то их просто стоит
where is our Morozenko Morozenko
где наш Морозенко Морозенко
says rebooting so we see
говорит перезагружается так вижу мы
exhausted such basic questions Perhaps
исчерпали следующие основные вопросы Возможно
you have any interesting questions or for
у вас есть какие-то вопросы интересные или для
some remarks from the audience
зрителей какие-то реплики
Nikita
Никита
But in principle, I have already put it on the go
Да я в принципе по ходу уже и поставил
sprat
несколько
Vladyslav Shilov came, there is another question
пришел еще вопрос Владислав Шилов
sylobrid finish Me with this question I them
шилобрид добивай Меня этим вопросом я их
I'm nervous, ignored it, but doesn't finish writing
нервою игнорировал но не добивает пишет
Andrew, a question for all bloggers, how are they?
Андрей вопрос ко всем блоггерам как они
they consider it the right thing to do or should do
считают как правильно сделать или нужно
do as the Baltic countries appoint 24
сделать как страны Балтии назначить 24
August is the day of restoration of our
августа днем ​​восстановления нашей
Independence
Независимости
from UNR, I said about this for a long time that we have a day
из УНР я давно Об этом говорил что у нас день
restoration of Independence There is even a video
восстановление Независимости Даже есть видео
old woman, I have repeatedly used it
старенькое я его неоднократно
demonstrated in his videos applied that
демонстрировал в своих видео прикладывал что
the last President of the UNR in exile handed over
последний Президент УНР в экзилии передал
powers of the first president of Ukraine
полномочия первому президенту Украины
therefore we can safely
поэтому мы спокойно можем
believe that we have a recovery day
считать что у нас день восстановления
as we then see it turns out we then
как мы тогда смотрите получается мы тогда
legal successors of the Ukrainian SSR in fact
правопреемники УССР фактически
yes, that is, in fact, two state ones
да есть фактически две государственных
the formation of which is essentially a conflict yes
образование по существу конфликта да
in principle, if you are afraid because
в принципе если у вас страшного потому что
give up what was
отказываться от этого того, что было
made at
сделано при
Ukrainian SSR
УССР
all our parents, grandfathers, great-grandfathers, God forbid
все наши отцы деды ну прадеды Боже пусть
he asks if Bohdan's role is overestimated
он спрашивает не переоценена ли роль Богдана
Khmelnytsky in our historiography
Хмельницкого в нашей историографии
I think, no
Думаю нет
it is necessary to write a work in which we are overestimated
надо пишет труд в котором переоценена мы
let's sit here
здесь сядем
Can Can question So what
Можно Можно вопрос Так что
Do you agree with the position where Nevsky is?
Согласны ли вы с позицией где есть Невского
imsun regarding OUN and Stepan Bandera no
imsun по поводу ОУН и Степана Бандеры нет
short
коротко
it will
это будет
the forest
лесом
we agreed on our technical
мы договаривались своими техническими
questions and does not get into banderoology
вопросами и не лезет в бандероведение Мы
we didn't agree on this before the video
договаривались перед видео об этом не
to speak, but I will say so, but I will have it
говорить но я скажу так вот У меня будет
the next video about Bandera will be there
ближайшее видео о Бандере там будет
literally one short document there i
буквально один краткий документ там я
I will not analyze the entire biography of Benderik
не буду разбирать всю биографию
many people do it for 15 minutes
многие это делают 15 минутных
videos I just read one document
роликах Я просто зачитаю один документ
one single document that will show what happened
один единственный документ который покажет что было
in the head in Bandera That's who Let's say so what
в голове у Бандеры Вот кто Скажем так что
thought Bandera his paradigm of thinking
думал Бандера его парадигму мышления
but already evaluate him as a person and
но уже сами оценивайте его как человека и
I also have a desire to do about
Также у меня есть желание сделать о
Khmelnytsky because Lately I've been me
Хмельницкого потому что В последнее время я уже я
I've been talking about it lately
уже говорю об этом в последнее время
the names of some people were already mentioned there
уже там были названы фамилии некоторые люди
speak about bloodshed
высказываются о кровавости
Khmelnytsky about there as if only him
Хмельницкого о там как как его только
they don't call any Bloody maniac and
не называют какие-то там Кровавый маньяк и
I will have a mass murderer, well, whatever
убийца массовый вот у меня будет ну как будет
I plan to make a video as well
Я планирую сделать видео также
by reading one document which
зачитыванием одного документа
clarify a little the time in which he lived
прояснит немного времени, в котором жил
Khmelnytskyi And those actions of Khmelnytskyi
Хмельницкий И Те действия, которые Хмельницкий
could which to us modern people from our
мог которые нам современным людям с нашей
modern morality and a modern view of
современная мораль и современный взгляд на
the world of action can seem cruel why
мир действия могут показаться жестокими почему
why these actions were taken after all
почему эти действия были предприняты все же
has cause and effect and so on, that's it
имеет причину последствия и так далее
I want to make a video
видео я у меня желание сделать
How do you feel about amateur diggers?
Как вы относитесь к Копачам любителей которые
digging through history with metal detectors
с металлоискателями копают по истории
task
Задание
I wanted to ask this question myself. Well, how are you?
это я сам вопрос хотел задать Ну как ты
behaved as I behave, behave as it is
относился как я отношусь отношусь так что есть
our problems are of course on the state level
проблемы у нас обычно на государственном
levels that the state does not encourage Let's say
равные то, что государство не поощряет Скажем
so somehow, that is, they are one way or another
да как-то ну то есть они так или иначе
they were yes in any way. Well, for example
они были да по-любому вот Ну например
the same data it is encouraged That is there
те же данные это поощряется То есть там
someone left
какой-то ушел
financially and in general, what are you like?
финансово и так вообще что вот ты такой
Well done. Are you there or in the newspaper?
молодец Мы тебя там или в газете ну
conditionally Yes, we will publish that this is there
условно Да опубликуем что вот это там
You found us, supported the museum there, and so on
Нашел ты нас поддержал там музей и так
further
Далее
that is, what is going on at the state level
то есть идет на государственном уровне то, что
indeed, they are not some Diggers, but some
действительно копатели они не какие-то там да какие-то
blacks are running. And this one is just like ours
бегают черные А этот а так как у нас этого
we don't have it, so-and-so redrawn it
нет то у нас это перерисовал такой себе
Let's just say that looting is so-so
Скажем так мародерство такое себе
historical because well that is how what
историческое потому что ну то есть вот как чего
they think black Digger Well, I don't
они мыслит черный Копач Ну я же не
I dig up Scythian graves, for example
раскапываю Вот например могилы скифские то
What kind of black Digger am I there?
я какой же из меня черный Копач я там
I found a coin somewhere in the field
монетку где-то нашел где-то там на поле в
something else to the forest. Well, it's the same, but
лесу еще что-то Ну это же это такое но
in fact, each and every such artifact
на самом деле каждое каждый такой артефакт
That is, Well, there are many cases of what is there
То есть Ну много случаев того что там тот
the very VIOLITY auction - auction Yes, he is
самый VIOLITY аукцион- аукцион Да он
if it was legal, well, if it was caught
если бы легальный ну если бы на нем ловят
there are many such people who catch people
многие такие ну бывают что ловят людей
who are then imprisoned because of this
которых потом еще и сажают на этом из-за этого
there is an auction, that is, something legal there
есть аукцион есть этакое легальченое там
various such artifacts are transmitted
передаются разные такие артефакты бывают
unique, i.e. some golden gold
уникальные то есть какие-то золотые золотые
Belts were sold there
пояса там продавался продавалось
Soyraste communicative, that is, by the way, I am
сокирасте коммуникальная то есть кстати я
I wanted to tell you something about it
вам об этом хотел сказать что
bought some
выкупил какой-то
benefactor of the ax with the trident of the day
благотворитель топора с трезубцем суток
Volodymyr of the time of Volodymyr the Great
Владимир времен Владимира Великого
the prince is a luxurious ax, she is like that
князя это роскошный топор он такой
of the Scandinavian type, you know this
скандинавского типа такая знаете по этому
by extending the blade downwards and on Obukhov on
удлинением вниз лезвия и на Обухов на
What is it called back there?
Как оно называется там сзади на ну
behind there is a knocked out wolf and from the side it seems
позади там выбитый волк, а сбоку кажется
from the side or from above, there may be three tridents from above
сбоку или сверху может сверху трезубец три
as if stylized for this
как бы стилизован под эту
you know this Scandinavian pattern somewhere
скандинавский образец знаете этот там где
snakes intertwine is so characteristic
змеи переплетаются такой характерный
the Scandinavian RCD in silver is everything
скандинавское УЗО серебром оно все оно
everything inlaid with silver is a luxurious thing
все инкрустировано серебром это роскошная вещь
I watched I do not understand why the masses about it
Я смотрел Я не понимаю почему массы об этом
they don't know what kind of ax it is
не знают Это же невероятно топор которого
Probably somewhere in the 10th century
10-го века наверняка где-то
10th century yak with a trident
10-го века с трезубцем
Scandinavian type. Very cool thing and more
скандинавского типа очень крутая вещь а еще
there was one case when the Dude left for himself
был один случай что Чувак пошел себе
to dig up sand something there construction in
накопать песка что-то там строительство в
him some because he went to dig and
его какое-то потому что он пошел накопать и
found the largest hoard of coins of the time
нашел самое большое сокровище монет суток
Volodymyr with tridents in my opinion
Владимира с трезубцами по-моему в
stories, in my opinion, there were dozens of coins
истории по-моему там Десятки монет были
I want them to let the bastards go
вот я хочу чтобы они подлецы разрешают
cultural layer and he gave it to
культурный слой, а он отдал его в
these things are a three-pronged ax
кстати вот эти этот топор трезубцем она
was sold and bought back and handed over
была продана и ее выкупили и передали
The museum is a wonderful person in my opinion
музея это замечательный человек по-моему за
$10,000 or so to the archaeologist
10,000 $ или что-то около того археолога
Zhenya tells you important not only
Женя вам рассказывает важный не только
joke and location and so on
шутка и месторасположение и так далее
The whole essence The whole essence of a person has there well
Вся суть Вся суть человек имеет там ну
the person went somewhere there to make money for himself
человек пошел куда-то там накопать себе
sand just found the coins. She didn't
песка просто и нашла монеты Она же не
it is her fault that she dug there
виновата что она копнула там где
philologists at the expense
филологов с на счет
See for everyone if you find
Вот смотрите для всех если вы находите
Do you have any old ceramics or something?
какую-то керамику древние или вот что-то вы
think that it might be of some interest
считаете что это возможно быть какие-то интересные
there are stories about what to do in this case
истории что делать в этом случае вот есть
contact some local museums in
обращаться к местным каким-то музеям в
first of all if it is something more like that
в первую очередь если это какое-то более такое
Let's say so large-scale, something more like that
Скажем так масштабно какое-нибудь более такое
It's interesting to call life experts
интересное то лайфологов вызвать ну на
in relation to this Skype, it really is there
по этому Скайпу действительно там оно
it was basically found in the sand There is such a thing
его нашли в принципе в песке Там такое
whose is Zhytomyrska or something
чейское есть или что-то такое это Житомирская
area like There really is even there
область вроде Там действительно там даже
probably not dozens, maybe more
пожалуй и не десятки пожалуй Ну больше
there were silversmiths of Volodymyr in general
было сребреников Владимира вообще
unique thing is good that this person
уникальная вещь хорошо что этот человек
passed it on because if not the second one
передала это потому что если бы не второй
found That's somewhere flew somewhere there on
нашел Так это где-то полетел где-то там на
Russia because it is precisely with this ax
Россию потому что как раз с этим топором
it was that they wanted to buy from Russia
было так, чтобы хотели выкупить по России
this ax is indeed from Lviv
как раз этот топор ну львовянин
he is also an archaeologist by profession
также археолог по специальности он это
redeemed and handed them over there for crazy
выкупил и передал они там за безумные
money, the whole problem is not that there
деньги вся проблематика не в том что там
a person takes a metal detector and finds it
человек берет металлоискатель и находит
digs a coin there, a cross there, something
выкапывает там монету крестик там Да что-то
Whatever, and the fact that in this way she is
Что угодно А в том что таким образом она
Well, not always, but sometimes it affects cultural
Ну, не всегда, но иногда это влияет на культуру.
the layer that lies Well, how powerful is this find
лежащий слой Ну как может эта находка
That is, she violates it in this way
То есть она его таким образом нарушает мы я
I was in Dubno of the Rivne region on
вот был в Дубно Ровенской области на
excavations of the monastery alone and there is interesting
раскопках монастыря одна и там интересно
it was like a sea, then the ospreys were like that
было как морской дальше скопы были так
they say Look, this is how you can see that Otaki
говорят Вот смотри так видно что Такие
strips of black earth Like these are like cylinders
полосы чернозема Такие как эти как цилиндры
Yes, it's precisely the pits dug by the eyes, that is
да это именно ямки выкопаны эти т.е.
cultural layer There is completely all His there
культурный слой Там полностью все Его там
it is not there, it is not clear that this one was already there
нет там не ясно что там было уже этот
if so much cultural layer disappears
если такой много культурный слой исчезает
We cannot understand what was there
Мы не можем понять что там было
in general, that is, the problem is not even not
вообще есть проблематика не даже не
facts are worth more though artifacts too
стоит фактах больше хотя артефакты также
so juices and this one are unique like this one
значит такие уникальные как это соки и этот
namely, in the violation of these cultural layers
а именно в нарушении этих культурных слоев
Well, that's kind of good. That's it. Then the question
ну Так как-то хорошо Вот такой тогда вопрос
from a legal point of view, I bought it for myself
с правовой точки зрения вот купил Я себе
land land bought a piece of land somewhere
землю землю где-то купил себе земельку
I visited a house there and planted it for myself
побывал там дом и сажаю себе
and dug a little potato, and here it was about Sribnyak
картошку и копнул а тут о Сребняк
Volodymyr if I I have it begins
Владимира если я У меня начинается
Holoma syndrome and I realistically want to
синдром голая и я при реалисте хочу
to himself that you are at home, am I breaking the law or?
себе его что ты дома я нарушаю закон или
no it is found on my legal land
нет это найдено на моей легальной земле
for example, I am breaking the law because I am not
например вот я нарушаю закон тем что не
informs no one and keeps this one for myself
сообщает никого и оставляю себе эту эту
Silversmith Volodymyr of the 10th century is there
Серебряк Владимир 10-го века там ее
I don't remember which article of the Constitution and
не помню по какой статье Конституции и
they are all facts, all these material things
все факты все эти материальные вещи они
belong to Ukraine. That is, it is state-owned
принадлежат Украине То есть это государственная
property actually what is your land what
собственность фактически что это твоя земля что
not yours, that is, I am obliged to inform
не твоя то есть Я обязан сообщить
who is needed as there as in the Soviet Union
кого надо как там как в Советском Союзе
relevant authorities and inform
соответствующие органы и сообщить
the voter with the competent body Well, but
обратитель с компетентным органом Ну но
this is again, I emphasize that it should
это опять же подчеркиваю что этим должна
engage the state because Well, of course
заниматься государство потому что Ну конечно
stands more on some individual
стоит больше на какие-то индивидуальные
on the basis of the type here Well, one can say Ya
основе типа вот Ну какое-то можно сказать Я
I don't know initiative and initiative
не знаю инициативность да инициативность
actually these people because that's really it
собственно людей этих потому что действительно вот
for some reason, for some reason, a state with a history. Well, me
почему-то почему-то государство с историей Ну я
it is precisely in this regard that she does not want to
именно в этом плане она вообще не хочет
generally directly generally This is very sad
вообще прямо вообще Это очень грустная
situation Dark Face 109 writes philologists
ситуация Dark Face 109 пишет филологи
many earn their finds in general
многие зарабатывают вообще свои находки
have the right to sell Tell me who they are
имеют право продавать Расскажи кто такие
archaeologist scientists, what are they digging and what is it
ученые археологи что они роют И что это
they do not belong. I would call this archaeologists
им не принадлежат Я бы назвал этот археологов
volunteers are lucky because they are there
волонтерам счастья потому что они там
in fact, there is no salary there, it is a salary
фактически зарплаты нет там это зарплатой
don't call it a pension
не назовешь это такое пенсия
there
там
lifeguard, even with some experience there
лайфорогом даже с каким-то там стажем
huge with some there
огромным с каким-то там
trust and yes to him, that is, I know what
доверием и да к нему ну есть знаю что
he is that professional
он там этот профессиональный
an archaeologist, he digs everything, well, let's say it is
археолог он копает все ну Скажем так есть
he can't play nine tones
девятонов он не может банально какие-то
collect to issue the budget Yes from the budget
собрать чтобы выдал бюджет Да из бюджета
some funds were allocated in order to
средства какие-то выделили для того чтобы
Excavation to start is banal, that is
перескопки начать банально какие-то
the expedition should be timed there
там же надо экспедицию таймать на
for some reason, that is, 20 people dig there and give
почему-то ну то есть копает там 20 человек дает
the situation
ситуацию
it's very, very difficult, it's money, it's necessary
очень очень да это деньги это надо этот
there is a little Lina of your wallet, it all goes
там чуть Лины своего кошелька это все идет
yes, slippers, yes, yes, yes, yes, it was still there
да капец е-е да-да-да е-е еще было
I can ask or about
Я могу задать или о
asked the Belarusian cat what he was like
пытался кота Беларусь что вроде вон
read that documents in the Grand Duchy
читал что документы в Великом княжестве
Lithuanian was written in Old Belarusian
литовском писались на старобелорусском
jazyke so how to explain it here in which one
языке то как это объяснить вот на какой
document circulation was spoken in Old Russian
языке было документооборот на Старый русский
Old Ukrainian Old Belarusian is
староукраинский старобелорусский есть
documents that are similar to Nu na Stara
документы которые похожи на Ну на Стару
Belarusian and some in Old Ukrainian
белорусский а есть которые на староукраинском
if we are talking about Russians, it is Mr. Vitaly
если речь идет о россиянах то уже Виталий
mentioned that Muscovites wrote everything described
вспоминал что [ __ ] писали все описано
in Belarusian writing Are they somehow like that?
белорусским письмом Или как-то так и они
But they called us Cherkassy
это все называли Да они нас и Черкассами
called which of them to take if that's why
называли что из них взять если бы потому вот это
Church Slavonic language, but in
церковный славянский язык но в
depending on that 10 days the scribe himself
зависимости от того 10 дней сам писарь
he could use either Ukrainianisms
он мог использовать или в украинизме
or Belarusianisms there and so on Well
или белорусизмы там и так далее
in general, Wikipedia has such a term
вообще есть там Википедии такой термин
Western Russian language from If if
западный русский язык от Если если
other synonyms will be written there verbatim
написать там будет дословно другие синонимы
- the Russian language became the Ukrainian language
- это русский язык стали украинский язык
old Belarusian language
старый белорусский язык
That is, it is actually there
вот есть это фактически оно там
it actually intersects strongly
пересекается сильно оно фактически
a conditional substratum that has not yet come out
условный субстракт еще не вышедший не
Elk is not a Belarusian or Ukrainian language
лося не белорусский не украинский язык как
like that
такая
literary language is only if
литературный язык - это всего лишь если бы
codification of a dialect or set of actions
кодификация диалекта или совокупность действий
the collective of even some there
коллектив даже некоторых там
here is an interesting question asked by matikov
вот вопрос интересным материков спрашивает
questions about the various capitals of the centers as
вопросы по разным столицам центров как
Galicia-Volyn principality became
галицко-волынское княжество стали
Prince Danylo even became the head of the movement
главным в движении князь Даниил даже стал
the king
королем
a broad question for a lecture to say the least
широкий вопрос на лекцию по меньшей мере
How Roman became a father
Как случилось и стало отца Роман
Prince Mstislavovych of Volyn captured
Мстиславович Волынский князь захватил
Halych began to conquer the territory
Галич стал подчинять себе территорию
flesh to Kyiv and so became historians
плоть в Киев так и стало историки
like historically it was served like this
любят исторически так служилось
by conquest plus intercourse
путем завоевания плюс половой
ravaged the land
опустошили земли
former and all Chernihivske
бывший да все Черниговское
Pereyaslavsky Principality of Kyiv
Переяславское Киевское княжество
principalities were devastated before
княжества были опустошены назад
back quite interesting more important often
назад довольно интересно важнее часто
influenced by such ideas and questions
влияют такие идеи от вопроса
restoration of the monarchy in Ukraine is also possible
восстановление монархии в Украине возможно и
I don't get sick with my finger. But I wonder if they can
перстем я не болею Но интересно могут ли
to be a perspective in this and somehow to be
быть перспективы в этом и каким-то быть
pretenders to the throne. Here we often have
претенденты на трон Вот у нас часто в
Ukrainian political opinion some there
украинскому политическому мнению некоторые там
original or marginal emerge that
оригинальные или маргинальные всплывают что
the restoration of the monarchy must be so
вот должно там восстановление монархии так быть
How do you feel about it? Did it survive?
Как вы к этому относитесь
We have a monarchist, for example
уже или нет У нас монархист есть например
Yurchenko is known as such
Юрченко известен такой
exercise intellectual as he is called or
упражнения интеллектуал как его называют или
what a monarchist he is
как он монархист
Well, I just don't see where he can even be
Ну я просто не вижу. Где он можно даже
if you really insist on this idea
если ты действительно настаиваешь на этой идее
to want to restore the And where we dynasty
захотеть восстановить А где мы династию
let's take where to take the monarch
возьмем где монарха взять
Monarchs, someone became And everything And he gave birth
Монархи кто-то стал И все И он родил
wanted The question is what it is for
хотел Вопрос в том для чего это на
this historical as Ivan Vasyliovych
этому историческому как Иван Васильевич
change profession yes
меняют профессию да
so Someone writes the three of us are their loved ones
да Кто-то пишет трое мы их любимых
bloggers in short Alex tsyuryukh someone from
блоггеров короче Алекс цюрюх кого-то из
one does not respect us, we write three of mine
нас не уважает одного пишем три моих
let's love with us once again Yes Oh, I ask Natalya
любимы у нас еще раз Да Ого спрашиваю Наталья
I am interested in learning about the Monomakh hat
Мне интересно узнать о шапке Мономаха
Is this the main female outfit, what is it
Или это головной женский убор что это
in general Monomakh's cap with Arabic
вообще Шапка Мономаха с арабским
elm or something
вязью что ли
the Arab elm is Alexander's helmet
арабской вязи то шлем Александра
Nevsky hats are here. This is my favorite topic
Невские шапки Это моя любимая тема
you only ask a Muscovite for what
их только спрашиваешь москвита за то что
Where did the prisons come from and he immediately
Откуда там тюрьмах шлемах и он сразу
well, it's like the front slimes, yes
все ну это типа как это передние шламы да
helmets
шлемы
That is, there is a helmet of this Well, as it is considered
То есть там есть шлем этого Ну как считается
Oleksandr Nevsky, it was redone
Александр Невского он переработан
Mykhailo Fedorovycha is Oleksiy Mykhailovycha
Михаил Федорович есть Алексей Михайлович
there are their own these boyars and on each of these
есть их этих бояр и на каждом из этих
helmets we see the Arab elm in the plan
шлемов мы видим арабскую вязь в плане
when this religious context ie
когда эта религиозный контекст то есть
for example, you can write some title there
например, может там какой-то титул писать
that there is some kind of prince of Konosetsk
что князь Да какой-то там на это коносецкий
And this is precisely the prayer Yes she is for us
А вот именно молитва Да она нам
in my opinion it is said as they say a prophet
по-моему сказано как они говорят пророк
May Muhammad bless something there
Мухаммед пусть там что-то там благословит
There's something like that on Ivan the Terrible
меня что-то там такое И на Ивана Грозного
Also What
Тоже что
there is a well-known fur coat with a cross
там мехом с крестиком ну известен
a forgery from the time of Ivan the Terrible
фальсификат времен Ивана Грозного
so once again I throw guests' channels into the chats
да еще раз бросаю в чаты каналы гостей
so the block is stored by Nikita January now
да блок храниться Никита январь сейчас
you will definitely subscribe to get some sleep
вам поспать подпишитесь обязательно будет
I myself spy on you very often for them
тебя я сам подсмотрю очень часто за ними
They say something interesting. The question is not
что-то они интересное говорят Вопрос не
on the subject, Yevgeny A
по теме вот к Евгению карась он Евгений А
you have Yevgenia written in what
вот у тебя написано Евгения в чем
the difference is how to distinguish it because
разница как это отличить потому что
the passport is written ie
паспорте написано т.е.
as if cultural
будто культурно
the linguistic origin of the name is one
лингвистическое происхождение имя одно – это
basically one name and that's the way out. Well, I am
по существу одно имя и это выход выход Ну я
there is the Roman Roman Emperor Eugenius
там есть римский римский император Евгений
USS is growing from there. Well, that is Yevgeny
УСС это оттуда все растет Ну, то есть Евгений
Evgeniy Evgeny Well, in principle, there are differences
Евгений Евгений Ну в принципе там разницы
mastered how the passport officers wrote and
освоили как написали паспортистки так и
are called
называются
quickly age and sex
деле быстро возраст и пол под
passport holders to this Soviet joke O
паспортисты на это советские анекдот О
Ira asked a rather interesting question
вот довольно интересный вопрос Ира задала
I can't stand Khmelnytskyi's figure
Хмельницкого фигуру Терпеть не могу
well looted in the west of Ukraine together with
хорошо грабил на западе Украины вместе с
Tatars, in particular, My village, if not me
татарами в частности Моя деревня если я не
I'm wrong, there were such events
ошибаюсь были такие ну события что
for example, they calculated a sauna with the Tatars
например с татарами рассчитывали сауну
Is it true? Is it a myth or is it the norm?
правда ли это миф и это ли норма было в
those times are more like the 17th century
те времена больше это форматно 17 века я
I will tell you more
вам больше скажу
hetmans enslaved Ukrainians
гетманы украинцев в рабство отдавали
this is how Ukrainians were given to khans as slaves
так дарили ханам украинцев в рабство
it was normal at that time and when and with
то было нормально в то время и когда и с
this was fought by the Zaporizhzhya grassroots army
этим боролись войско Запорожское низовое
for example, Sirko in Shevchenko has Yak
например там Сирко у Шевченко же есть как
it is called
оно же называется
this poem I forgot what it is called
этот стих Я забыл как он называется
God knows that a Cossack rises from the grave
Боже о том, что из могилы казак становится
gray hair slanting becomes something there in the middle of the night
седой наклонный становится саму ночью что-то там
walking away singing a song sadly sings as for
уйдя песню пения грустно поет как за
sold the hetman the yoke of Christians sent us
продал гетману иго христиан нас послал
drive this about the fact that Sirko caught up with Fr
погонять это о том, что Сирко догнал о
those who sent
тех, кто послал
sell
продавать
Well, he ordered the Ukrainians into slavery
ну украинцев в рабство и серно приказал
chop them
их порубить
throw away the limbs and chopped body parts
конечности ну изрубленные части тела бросить
in the river so that the earth does not receive them, that is
в В реку чтобы земля их не принимала т.е.
but the Cossacks of the plow, that is, you understand those
вот казаки борону то есть понимаете в те
there were times when there were two Ukraines
времена у нас было бы две Украины была
The Hetmanship was the Zaporizhia army and
Гетманщина и было войско Запорожское и
they are not always
они не всегда
agreed with each other Let's say I
соглашались друг с другом Скажем да Я
I understand correctly
правильно понимаю
Just a state society in principle
Просто сословное общество и в принципе
the clergy was there
вот была там е-е духовенство там
military aristocracy You can say that
военная аристократия Так можно сказать
Is there any kind of nobility in different countries?
там ли дворянство Да какое-то у разных
countries of the world during attention
странах мира во время внимания
Khmelnytsky never mixed
Хмельницкого никогда не смешивались
Cossack units and peasant units in the field
казачьи отряды и крестьянские на поле
Zhenya says he is from the battle of Brest
берестейское сражение Женя говорит есть
it can be seen separately that these are peasant units
отдельно видно что это крестьянские отряды
stood And this is Cossack They never
стояли А это казацкие Они никогда не
got mixed up. We are Cossacks, we are free people, and you
смешались Мы казаки мы свободные люди а вы
Buckwheat and guys, well, it's normal for
гречкосию и ребята ну это нормально для
17th century This is not normal for us
17-го века Это не нормальная для нас
for us, this situation is the norm
для нас вот такая ситуация такая норма
Mr. Vitaly does not want to write
да не хочет ли пан Виталий написать
the new textbook for the school has already written that
новый учебник для школы уже написал что
already wrote two show
уже написал два покажите
how to find
как найти
From 1998 to 2006, I was with the Kryzhanovsky z
1998-2006 у меня был с ледяновским из
My textbook is the eighth grade
моим кладчиком учебник восьмой класс
world history official with reef
всемирная история официальная с рифом
ministries And now for the seventh grade
министерства А сейчас для седьмого класса
history of Ukraine there is a whole team
истории Украины там целый коллектив
authors Chupak Burlak Piskaryev i
авторов Щупак Бурлака Пискарева я
And if we return to the topic of Khmelnytskyi
А если вернуться к теме Хмельницкого
that someone doesn't like him
что там кому-то он не нравится он
you may like it or you may not
может вам нравиться может не нравиться
I hope we are a free country and such
надеюсь мы Свободная страна и такой
we will stay and everyone will have the right
останемся И каждый будет иметь право
to express their opinion about there different ones
высказывать свое мнение относительно там разных
historical characters as he wants but
исторических персонажей как хочет
to deny a huge contribution
отрицать огромный вклад
Khmelnytskyi in his outing
Хмельницкого в своей аутке
national liberation war as we her
национально-освободительной войной как мы ее
we call the formation of Ukraine and
называем в становление Украины и
forget the Cossack revolution in the program
в программе казацкая революция забудь
Nikita Shatan national liberation
Никита шатан национальный освободительна
the war is also a Cossack revolution
война тоже казацкая революция
in general, in general, it's a good day. Well, as they taught
вообще вообще ячным днем ​​Ну как учили
I say so. Well, I actually called it
меня так я говорю Ну я вообще назвал это
there by the Ukrainian-Polish war
там украинско-польской войной
in fact, because in essence it was Ukrainian
на самом деле потому, по сути это было украинский
in essence, as you say, in essence Ukrainian
по существу как вы говорите по существу украинский
state against essentially the Polish state
государство против по существу Польского государства
because we often raised this topic
потому что часто у нас это поднимали эту тему
take the capran and have it on the channel that you have
брать капрана и у себя на канале что у
us constantly rebellion rebellion
нас постоянно восстание восстание
it is called an uprising and thus in
восстание это называют и таким образом у
it is as if our consciousness is laid down that in
нас будто на сознании закладывается что в
we were not a state, but we seemed to be
нас не было государства, а мы будто были
always under someone and always rebelled
всегда под кем-то и вот всегда вставали
although at that time we had a state and this
хотя в это время у нас было государство и это
there was a war of the state against the state, that's why I
была война государства против государства поэтому я
would call it, for example, Cossack
бы это назвал например казацкого
Polish or Ukrainian Polish
польского или украинского польского
Cossacks' search for their place in things
поиск казачества своего места в вещи
Commonwealth when they did not find their own
посполитии когда они не нашли своего
places in ordinary things They found their own
места в вещи посполитые Они нашли свое
place in Muscovy, history has shown that
место в Московии история показала что
made a wrong move, it's on
сделали неправильный шаг это имеете на
keep in mind that they were just that
в виду что просто это были
vassal feudal relations Well, that's right
вассально сюзаряные отношения Ну типа того
yes you can, very very cool question
да можно так очень очень классный вопрос
raised Yulia Dranik why not at school
подняли Юля драник почему в школе не
they mention the settlement of white Croats like this
вспоминают поселения белых хорватов так вот
as I understand it, it is Styl's Horodyshche Da
я так понимаю это стульское Городище Да
In this or as in Lviv Oblast, that is, white people
На этом или как на Львовщине есть белые
Croats Who are they so are they one of the
хорваты Кто они так или являются они одним из
branches of the ancestors of modern Ukrainians Yes or
ветви предков современных украинцев
it is whether and whether they are related
это ли и имеют ли они родственное отношение
to those red Croats who are in Croatia
к тем красным хорватам, которые в Хорватии
actually
собственно
As far as I know, they went there to Croatia
Насколько я знаю они туда в Хорватию
pumped out And became these for themselves
откачивали Да и себе стали этими
by Croats who are Croats that is
хорватами которые хорваты есть
it turns out that it is quite Well, let's say
получается что это совсем Ну Скажем
so in the list of one side of the Chronicler
да в перечне одной стороны Летописца
Well, the chronicler wrote with a pitchfork
ну нет утверждает летописец писал вилами
on the water, as if we hear there, they will trust it
по воде как бы слышим там доверят то
were not difficult to say in my opinion
были не были трудно сказать по-моему
archeology there is a different culture even
археологии там какая-то другая культура даже
Prykarpattia is generally there
Прикарпатье там вообще там на
moved more How many cultures what
перемещено больше Сколько культур что
it promises archaeologists to understand there
разобраться там археологи оно обещает
Carpathians This is all Transcarpathia in the Caucasus
Карпаты Вот это все Закарпатье на Кавказе
each time separately some kind of community
каждый раз отдельно какое-то сообщество
the reason is so you know why so it turns out what
причина так знаете почему так получается чем
people live in the same territory longer
дольше е-е люди живут на одной территории
and they do not move there not this one there Ot
и не переселяются там не этот там
for example, why er Scythians Well, I heard so
например почему е-е Скифы Ну я так слышал
such an opinion that why Scythians and Sarmatians
такое мнение что почему Скифы и сарматы
they lost to the Slavs because the Slavs were fast
проиграли славяном потому что славяне быстро
settled quickly demographically
расселялись быстро быстро демографический
bun and them were similar to each other And why
бун и их походила друг на друга А почему
longer people live in the same territory
дольше люди живут на одной территории
their language is divided into dialects and
их язык на диалекты разделяется и
they are further and further away from each other
они все дальше и дальше отходят друг от друга
one, for example, the dialect of Nikita, which
одного например диалектные Никита которым
Scythian to the Slavs
славянам какой скифов
to simply pass the third century of Anu
чтобы просто прошли третий век Ану
who will remind, well, the third, fourth century
кто напомню ну третий четвертый век
even the Sarmatians of our era Well, you yourself
нашей эры сарматы даже Ну Сама ты
in general, they pass in the third century
вообще переходят еще в третьем веке
BC from the third to the third
до нашей эры с третьего до третьего
ours and the Slavs were bitten, God forbid
наше же славяне проклюнулись дайте Бог
So that somewhere in the sixth century there is a gap
Чтобы где-то в шестом веке, а там разрыв
300 years
300 лет
maybe some Slavs
славяне может какие-то
Well, maybe so. But
Ну может и так Но
And for example, on the territory of the Great Steppe
А например на территории Большой степи
in the south in the east
на юге на востоке
I was not friends after that
дружили после я не было
there were aromas and where is Sarmatian
ароматы были а где там сармата
Slavic wars, that is, in contact
славянские войны то есть у контактов
Some of them were unequivocally against
Какие-то они вступали однозначно против
the Slavs
славянами
culture cannot exist without
культура не может существовать без
agricultural culture
земледельческой культуры
As you can see, the territory is small, but
Какая указа территория небольшая но
dialects of small groups of people They are theirs
диалекты небольшие группы людей Они их
the language is very different and the Slavs
язык сильно отличается а славяне
for example They live on a very large
например Они живут на очень большой
territory but not so much language
территории но языки не так сильно
differ not so much that is
отличаются совсем не так сильно то есть
Conditionally, a Pole understands Ukrainian there too
условно поляк понимает Украинский там еще
after the sagmata, there was a gunnysche, i.e
после сагматов пришлось гунище то есть
they flew there too
гуща прилетели они там тоже
picked up the Slavs and here, that is, exactly
подхватили славян и здесь ну то есть самое
have they more like that Well, I don't think that there
иметь они больше такое Ну не думаю что там
There were some contacts Yes with the Slavs Actually
какие-то были стыки Да со славянами Собственно
it was said when only against the Slavs and
говоря было когда только против славяне и
you say
то скажете
modern history on what converges what
современная история на чем сходится что
Who were the Huns? Not yet
гунны кто такие были Пока так и не
came to an agreement
пришли к согласию
all these peoples were not impressed by this
не захватывали все эти народы это все
there was such a mixture of flow, even as he says
была такая смесь потока даже Как говорит
the author of the channel history of Russia, history knows
автор канала история России история знает
two Hun words and both of them
два гунских слова и оба они
Slavic med medus somehow that's the case
славянские мед медус как-то так и дело
honey is mentioned, I read a fable there
меда упоминается я там читал басня была
really write that Atilla is some kind of there
очень распиши что Атилла это какие-то там
Prince Gatylo is like this
князь Гатило так вот это
fiction Bohdan Gatilov
художественная литература Богдан гатилов
led this myth through fiction
вел этот миф через художественную литературу
Well, I heard about the book somewhere
Кто-то так Ну я слышал о книге где-то там
about Bohdan Gatylo somehow it is there
о Богдане Гатыло как-то там
it is said that he saw Areus these people with interest
называется вот интересно увидел Арея этих
tell me to say that completely Zhenya
скажите мне так сказать полностью Женя
who wrote this
кто написал это
I don't remember Oles Berdnyk, that's all
не помню Олесь Бердник это все
the fantasy of Les Berdnyk
фантазия Леся бердника
And once upon a time there was a bookkeeper, do you remember this one
А еще когда-то был книгин помните такой
there are such topics as Slavyanska
путешественников Там такие темы что Славянская
fertilized by the Simin civilization
симинской цивилизацией оплодотворенная
the capital of which still wrote such fiction
столица которой еще такую ​​фантастику писал что
But it was popular
Но было популярным
Oleksandr Gonchar is a very interesting question
Александр Гончар – очень интересный вопрос.
influenced Masonic lodges to establish
повлияли масонские ложи на установку
Ukraine In general, here they say
Украина Вообще вот у нас когда говорят
masons, this is something so steep
масоны это сразу так что-то такое стремно
that is, in the 19th century at the beginning of the 20th century
вот е-е в 19-м веке в начале XX
all Masonic currents were so popular
так были популярны все масонские течения
how they manifested themselves in Ukraine and
как они у нас проявились в Украине и
were a nerve Maybe there influenced but I I would
были нерв Возможно там влияли но я бы
you corrected were popular were
вас поправил были популярны были
popular you Take modern money
популярные вы Возьмите современные деньги
Ukrainian coins hryvnia and two you
украинские монеты гривну и две вы
find there the Masonic world now that is
найдете там масонский мир сейчас то есть
to say that you were popular is not exactly
говорить что вы были популярны не совсем
they are correct and popular if on
корректны они и популярны если на
our money so far
наших деньгах до сих пор
so that we have this symbol, I don't know what it is
то что у нас есть этот символ не знаю что в
these communities are at least popular with us
нас популярны эти сообщества как минимум
they They have influence enough to
они Они имеют влияние достаточно чтобы
wait for yours on the basis of what you do
чеканить свою на основании чего ты так
you say that it is And why then on ours
говоришь что это А почему тогда на наших
modern eyes
современных глаз От е-е
why on the dollar is all this we in it
почему на долларе это все это мы в этом
reptilian now Why are there reptilian
рептилоидом сейчас Почему Там рептилоидов
just is
просто есть
people soma Hrushevsky was a freemason and
люди сомами Грушевский был масоном и
further, I don't say that there is peace there
далее то что же не говорю что там вот мировое
the government is there
правительство там
accents, who are they, because we have Masons
акценты кто такие потому что у нас масоны
magical university Oksana Kryzhanivska
магический университет Оксана Крыжановская
candidates of historical sciences, here she is with us
кандидаты исторических наук вот она у нас
you need to look for the only flowerpot specialist
единственный специалист по вазонам надо искать
read her articles, then something will become clear
ее статьи читать тогда что-то прояснится
about those masons, but the sect is also closed
о тех масонах но секта закрыта еще и
darker than in archillology directly
темнее чем в архиллогии прямо
and I think that you know it is a cult, not the cult of A
а я думаю что это знаете культ не культ А
how is it called
как это называется
people with some common interests
люди с общими интересами какими-то
you know, maybe they have them there, you know, yours there
знаете Может у них там знаете свои там
er, as the Order of the Templars used to be
е-е как вот раньше были Орден тамплиеров
it's a kind of romance for them, something very special
это какая-то романтика для них что-то очень
interesting question Yuliya Dranik asks why
интересный вопрос Юлия драник спрашивает почему
excavations in Kyiv still do not show any
до сих пор в Киеве не показывают раскопки, которые
are taking place on Poštova Square And what is there
происходят на Почтовой площади И что там
found someone in the know
нашли кто-то в курсе
Why don't they show because they are in this
Почему не показывают потому что они в таком
show them in a stylish way
платяном состоянии их показывать стильно
simply
просто
I say it's all yes, it's not me
я же говорю оно на это все да оно это я не
I know in what condition it is now
знаю в каком сейчас оно состоянии оно еще
was a few years ago in terrible
было несколько лет назад в ужасном
state, despite the fact that the find is there, well, Exactly
состоянии при том что находка там
this complex is unique, it is you
этот комплекс он уникален там это же вы
it was there for ages
там были это целое время
Why Why don't they show such money
Почему Почему не показывают ну такие деньги
Mrs. Oksana will show you, look at which one she is going on
госпожа Оксана покажут смотри идет на какой
deep on Poštova Square lie
глубине вот на Почтовой площади залегают
here is this scarf
вот этот шарф
shallow, I don't remember exactly. Well, order
неглубоко я точно не помню Ну порядок
1.2 m, how much is a meter and a half, I'm sure
1,2 м сколько метр полутора наверное я я
I personally wasn't there, I was just for it
там Лично я там не был я просто за
from this side he watched it very sadly
этим со стороны наблюдал он это очень грустно
and even a stolog, how did I understand there?
и даже столог откуда я там понимал в
the field was built there for 1000 years
поле намело там за 1000 лет там тот
meter So where did this one come from in Kyiv
метр Так откуда в Киеве набрался вот этот
meter of soil
метр грунта
different processes located materials
разные процессы расположен материале
very soft material is not possible here
очень мягкий материал здесь нельзя
build
строить
high-voltage houses are very good
высокоэтажные дома очень ну
light
легко
the outgoing material here washes her
уходящий материал здесь его намывает ее
they washed and will wash and even more so
намывали и будет навать а тем более
Hem the river in a row with a drop
Подол река рядом перепадом
it's all clear
оно же все понятно
everything behind the river will be in order
все что за рекой оно будет на порядок
below What are some of these pluses to myself
ниже Чем там какие-то эти плюс я себе сам
soil specific impact in Kyiv
грунт специфический удар в Киеве
so let's be Yes a little
да давайте будем Да немножко
to round off the last couple of questions of some kind
закругляться последняя пара вопросов каких-то
interesting question yes yes yes What is there?
интересный вопрос да да да Что здесь есть
torture Andrey for us
замучить у нас Андрей
my eyes are already hurting, I look there
у меня как глаза Уж болят я выгляжу там
questions there are questions My eyes are watering
вопросы там вопросы У меня глаза вылизывают
Yes
да
Andriy, let Morozenka ask questions and
Андрей дайте Морозенко задать вопрос и
do not interrupt another sad so basket
не перебивайте в др. грустный да корзинку
ask a question
сдай вопрос
But no, I'm not very sad. Well, I am now
Да нет я не очень грустный Ну у меня теперь
I was also attacked by subscribers
ставишь Мне также подписчики набрасывали
I want questions. I can't answer them all
хочу вопрос Я их не могу все озвучить
I don't have time, so look here is a question about
не успеваю то смотрите вот есть вопрос о
yes, I read all these, what is the difference between them
так вот эти я все читал в чем разница между
events
событиями
1917-1920 to the present
1917-1920 годов с нынешними
such a question
такой вопрос
supported then I wanted to say for the only one
поддержала тогда я хотел сказать на единственную
Russia is now Europe for German tanks
Россию сейчас Европа на немецкие танки
they will go on our land, you know what
поедут по нашей земле знаете в чем
the difference is that we have ZUNR and UNR now united
разница у нас ЗУНР и УНР сейчас объединены
fight together, and in Russia, too, whites and
воюют вместе а в России тоже белые и
the reds also united against us
красные тоже вместе против нас объединились
so that Well then zvenerionr in principle
так что Ну тогда звенерионр в принципе
united, but it was already late, well, the evening
объединились но уже было поздно ну мероприятие
then he supported both Poland and Russia there
тогда поддержал и Польшу и там эту Россию
Yes, what is there, well, what is Soviet
Да какая там ну какая там Советская
was created, that is, they were based on the Soviet one
создавалась то есть они на советского
they were supported by children of Belarus
они Белоруссии же поддерживали дети на
kolchaka And yes
колчака А так
white means they supported all themes
белый то есть они поддерживали всех темы
Unfortunately for Ukraine
Украины к сожалению
the German army was stationed here
немецкое войско здесь стояло
that lost the First World War mountains
что проиграли Первую мировую войну горы
Alex writes his as part of a smile
свои в рамках улыбнуться пишет Алекс
Smityuk Vox is sad and everything Zhenya is like
мусор Вокс грустный и все Женя как
the student is expelled
студента гоняют
[music]
[музыка]
you can see if there are any
смотрите можно так давай если есть какие-то
I asked you a question
дали у тебя вопрос
So it means whether it is possible to identify
Так значит возможно ли идентифицировать
Scythians As the beginning of Ukrainian history we
скифов Как начало украинской истории мы
here, in principle, this topic was discussed
здесь уже в принципе эту тему говорили
I have my Cro-Magnons in my blog
мои кроманьонцев у себя в блоге я
I traditionally start with Ukrainian
традиционно начинаю украинский
Neanderthal in Russian Isovsky
Неандерталец на русском исовском
a person
человеком
I begin the story with Volodymyr from
Я начинаю историю от Владимира от
Russia Russia everything seems to me from there
Руси Русь вот оттуда все мне кажется
everything that is there on the territory of some country
все что там на территории какой-то страны
it is possible in principle
происходит в принципе можно
identify to hide some there
идентифицировать чтобы таями какие-то там
connections were this is our story this is history
связи были это наша история это история
Ukraine what happened in ours
Украина то, что происходило на нашей
territory is the history of Ukraine, simply that
территории это история Украины просто это
not exactly the history of our people, though either
не совсем история нашего народа хотя тоже
I already voiced about it there before
я там уже об этом высказывался
genetic connection By the way in history
генетична связь Кстати в истории
Maybe you watched some Turkeys there
Турции вот может вы там смотрели какие-то
they will go to them, Istanbul is the same
пойдут как у них Стамбул это же
They make history in Constantinople
Константинополь вносят историю
let's say that the empire contributes have
скажем той империи вносит должны
Of course they say that at least this one
Конечно они говорят что хоть этот
was stanomich so
было станомично так
or what
или как
Well, Istanbul once was
Ну Стамбул – это же когда-то был
Constantinople later and then they came
Константинополь потом а затем пришли
Turks and it happened
Турки и это произошло
writing the history of the state So it is now
написание истории государства Так что оно сейчас
This does not mean that Turkey is Muslim
Турция мусульманская это же не значит
that they start the videosman there first
что они видеосмана там первого начинают
write history they write territory that
писать историю они пишут территорию что
The Onian Greeks lived here and there
Здесь жили там и онийские греки там
Byzantine Empire
Византийская империя
what are they writing, what is history
что они пишут что вот история
Constantinople is simply their story
Константинополя – это их история просто
the Greeks write that this is their history of the Turks in
греки пишут что это их история турки в
its history includes it normally
свою историю включает это нормально
each has its own national history
каждого своя национальная история
Byzantines of Nematov
византийцев нематовского
let's have another question and you have a question
давайте есть еще вопросы да у тебя вопрос
come on
есть Давай
cool question, are there any documents?
классный вопрос, есть ли документы?
which confirm Ukrainian origin
которые подтверждают украинское происхождение
Emelyana Pugacheva
эмельяна Пугачева
[music]
[музыка]
there is something there, he had some clues
там что-то есть у него какой-то зацепки были
In my opinion, something happened there with Ukraine
там с Украиной по-моему оказалось что
like there, Omelyan is actually Omelyan, that is
типа там Емельян на самом деле Емельян то есть
he was a Cossack, he had it anyway
он же казаком был он по-любому имел
somehow you can say that Well somehow
как-то можно так сказать Ну как-то
indirectly gave contact
косвенно дал контакт
bandages Yes and thus there already in
повязки Да и таким образом там уже в
there was an uprising
него Восстание было
1774 ended, and in 1070, 1775 was destroyed
1774 г. закончилось а в 1070 г. 1775 г. уничтожают
Zaporizhzhia, Sich, and so on
Запорожскую Сечь и вот типа еще какие-то там
maybe connection maybe still maybe still
может связь может все же может все же
after all, of course, more is more
таки ну это конечно что больше больше
fantasies
фантазии
there is still a question
еще вопрос есть
if Kievan Rus had survived to what it was
если бы Киевская Русь выстояла до которой была
story now If you were different
история сейчас Если бы ты другой
another
другой
we can only guess this one
это мы можем только догадывать этот
guess
догадываться
each a small replica if for
каждый небольшую реплику если бы для
the audience will say something nice to
зрителей что-то приятное скажет на
completion
завершение
it was nice to meet interesting people
приятно было встретиться с интересными
people are so really interesting to sit
людьми так действительно интересно сидеть
to talk about such topics especially to me as
разговаривать на такие темы особенно мне как
not a specialist by specialists
не специалисту специалистами
specialists
специалистами
I'm talking about guests, I'm talking about Osi
я же говорю о гостях я же говорю об Вот
as a guest on Andriy Popika's channel
на гости на канале Андрея попика назад
here, because I'm far away, I'll tell the story
вот потому что я далеко я скажу Да я историю
I'm looking more at yours, yes, yes, yes
больше по вашим там смотрю да Ага да
in short, what about Novgorod Aga like this
что короче что о Новгороде Ага так
to tell That's all I'm already now so what
рассказать Да все Я уже теперь так что вот
This is my story
Это моя история
Well, I would like to thank Andrii, of course
Ну я хотел бы поблагодарить обычно Андрея
thank you for inviting me again
попику за то что снова меня пригласил для
it is an honor for me, a great honor to be
меня это вообще честь большая честь быть
here together with boxing Veitatis sichnym
вот вместе с боксом вейтатисом сечным
popikom such if such had such
попиком такой если бы такой иметь такую
The discussion is interesting. In fact, I would like to
дискуссию интересную На самом деле Я бы хотел бы
to discuss something else. Well, there you go
обсудить что-то другое. Ну, вот и все.
got tired
устали
in general
вообще
I think it was
считаю что была
I had a dialogue with my best man
был диалог с моим кумом январским был
dialogue with sensei Vitaly and there was a dialogue with
диалог с сенсеем Виталием и был диалог с
To my colleague Andrii, thank you very much
коллегой Андрею очень спасибо
to the subscribers for also crushing Osi
подписчикам за то что тоже задавил
there are quite a lot of such interesting questions If
такие интересные вопросы достаточно много Если
I apologize for not having time to voice any of them
не успел какие-то озвучить то Извиняюсь
thank you all especially guys especially
спасибо всем особенно ребятам особенно
Andriy who brought us all here Well
Андрея которых нас всех здесь собрал Ну
and let's respect each other because we are worth it guys
и чтимся потому, что мы того достойны ребят
thank you
Спасибо
Thank you all thank you thank our
Спасибо всем благодарим благодарим наших
energy workers who really give us light
энергетикам которые реально нам свет в
In January, they didn't turn off the lights like that for me
январе свет не выключили так У меня
turned on And you have so that everyone everyone who
включили И у вас так что всем всем кто
watched us and is watching. In fact, I do
нас смотрел и смотрит На самом деле Я так
I think, damn it, that won't be a topic
думаю А блин ну вот это тема не будет
quite interesting plus We communicate
совсем интересная плюс Мы общаемся
will not watch much in Ukrainian
украинском много не будет смотреть
People are watching, watching a lot
смотрят люди смотрят большое вот
let's say no less than my usual ones
скажем не меньше чем и такие обычные мои
broadcasts with stupid Russians
эфиры с глуповатыми это мы там россиянами
yes and it's pretty cool yes because I am
да и это довольно классно так как я
I will say that any changes in
скажу так что любые изменения в
society begins with changes in
обществе начинаются с изменений в
Heads So when we have something for ourselves
Головах Да когда мы для себя что-то
we realize when we feed on something
осознаем когда мы живемся каким-то
becomes an intellectual candidate for us
интеллектуальным кандидатом у нас становится
everything is very cool. I thank everyone very much
всего очень классно Я очень благодарю всех кто
er, today was Yes, I think we are still
е-е сегодня был Да я думаю мы еще
we will do some such measures by the way
будем делать какие-то такие меры кстати
next Saturday, February 18, we will have a
следующую субботу 18 февраля у нас будет на
The channels are girlish dvizh yes. That is, they will be
канале е девичий двое
bloggers or tourist girls too
блоггеры или девушки-туристки тоже
invite, I will announce it in a few days
приглашаю я анонсирую на днях его
guys historians I think we will still be in
ребят историков Я думаю мы еще будем в
take different formats because
разных форматах е-е брать потому что
history is, let's say, Terra for us
история – это такая скажем для нас Терра
Incognita is for such people as and
Инкогнито так для вот таких людей как и
are Not historians so and even when you
есть Не историками так и даже когда ты
can you hear any such grains in you already?
слышишь какие-то такие крупинки у тебя уже
it seems that you met there, well, let's say
кажется что ты там узнал е-е ну скажем
great great wisdom so therefore now
великую великому мудрость так поэтому сейчас
let's let the guests go and continue
отпустим гостей и продолжим дальше
our stream is still recorded with a troll
наша стрим же там еще троллеточкой запись
there will be a stream for those who could not watch
стрима будет кто не смог посмотреть
He will definitely stay like that Plus
обязательно Он останется да Плюс
I will post this recording separately in a separate video
отдельно я выложу эту запись отдельным видео
so that everyone can enjoy themselves
чтобы все все смогли насладиться так что
Thank you guys very much for what you found
очень спасибо вам е Ребята что нашли
opportunity despite there problems with
возможность несмотря на там проблемы с
Someone prepared a generator with light
светом кто-то подготовил генератор кто-то
it is so that Glory to Ukraine
это так что Слава Украине